          CHARLES T. R. WILSON

On the cloud method of making visible ions and the 
        tracks of ionizing particles
         Nobel Lecture, December 12, 1927

In September 1894 I spent a few weeks in the Observatory which then exist- 
ed on the summit of Ben Nevis, the highest of the Scottish hills. The won- 
derful optical phenomena shown when the sun shone on the clouds sur- 
rounding the hill-top, and especially the coloured rings surrounding the sun 
(coronas) or surrounding the shadow cast by the hill-top or observer on mist 
or cloud (glories), greatly excited my interest and made me wish to imitate 
them in the laboratory.
 At the beginning of 1895 I made some experiments for this purpose - 
making clouds by expansion of moist air after the manner of Coulier and 
Aitken. Almost immediately I came across something which promised to be 
of more interest than the optical phenomena which I had intended to study. 
Moist air which had been freed from Aitken's dust particles, so that no cloud  
was formed even when a considerable degree of supersaturation was pro- 
duced by expansion, did appear to give a cloud if the expansion and con- 
sequent supersaturation exceeded a certain limit. A quantitative expansion 
apparatus (Fig. 1) was therefore made in which given samples of moist air 
could repeatedly be allowed to expand suddenly without danger of con- 
tamination, and in which the increase of volume to be made could be adjust- 
ed at will.
 It was found that there was a definite critical value for the expansion ratio 
(viv,= 1.25) corresponding to an approximately fourfold supersaturation. 
In moist air which had been freed from Aitken's nuclei by repeatedly form- 
ing a cloud and allowing the drops to settle, no drops were formed unless the  
expansion exceeded this limit, while if it were exceeded, a shower of drops 
was seen to fall. The number of drops in the shower showed no diminution 
however often the process of producing the shower and allowing the drops 
to fall was repeated. It was evident then that the nuclei were always being 
regenerated in the air. A note describing these experiments was read before 
the Cambridge Philosophical Society in May 1895.
 Further experiments with somewhat more elaborate apparatus (Fig. 2)

          CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD    195





















                Fig_ 1.
which allowed of more sudden expansion showed that there was a second 
critical expansion corresponding to an approximately eightfold supersatura- 
tion of the vapour. With expansions exceeding this limit, dense clouds were 
formed in dust-free air, the number of drops in the cloud increasing with 
very great rapidity as the expansion was increased beyond it and giving rise  
on account of their small and uniform size to very beautiful colour phenom- 
ena. The number of drops for expansions between the two limits remained 
small - the resulting condensation resembling a shower of rain rather than a  
cloud. The results were not essentially different in the various pure gases 
tried - although the expansion required to produce a given supersaturation 
was naturally different.
 While the obvious explanation of the dense clouds formed when the sec- 
ond supersaturation limit was exceeded was that here we had condensation 
occurring in the absence of any nuclei other than the molecules of the vapour 
or gas - those responsible for the rain-like condensation which occurred 
when the supersaturation lay between the two limits from the first, excited

196                   1927 C.T.R.WILSON

























                          Fig.2.
my interest. The very fact that their number was so limited and yet that they 
were always being regenerated, together with the fact that the supersatura- 
tion required indicated a magnitude not greatly exceeding molecular dimen- 
sions, at once suggested that we had a means of making visible and counting 
certain individual molecules or atoms which were at the moment in some 
exceptional condition. Could they be electrically charged atoms or ions?*
  In the autumn of 1895 came the news of Rontgen's great discovery. At the 
beginning of 1896 J. J. Thomson was investigating the conductivity of air 
exposed to the new rays - and I had the opportunity of using an X-ray tube 
of the primitive form then used which had been made by Prof. Thomson's 
assistant Mr. Everett in the Cavendish Laboratory. I can well recall my 
delight when I found at the first trial that while no drops were formed on 
expansion of the cloud chamber when exposed to X-rays if the expansion 
were less than 1.25, a fog which took many minutes to fall was produced
* The striking effect of point discharges on condensation in a steam jet had been attrib-
uted to ions by H. v. Helmholtz and Richarz.

                   CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD                     197
when the expansion lay between the rain-like and cloud-like limits; X-rays 
thus produced in large numbers nuclei of the same kind as were always 
being produced in very small numbers in the air within the cloud chamber.
  A short note describing this experiment was communicated to the Royal 
Society in March 1896.* The full paper containing the detailed account of 
the measurement of the two cloud limits in different gases was communi- 
cated a year later.
  During the following two years I investigated by means of the expansion 
apparatus the condensation nuclei produced in gases by X-rays, by the newly 
discovered uranium rays, by ultraviolet light, by point discharges and other 
agents.
  The purely ionizing agents all produced nuclei, identical as regards the 
minimum supersaturation required to cause water to condense upon them.
  The condensation nuclei produced by these ionizing agents were shown to 
be indeed themselves the ions by their behaviour in an electric field. They 
could be completely removed by applying an electric field before expansion 
- so that no cloud was formed.
  Uncharged nuclei, not removable by a field, were also found to be pro- 
duced in various ways and their properties were investigated.
  A paper describing these investigations was communicated to the Royal 
Society in the autumn of 1898.
  The following winter was occupied in studying separately the phenomena 
of condensation on positive and negative ions. It was found that the meas- 
urement of the least expansion required to condense water in ionized air or 
other gas had all been concerned with the negative ion; to catch the positive 
ion the expansion ratio v,/v„ had to exceed a limit of about 1.31, correspond- 
ing to an approximately sixfold supersaturation instead of the fourfold super- 
saturation required by the negative ion.
  This paper marked the completion of a stage in my work, the behaviour 
of ions as condensation nuclei. It was now possible to make visible the in- 
dividual ions and to distinguish between positive and negative ions.
  This found its immediate application in the determination of the charge 
carried by an ion by Thomson and later by H. A. Wilson. The method used 
by the latter of partially balancing the weight of a charged drop by a known 
electric field and determining the change in the rate of fall did not however

* Richarz about the same time described the action of X-rays on condensation in the
steam jet.

198           1927 C.T.R.W1LSON
really depend essentially on the charge being due to condensation on an ion; 
and Millikan, whose earlier experiments were made by H. A. Wilson's 
method, soon abandoned the use of water drops and the expansion method.
 It is, I think, of some interest that the value of the elementary charge <<e>>,  
deduced directly from the degree of supersaturation required to cause nega- 
tive ions to grow into visible drops, is 4.9 x 101° e.s.u.; it agrees within i 
per cent with Millikan's accurately determined value.
 My own researches at this time were directed in another direction. Since 
the nuclei responsible for the rain-like condensation in air not exposed to 
known ionizing agents require just the same degree of supersaturation to 
make water condense upon them as do the ions produced by X-rays and 
other ionizing agents, it seemed almost certain that they also are ions. Exper- 
iments were therefore made to find if there was a measurable conduction of 
electricity through air in a closed vessel containing dust-free air. These led at 
once to positive results, and proved that the air in a closed vessel is always 
ionized. Quite independently and approaching the matter from a different 
side, Geitel was working at the subject in Germany and arrived at the same 
conclusion; his paper was published very shortly before mine. My own ex- 
periments were performed on a small scale, the method used being one after- 
wards very largely employed, in which the rate of loss of charge was meas- 
ured from an insulated system consisting of a short metal rod with a gold 
leaf attached which was suspended in an ionization chamber in such a way 
that the possibility of leakage along the supports was eliminated.
 These experiments were carried out in 1900, and they led me naturally to 
further experiments on conduction in closed vessels, to the direction of radio- 
active matter carried down by rain and snow, to the direct measurement of 
the current between the atmosphere and the earth, and to the study of 
atmospheric electricity generally.
 With the exception of some experiments published in 1904 proving di- 
rectly that the nuclei causing the ordinary rain-like condensation are remov- 
able by an electric field and are therefore ions (an experiment which required 
for success a somewhat larger expansion apparatus than that which had been 
used in the condensation experiments on the ions produced by X-rays) my 
experimental work on condensation phenomena was not resumed for many 
years.
 Among the experimental work on the subject carried out by others in this 
period, in addition to the determination of the electronic charge, that on 
condensation phenomena in other vapours than water by Przibram and by

          CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD    199
Laby should be mentioned. These investigations showed that water vapour 
is quite exceptional in condensing more readily on the negative than on the 
positive ion; a connection between the relative efficiency of the positive and  
negative ions and the sign of the electrical charges developed on splashing - 
the Lenard effect - was established.
 Towards 1910 I began to make experiments with a view to increasing the 
usefulness of the condensation method.
 I had from the time of my first experiments on condensation of water 
vapour on the ions had in view the possibility of determining the ionic 
charge by a direct method, in which the ions carrying a known charge were 
to be made visible by condensation, photographed and counted. The plan 
which I had in view on resuming the work was that of measuring an inter- 
mittent current from a negatively charged plate exposed to ultraviolet light 
within the cloud chamber, thus obtaining a stream of ions divided into 
groups, and finding the number of ions per group by the condensation 
method.
 Again in the years which had elapsed since my earlier experiments, ideas on 
the corpuscular nature of cc- and a—rays had become much more definite, and 
I had in view the possibility that the track of an ionizing particle might be 
made visible and photographed by condensing water on the ions which it 
liberated. As I succeeded in this latter aim, and Millikan had by this time 
rendered the other project unnecessary, the determination of "e", by the
method of direct counting of drops was never carried out.
 Much time was spent in making tests of the most suitable form of expan- 
sion apparatus and in finding an efficient means of instantaneous illumination  
of the cloud particles for the purpose of photographing them. In the spring 
of 1911 tests were still incomplete, but it occurred to me one day to try 
whether some indication of the tracks might not be made visible with the 
rough apparatus already constructed. The first test was made with X-rays, 
with little expectation of success, and in making an expansion of the proper 
magnitude for condensation on the ions while the air was exposed to the rays 
I was delighted to see the cloud chamber filled with little wisps and threads 
of clouds - the tracks of the electrons ejected by the action of the rays. The  
radium-tipped metal tongue of a spintharoscope was then placed inside the 
cloud chamber and the very beautiful sight of the clouds condensed along 
the tracks of the a-particles was seen for the first time. The long thread-like 
tracks of fast a—particles were also seen when a suitable source was brought 
near the cloud chamber.

200          1927 C.T.R.WILSON
 Some rough photographs were obtained and were included in a short 
communication to the Royal Society made in April 1911.
 The summer of 1911 was occupied in designing improved apparatus. The 
expansion apparatus (Fig. 3) was constructed in the workshop of the Caven- 
dish Laboratory and is the one which I have had in use up to the present 
time. In the winter which followed, the photographs were obtained which 
formed the basis of a paper communicated to the Royal Society in the fol- 
lowing June (1912).
 The essential conditions to be fulfilled if good pictures of the tracks are to 
be obtained are mainly these. The expansion must be effected without stir- 
ring up the gas; this condition is secured by using a wide, shallow cloud 
chamber of which the floor can be made to drop suddenly and so produce 
the desired increase of volume. The cloud chamber must be freed not only 
from "dust" particles, but from ions other than those produced by the 
ionizing particles under observation; an electric field maintained between 
the roof and floor of the cloud chamber serves this purpose.
 For the purpose of obtaining sharp pictures of the tracks, the order of 
operations has to be: firstly, the production of the necessary supersaturation  
  by sudden expansion of the gas; secondly, the passage of the ionizing par-


















                Fig.3.

         CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD  201
titles through the supersaturated gas; and finally, the illumination of the 
cloud condensed on the ions along the track.
 Perhaps the most important purpose that the photographs obtained at this 
time served, was to confirm, in a way which was free from ambiguity, con- 
clusions which had already been reached by less direct means and which in 
some cases, but not in all, had come to be generally accepted.
 I remember showing W. H. Bragg one of the first good pictures of a— 
ray tracks very shortly after it was obtained. He at once showed me a dia- 
gram which he had just published showing examples of what he considered 
likely forms for the paths of a— rays. The similarity between the actual pho- 
tograph and Bragg's ideal picture was astonishing. (Lantern slides from pho-  
tographs of a-particle cloud-tracks taken at this time were shown - Figs. 4 
and 5.)






               Fig. 4.




               Fig. 5.








               Fig. 6.
 The tracks of electrons were of remarkable straightness when the velocity 
was high, but slower electrons (Fig. 6) showed both sudden deflections

202         1927 C. T. R. WILSON
through large angles and gradual deviations due to an accumulation of small 
deflections - Rutherford's single and compound scattering. Both types of 
scattering were also shown in the last part of the course of the u,particles.
 The pictures of the clouds condensed in air exposed to a beam of X-rays 
showed perfectly clearly that the primary effect of the rays is to eject elec-  
trons with considerable velocity from atoms in the path of the beam, 
and that the ionization is due to the action of these secondary /3-particles. 
This was in accordance with the conclusions at which W. H. Bragg had 
arrived.
 Information as to the nature of the ionization by /3-particles was afforded 
by the photographs (e.g. Fig. 6). As was stated in the paper published in 
1912, the ions along the track of a A-particle occur partly in pairs, partly in 
groups; and the groups were interpreted as indicating that in certain cases an  
electron ejected from an atom by a A-particle may itself have energy enough 
to ionize. This result appeared to be overlooked in later discussions as to the 
nature of ionization by A-particles.
 Further photographs were taken in the winter of 1912-1913, especially 
illustrating the effects of X-rays. Some of these were exhibited at lectures 
before the Royal Institution and the French Physical Society, and published 
in their journals. Among these were pictures showing the effects of placing 
a sheet of metal, e.g. silver (Fig. 7), in the path of a beam of X-rays. These  
showed very clearly the absorption by the screen of the primary radiation; 
and the absorption by the air of the characteristic radiations from a copper 
or silver screen was also shown by the clouds condensed along tracks of the 
electrons which they ejected.
 The tracks of the electrons ejected from a thin copper screen as a result of 
the absorption of the primary X-rays was also well shown (Fig. 8); the ex- 
cess of the number ejected on the side of emergence being conspicuous. In 
obtaining the pictures which best showed this effect, the intensity of the 
radiation was reduced by introducing a plate of aluminium about 1 cm in 
thickness which removed especially the less penetrating rays. A very in- 
teresting feature appears in these photographs. It is described in the con- 
cluding paragraph of the Journal de Physique paper:
  "A great number of the rays emitted by the copper and the air under the 
influence of the X-rays are extraordinarily long; some attain a length which 
in air at atmospheric pressure corresponds to nearly three centimetres. It 
should be added, however, that on the path of the primary X-rays one can 
see a large number of little patches of cloud, which perhaps represent the

          CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD  203
paths of exceedingly short cathode rays, and of which the interpretation 
requires further investigation."
 These very short tracks, we now know, are due to the Compton effect; 
they are the tracks of recoiling electrons, each of which has scattered a quan- 
tum of radiation.
 At this stage of the work, some stereoscopic pictures of cloud tracks were 
obtained; and the advantages of such virtually three-dimensional pictures 
were so apparent that henceforth this method was exclusively used. A num- 
ber of stereoscopic pictures of a-ray tracks and of the tracks of electrons 
ejected by X-rays had been obtained when war broke out.
 Work on the tracks was entirely laid aside during the war. When it was 
resumed (at the Solar Physics Observatory, to which I was now attached) it 
was some time before good pictures were obtained, not till the autumn of
























                Fig. 7.

204  1927 C.T.R.WILSON

CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD205

      Fig. 9.


      Fig. io.

206           1927 C.T.R.WILSON
1921. A number of stereoscopic pictures of a-ray tracks were then obtained 
with some thorium emanation in the cloud chamber; some of these pictures 
were of interest and were published in November 1922. They showed well, 
for example (Figs.9 and 10), the separation by an electric field of the positive 
and negative ions liberated along the track of an cc-particle which traversed 
the cloud chamber before expansion; the two associated tracks of a-particles 
from an atom of thorium emanation and from the resulting thorium A 
atom; the track of the recoiling atom which has ejected an a-particle; and 
the tracks of 6— rays (electrons ejected by the cc-particle with velocity com- 
parable with its own) projecting from the initial portions of cc-ray tracks. 
The tracks of 6— rays due to a-rays in hydrogen had been photographed some 
years before by Bumstead in America.









                 Fig. II.

 The experiments on the effects of X-rays and of the electrons ejected by 
them, which had been interrupted by the war, were now resumed, and a 
number of stereoscopic pictures were obtained between December 1921 and 
July 1922. These contained a large amount of material for study and the re- 
sults were not ready for publication till June 1923. When the cloud chamber 
is momentarily traversed by a beam of X-rays of suitable intensity a picture 
(Fig. 1 i) is obtained (in three dimensions if the stereoscopic method is used) 
of the tracks of all the electrons ejected from a given volume of the gas by 
the action of the X-rays, primary and secondary. An examination of the 
picture shows at once : ( 1) the point of origin of each ray (electron track); 
(2) its initial direction (i.e. the direction in which an electron has been ejected 
from its parent atom by the action of the radiation) ; (3) its range or total 
length of its path; (4) the form of the track, its sudden or gradual bends, 
and the number and direction of emission of any secondary rays (branch- 
es); and (5) the variation of ionization along the track; under favourable

           CLOUD CHAMBER METHOD   207
conditions the number and distribution of the ions along the tracks may be 
obtained by direct counting.
 The general results obtained can hardly be indicated otherwise than by 
showing examples of the photographs. Unfortunately I am not able to show 
them stereoscopically on the screen.
1. The first picture (Fig. 12) shows the absolutely straight track of a fast 
electron, and the devious tracks of electrons of which the energy corresponds 
to less than about 20,000 volts.
2. This (Fig. 13) shows the track of an electron of moderate energy: the 
straightness of the initial portion - a deviation through a large angle as a re- 
sult of a close approach to the nucleus of an atom - the increasing curvature 
of the track and increasing ionization as the velocity diminishes.
3. Here (Fig. 14) the primary electron has ejected from an atom a sec- 
ondary electron with energy enough to form a conspicuous branch track.
4. This (Fig. 15) is the track of a very fast electron passing through air at 
rather low pressure. In this picture the drops condensed on positive and nega- 
tive ions are individually visible, and occur sometimes in pairs, sometimes in 
groups. The electron ejected from an atom by the primary 13-particle has in 
many cases emerged with insufficient energy to produce further ionization; 
in other cases the energy of the ejected electron has been sufficient to produce 
one or more additional pairs of ions by collision.
5. In a large number of cases (e.g. Fig. 16) while the individual ions could 
not be counted, it was easy to determine the number of groups, i.e. the pri- 
mary ionization or number of atoms from which an electron was ejected 
per cm of path.
6. This (Fig. 17) shows the tracks of electrons ejected by the K-radiations 
from silver.
7. The next picture (Fig. 18) shows the tracks of those ejected under iden- 
tical conditions by the K-rays from copper.
 From data such as those contained in these two pictures it was possible to 
measure the ranges of electrons of known initial energy. The range in air 
was found to be 1 cm for an electron of about 21,000 volts, and to vary 
according to Whiddington's law of the fourth power of the velocity. This 
result was utilized in determining the primary ionization for electrons of ap- 
proximately known velocity.
8. The next picture (Fig. 19) was obtained by passing a very narrow beam 
of hard X-rays through a thin copper plate. Only two tracks appeared in 
the photograph, that of an electron ejected from the copper by the primary

208           1927 C.T.R.WILSON
beam, and a short one, in the air outside the primary beam, of range cor- 
responding to ejection of an electron by copper K-radiation. We almost cer- 
tainly have here the tracks of the copper K-electron whose ejection was fol- 
lowed by the emission of a quantum of copper K-radiation, and of the elec- 
tron ejected from nitrogen or oxygen as a result of the absorption of this 
same quantum of copper K-radiation.
9. A quite similar picture (Fig. 20) obtained with a narrow beam of hard 
X-rays passing through a platinum plate.
10. Similarly related tracks may occur, both of which have their origin in 
the air. This picture (Fig. 21) shows the most common case (one independ- 
ently discovered by Auger and explained, and very thoroughly investigated 
by him). Here both tracks start from the same atom; the K-radiation (or the 
energy which might have been spent in emitting it) being used in ejecting 
an outer electron from the atom from which the X-rays had ejected a K- 
electron.
 The remaining pictures (Figs. 22, 23, and 24) show the cloud tracks ob- 
tained when horizontal beams of X-rays traversed the cloud chamber from 
right to left. They show, as some of the pictures obtained in 1913 had al- 
ready indicated, that two classes of rays are produced by such rays, giving 
<< long>> tracks and <<short>> tracks.
 A <<long>> track is the track of a photoelectron, i.e. of an electron ejected 
as the result of absorption of a quantum of X-radiation. The number of short 
tracks was found to be very small relatively to that of the long tracks when 
the wavelength of the incident radiation is as great as one angstrom. It in- 
creases rapidly as the wavelength diminishes, and for short wavelengths the 
number greatly exceeds that for the long tracks. At the same time the short 
tracks which are mere <<sphere tracks>> when they are due to the longer waves 
become <<fish tracks>>; they begin to have a measurable range, and their ap- 
pearance shows that they are due to electrons ejected nearly along the direc- 
tion of propagation of the primary beam.
 It was pointed out in the 1923 paper that the phenomena relating to these 
tracks supported A. H. Compton's theory of the scattering of X-rays, and 
that they are in all probability just the tracks of the recoiling electrons which  
according to this theory have scattered individual quanta of radiation.
  It was pointed out by Compton that the relative numbers of the short and 
long tracks for a given wavelength of the incident radiation in these pho- 
tographs are in agreement with the ratio between the scattering and absorp- 
tion coefficients, and that this in itself furnishes strong support for his theory

