ELECTRONIC IMAGING OF IONIZING 
RADIATION WITH LIMITED AVALANCHES 
IN GASES

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1992
GEORGES C HARPAK
CERN, Geneva, Switzerland





Detecting and localizing radiation is the very basis of physicists' work in a 
variety of fields, especially nuclear or subnuclear physics.
 Certain instruments have assumed special importance in the understand- 
ing of fundamental phenomena and have been milestones in the building up 
of modern theories. They make up a long list: the ionization chamber, the 
cloud chamber, Geiger-Muller counters, proportional counters, scintilla- 
tion counters, semiconductor detectors, nuclear emulsions, bubble cham- 
bers, spark and streamer chambers, multiwire and drift chambers, various 
calorimeters designed for total absorption and then measurement of parti- 
cle energy, Cherenkov or transition radiation counters designed to identify 
or select particles, and many other detectors, some very important examples 
of which are still being developed. However, some of this equipment has 
become obsolete as physicists' requirements have changed. Wire and drift- 
chambers, introduced in 1968, met the then requirements of physicists, 
whereas the properties of the most productive detectors available at the 
time, mainly bubble and spark chambers, were no longer capable of meet- 
ing those needs.
 Multiwire chambers gave rise to further developments in the art of 
detectors, of which some are highly innovative. Most high-energy physics 
experiments make use of these methods, but their application has extended 
to widely differing fields such as biology, medicine, and industrial radiology. 
 Our study of multiwire proportional chambers, which began in 1967, was 
triggered by the problems with spark chambers which then faced us. The 
latter, introduced in 1959 by Fukui and Myamoto, beautifully supplement- 
ed the bubble chamber. Whereas the latter was still peerless in the quality of  
the information which it provided and from which one single exposure 
could on its own lead to an interesting discovery, the spark chamber gave a 
repetition rate more than 100 times higher. Moreover, as it had a memory 
of almost 1 p, s, the instrument could be triggered only for events selected by 
faster auxiliary counters, making it possible to address the study of phenom- 
ena which occurred much more rarely in very high-energy interactions. 
Nevertheless, the need to store the information on photographic films led

24             Physics INIZ

to a bottleneck: beyond a few million photogimphs per year or per experi- 
ment, the exposure analysis equipment was saturated.
 Physicists therefore had to invent methods of reading the sparks which 
bypassed photographs. We introduced two new methods: one was based on 
the measurable delay of the signal produced by a spark in reaching the end 
of an electrode; the second, based on the division of the current produced 
by a spark in plane or wire electrodes, at the ends of which the current 
pulses are measured, made it possible to obtain the coordinates of the spark 
and hence of the particle by purely electronic means. This latter method was 
developed in several laboratories for the focal planes of spectrometers and 
we have ourselves thus performed experiments on the nuclear reactions 
induced by pions.
 Other approaches, some of them better than ours, were developed simul- 
taneously: sonic spark chambers and wire spark chambers which gave rise to 
very important developments. Nevertheless, the fad that it is impossible to 
trigger spark chambers at rates above about 100 times per second reduced 
their scope. In the minds of some physicists arose the idea of limiting the 
discharge produced from electrons released in a gas to a much lower level 
than that attained by the spark so as not to discharge the capacitance 
formed by the electrodes; the additional gain thus needed was to be ob- 
tained by means of electronic circuits.
 In 1967, I undertook this step, armed with some experience acquired at 
the College de France from 1948, some ten years before I joined CERN. I 
built cylindrical single-wire proportional chambers and also demonstrated 
the possibility of making use of the light phenomena produced by an 
avalanche of electrons in a gas. This approach led to no practical method. It 
was greatly extended later on during work done at the University of Coim- 
bra in Portugal by E. Policarpo. This work, from which I drew a great deal 
of inspiration, proved very valuable for the eicperience I gained arid, more 
particularly, the understanding of the principles governing the multiplica- 
tion of electrons in gases. It led me to an attempt to build chambers with 
avalanches made visible by short electric pulses. It resulted, in 1956, in the 
first detector with sparks following the trajectory of particles. It played no 
role in the introduction of spark chambers in particle physics.
 Figure 1 shows the design selected in 1967 to study proportional 
multiwire structures.
 A study of the electric fields shows that, in the region near the wire taken 
to a positive potential, where a limited-scale avalanche is to be produced, 
the electric field is the same as that prevailing near a wire tensioned in the 
axis of a cylindrical tube, as can be seen in figs. 2 and 3. With the param- 
eters we chose, in a gas in common use in proportional counters, the 
average mean free path of an ionizing collision should, at atmospheric 
pressure, be about 1 µm (fig. 4). We might therefore expect a gain of about 
l0Ffor an avalanche extending over a distance close to the diameter of the 
wire, i.e. 20

                                                  &ova Curial


                           Guard Scrip           Mylar                 Mesh



           t
          T5 PI
                                                                                            — Araldite


                               Thci< wire Wires al Slim                        Myliar

                                       Mesh
                             11.                                                 High voitage

                                                                     va2.• Araldite

           15                                                                          Amplifier
                                                                                    10 KO.

                                    F                                            Nft,



                                 Guard skip


          F4      A few constructinn detaiLs of multiwire chambers. The scnsitives anode wires ETC
          separated by 2 nun from each other, their diameter is 20 p.m. They ETC stretched between two 
          cathode meshes, in a gas at atmospheric pressure. The edges of the pilules are potted in 
          Aralchte., allowing only the high voltage to enter End only the puLses to Leave to go to a 'ICI 1.11 
          amp lifier.








IIHH 1111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111
11111111101111111111M111111111111111111114101111111111 
imiimiimmilmiim mill111111111111111111111111H111111
 nuiliMIIIIIIIIHHM11111115111111111 I 111111111111ffi1 
  111111111HIM1111 HM11110111 1111 11111111111111111
II 11111111111111111111111M1111111111111111111111111111111111 
II mmit1mmill11111111I IIMIIIIIIM1111111111111111
minfigiwiRM111141111111111111111111111111M111111111
1111111M111111111110 1IN1E11111111111111111111111M1
 1111111111111111R1    M11111M11111111111111111I
                                nillak5111
               1 4.


  lli1110111111111111111111    1111    111 111111
 111111111M1111 11P11111111111MM1111 111=111111111
        mi11111111111111111111111110111111M1110111111
        U11"1111111111H11111111111111111111111M1111 1111M1 
           UM      H11111111    HUH11111111RIMII


Fig 2. EquipotcntiaLs and electric field lines in a          3 paha cif fig. 2 showing the electric field 
multiwirc proportional chamber. The efkct of            around a wire (wire spacing 2 mm, diameter 20
the slight shifting of one of the wino' bc• seen. 
It has no effect en the field clear to the wire

Fit 4: 111:21.rial i4 f11 111.1 TP11 PIN11.111.1)11;41 i I1a1111x 1 4 011. [Inc 0/Cvl 1 14. 1.14:11d alp OrilK 1.114;	
:.1 rn.;. perpendicular lo
the piarku 4 Or Li	
arki I. CM I Cvl i011 1111Q a  ii 11 IC 11119 ;111(1 IFl I tie y dircoi	
s 1811 .
111C V;101111LIS regi4 Oris (0 10;1 P 1 Orr. VIVO !Mil it' 41101 L E I riff :pot i	
variable.' al oti ri KI1 vi ill %1 a] 1 I. fitich arc 
slum (11.
There still remained one challenging problem, that of the capacitive cou- 
pling between the wires. The closer they were, the more likely it was that a  
pulse induced in one wire would be propagated on its neighbours. This was  
true for pulses produced by an external electric generator but untrue for  
the interim.] generator formed by the positive and negative ions FRparating  
under the effect of the electric field. There had, in the past, been examples  
of wire counters, especially in cosmic-ray experiments, where this fear of  
coupling led to the insulation of each of the positive amplifying wires by  
partitions or thick intermediate wires. We merely have to enmine the pulse- 
generation mechanism in a proportional counter to see that, whatever the  
distance between the wires, the one which is the seat of an avalanche will  
develop a negative signal, whereas the neighbouring wires and, in genera],  
all the neighbouring electrodes, develop a positive signal which is therefore  
easy to distinguish from the other.
Most of the electrons produced in the first microns in front of the wire  
pass through a very small proportion, AU, of the potential V applied  
between the wire and the cathode on their trajectory. The collected charge  
Q will produce on the wire taken to the potential V only a pulse of charge  
.6iL), so that V•AQ=Q•A V. With our selected parameters, the time needed  
to collect the electron charge was a fraction of a nanosecond. However, the  
positive ions have to pass through the whole of the potential drop V and  
thus induce almost all of the charge pulse which develops as a function of  
time according to a law which reflects the considerable field close to the  
wire and the decreasing field far from it. The initial very fast increase of the
ZG
1
4q/ci
1/r
Drift region in  
variable field
Drift region in
-
constant field
Avalanche regia
Field along 
x axis
Field along 
y axis
0.01
0.1
2q	
-
Distance tom ienire of wire (m)
-4%

                                                                                               Georges Chirpak                                                                                                             27

pulse gave some people the illusion that the initial pulse observed was 
caused by the collection of the electrons of the avalanche. For a pmportion- 
al counter with a radius of 1 cm, and a wire with a diameter of 20 II en, the 
electron contribution is only 1 %, Figure 5 shows the characteristic shape of 
the development of a pulse in a proportional chamber owing to the motion 
of the ions. Although the total time taken for icm collection is close to 500 
  is in the example chosen, almost half of the signal develops within a time 
close to a thousandth of this value, which is very useful for fast detection.

                                                  100                             200                              300  1                          400  I                         500 T I
                                      _10 us
                                                                   =100 M5









         —V(t)

            5: Ilevelopilleril                                         111        INLJINV il3                                              111E.111111CII I IS 4 he 104di di-WI-11171e rd.
Ll'pe Nye i i ix t i•1 ptIN Ile(lo.Cell lie 3114iik al id 4 lie i.                                                 F11 H k. Thie eik4 L                            [Ice iniS111:14 differenlialkko 
Lune 4:4 Ppr{.161IIIN x is S4:Cii. .1.11.0 1114 Ft i4 ol I 4 ,f tIic rposilive 14113S 4:111SC t11 1111V wrrOs. produi.Vs. a very 
rihing !make .

The key phenOineT1011                                                    this:. whereas the induced signal is negative on the
wire from which the positive ions are going away, it is positive on the 
neighbouring wires or electrodes.
       This has two important consequences.,
-        It is a simple matter to locate the wire which is the seat of the avalanche,
         whatever the distance between the wires.
         The position of this avalanche along the wire can be obtained if the
         cathode is made of wires or strips perpendicular to the anode wire.
       The distribution of the induced positive signals is then centred on the 
avalanche. Experience was to show that this observation was of prime 
importance to the imaging of neutral radiation, photons, or neutrons.
       The hum resolution of the detector depends on the distance between the 
wires. Proportional cylindrical chambers had been abandoned in particle- 
physics experiments as this resolution was poor: the time taken by the 
electrons re/eased in the gas to reach the multiplication region near the wire 
is actually variable. It immediately appeared that the delay was easily 
measured in a multiwire chamber and that it gave precisely the distance of 
the ionizing particle iron the wire.

28                                  nyelen 1MEE




  This cleared the way for a class of detectors derived from. wire chambers 

in which the detecting wires are very far apart and where the coordinate is

calculated by measuring the drift-time of the electrons in the gas. From 

1968 we showed that it was pOSSible to obtain accuracies of the order of 100

pm with structures such as that of fig. 6, which provide a constant electric 

field over a long distance. In 1969, a group at 5aclay began to build drift

chambers with a migration length of 20 cm, while, in Heidelberg, studies 

were undertaken on chambers constructed, similarly to ordinary wire cham- 

bers, with a field wire fitted between the anode wires to repel the electrons.

The drift chamber seemed to be the ideal instrument for large detectors; 

many were the groups which then began to fit considerable areas with these

detectors, reaching, for instance, 5 m X 5 m, making possible a precision of 

a few hundred microns, with electronics comprising a limited number of 

channels.





                                                             —2200 V




                                •

                                                             Field wires 
             Beam               •                            producing 

                                I             •              a uniform 
                                                             field

                                •             •


      —2000 V                                 ..2            90%

                                  • 0 0 • 0 •                transparent grid
      Measurement                                            Chamber with 
      of the pulse                                           prDportional 
      arrival time                                           amplification




Fig_  Operating principle of a &teeter bawd ante drift-timy rhy do ptrom in a. yeambard

electric field (14)68).






   Starling in 1%9, we stressed that the exploitation of electron drift in 

large volumes, combined with the measurement of the centroid of the 

avalanches induced in a wire chamber, was the way leading to threedimen- 

skNial detectors. It was, however, D. Nygren who, by combining the et fleets 

of parallel magnetic and electric fields and solving formidable data acquisi- 

tion problems, succeeded in creating an instrument which provides the 

finest images of the most complex configurations obtained in colliders; for 

this purpose the repetition rate must be low enough to accommodate an 

electron drift over long distances. In fact it was the demands of physics, 

differing very widely depending on the nature of experiments and accelera- 

tors, which dictated the structures of gas detectors, making use of the 

properties that we demonstrated in 1968.

  The development of transistor electronics, however, made it possible to

design systems requiring tens of thousands of channels. The advantage of 
wire over drift chambers was their capacity of accepting very high counting 
rates. The resolution tine, of about 30 ns, and the possible counting rate of 
lOyulses per second, made it feasible to tackle the study of rare phenom- 
ena which were beyond the reach of spark chambers as they needed very 
high counting rates.
 The design study of a giant detector, the Split-Field Magnet (SFIV1) was 
launched at CERN in 1 970 under the direction of A. Minten for an 
experiment at the Intersecting Storage Rings (ISR). This detector com- 
prised 70,000 wires, some of them 2 in long. Another group under J. 
Steinberger undertook the construction of a detector designed to collect a 
large number of events violating charge parity conjugation in the study of 
kwon decay, A large number of difficult problems had to be solved to go 
from the 10 cu i 10 cm chamber to these large areas. The intensity of the 
pulses collected on the wires of a chamber was proportional to the energy 
deposited in the volume defined by the electric field lines ending at a wire. 
In a cylindrical counter, simple considerations showed that the logarithm of 
the gain was proportional to a factor off= VI '')- ]1., where V is 
the applied voltage and V, the threshold voltage. The behaviour of the wire 
chamber is exactly the same as that of a cylindrical counter.
 My group was then reinforced by F. Sauli, who, together with collabo- 
rators joining the various projects launched by us, contributed greatly to 
the success of many new detectors. We undertook a systematic study of the 
factors controlling the accuracy in drift chambers. We investigated the 
ultimate accuracy which can be reached in multiwire chambers by measur- 
ing the signals induced on the cathodes. We showed that the avalanches 
could extend to only a very limited extent around the wire and that by 
measuring the centroid of the induced signals it was possible to determine 
the azimuth of an avalanche. Our results and those of a few others, which 
started a systematic study of the multiwire stnictures, led to a generalization 
of the use of wire chambers and drift chambers with a considerable diversifi- 
cation of the detector's structure be adapted to the variety of situations 
encountered in particle physics.
 Mixtures of up to four gases were found to reduce the cost of the 
necessary electronics, making it possible to obtain high saturated pulses 
independent of the energy deposited in the gas, and required less sensitive 
and expensive electronics than with the proportional system, as well as 
being sufficiently resistant to ageing effects.
 It was demonstrated that these pulses were produced by a series of 
avalanches which stopped at the uniform low field far from the wire.
 A systematic study of chambers filled at very low pressures, conducted in 
Israel by A. Breskin, was to show that the chambers operated at pressures as 
low as 1 Ton. with astonishing time resolutions: the range of application of 
wire chambers was widening.
 Whereas wire and drift chambers were essential in all the particle physics 
experiments, rapidly replacing spark chambers and, in some instances,

30             rigreica 1992

reinforcing bubble chambers with structures outside them, many groups 
were making use of the new opportunities offered for imaging various types 
of ionizing radiation. The main applications appeared in the field of X-rays 
with an energy dose to 10 leV. Under the inspiration of V. Perez-Mendez, 
chambers were built to study the structure of proteins by the imaging of 
X-rays diffracted by their crystals. Gas detectors had the drawback of being 
highly transparent to X-rays and the methods used to overcome this re- 
quired compressed xenon.
 We, on our side, tried to solve this problem by building a spherical drift 
chamber centred on the macromolecule crystal. The radial lines of the 
electric field eliminate any parallax and the electrons drifting over 15 cm 
are transferred into a 50 nu X 50 cm multiwire chamber in which the 
avalanches are measured to a precision of 0.5 mm. It is also found that the 
response is continuous in both dimensions, as the diffusion ensures an 
expansion of the cloud of ionization electrons which always covers two 
wires, making it possible to interpolate the position of the avalanche be- 
tween them.
 The apparatus has considerable advantages over photography in terms of 
data-acquisition rate and the signal-to-noise ratio. Used routinely with the 
X-ray beams produced by the synchrotron radiation from an electron 
storage ring at Orsay it gives a good crop of important results.
 The imagination shown by various groups has made it possible also to 
extend the field of application of wire chambers for higher X- or y-ray 
energies.
 Thus, a Novosibirsk group has developed a chamber making it possible to 
X-ray the human body with a decrease in dosage over the most powerful 
equipment available on the market of at least a factor of 10.
 A group at Schlumberger has produced a system for radiographing giant 
containers using X-rays of up to 5 MeV. A. Jeavons has constructed posi- 
tron cameras capable of detecting 0.511 MeV 7-rays with a precision of 
about 1 mm. These cameras, which are not efficient enough for the method 
to be applied to nuclear medicine, made possible a remarkable advance in 
the field of solid-sate physics. Finally, a firm is now marketing a camera for 
y-rays, competing with the Anger camera, which is specially suitable for use 
on children. Its principle is based on a wire chamber filled with compressed 
xenon. It gives a considerable reduction in the doses administered and also 
increased precision.
 These few examples are enough to show that we may be on the threshold 
of the general use of radiation detectors originally invented for particle 
physics. It will develop in line with the progress made in particle physics 
research laboratories.
 An important stage in the widening of the field of application of gas 
detectors was made with the introduction, by J. Seguinot and T. Ypsilantis, 
of photosensitive vapours. They make it possible to locate photons in the far 
ultraviolet of an energy above about 5.3 eV with a precision of less than 1 
mm. Major instruments designed to identify particles through Cherenkov

                 Georges Chu-park       31

radiation are now in use in some giant collider detectors. D. Anderson 
explored the opportunities provided by the detection of the photons emit- 
ted by scintillators. Figure 7 shows a 9 GeV photon spectrum obtained with 
a chamber containing a tetrakis(dimethylamine)ethylene (TMAE) vapour. 
Subsequent research also shows that it is possible to use condensed photo- 
cathodes compatible with gas amplification.



    800







    400






         -1117111 
             2    4     6     8    10
                    E(CeV)
Pig_ 7: Energy spectrum of 9 GeV particles (elodrons End picas) with Bairrystals praTic.c1. 
wire charthers filled with a photiseraritive gas (TivIAE, see text)


As the intensity of accelerators increased, it was found that the wire cham- 
bers themselves could not cope with the expected counting rates. Beyond 
particle fluxes from lOito Whits per second and per millimetre of wire, 
the space charge produced by the accumulation of positive ions offset the 
applied field and annulled the gain.
 To overcome this problem I thought, together with F. Sault, of separating 
the gas amplification into two stags: a gain in a preamplification structure 
followed by a partial extraction of the electrons into a drift region fitted 
with a control grid, and their transfer into a wire chamber which would be 
required only to amplify the electrons accepted by the grid (fig. 8). It is then 
possible th accept or reject an event with a time precision of about 30 ns and 
a delay defined by the electron drift-time. Together with S. Majewski we 
found a structure reaching this goal. It made it possible easily th amplify 
single photoelectrons released by an ultraviolet photon in a photosensitive 
gas. The drift region in fad largely eliminates the effect of the radiations 
emitted by excited atoms produced in an avalanche, which are responsible

   aidFiciska


   for secondary effects by ejecting electrons near the initial position of the 
   photoelectrons. We have built large detectors of this kind in collaboration 
   with Saclay to obtain images of Cherenkov rings in an experiment per- 
   formed at the Fermi Laboratory Tevatron in the United States. This devel- 
   opment proved most fruitful, however, in a special biological field of 
   application. There are several research fields in which it is necessary to 
   obtain the image of the distribution of molecules marked with radioactive 
   elements. Several commercial firms have tried to make use of wire chambers 
   for this imaging, purpose. The main difficulty lies in the generally consider- 
   able distance which the electrons from the radioactive bodies may have to 
   travel in the gases. We have observed that an amplifying structure based on 
   parallel grids did not suffer from this defect. Multiplying an electron by a 
   Townsend avalanche, in fact, exponentially helps the ionization electrons 
   released in the gas near the cathode, which is the entry window. Precisions 
   of the order of 0,3 mm have thus been obtained for P radiation emitted by 
   phosphorus-32, for instance.





                X - photon

                                                            PA

                     Ge.0
                        ---  -                              T1
  Avalanche•            F • i F   -----P.41           • + F +
Transferred          PAT                   -LF              T2
electrons

Arriplikation aria                     PA2
Joaa.li zation                  -------
                   } MWPC.









   Fig  Various multistage structure.. (a) A preamplification (PA) and transfer (1) component is
   foliewcd by a multiwire proportional dumber (JAW; the corprersbon and drift space (C and 
    D) gad= t possible to Lnjcct a constant charge (X-rays etc.) into the amplification region_ (b) 
   Two picallel-plke units with obErge transfer from PAJ to PA2 The beat tine resolution were 
   opined with this configuratim, (c) A multistage chamber with a gate: the wires of grid G are at 
   alternating potentials of = 70 V, The electrons are transmitted from component PA -F tto 
    MWPC and they arc transfcircd when the wires arc brought to the same potential by short 
    pulse!' of )1.1 nal, nuking it pasible to select MC events in a high rate environment



     We then took another step by coupling such a multiplication region with a 
   method of reading out the position of the avalanches, making use of the 
   light emitted. We had developed this method in order to study very rare

                         &gimes aarpak            33

       phenomena such as double 3 decay or collisions between gas atoms and 
       certain types of hidden matter. We thought that only the redundancy 
       provided by photographic methods could characterize a rare event. A 
       British group was also independently tackling this method for imaging 
       Cherenkov photons. They, tom used the multistage chambers which we had 
       introduced and reached the same conclusion: with suitable vapours it was 
       possible to obtain a sufficiently plentiful emission of photons to detect the 
       light emitted by the avalanches with simple optics.
        The great advantage of this method lies in the read-out which it permits in 
       the use of hundreds of thousands of channels now making up the CCD 
       (charge-coupling device), which is the basic component of video cameras. 
       Moreover, the fad that the image of a light avalanche covers several pixels 
       makes it possible to interpolate the centre of the avalanche and multiply the 
       number of real channels by almost 10. We were thus able to make an 
       instrument for visualizing the distribution of the electrons emitted by 
       tritium in a slice of rats kidney, making it possible to observe details of 
       about 100 The fad that the same data (fig. 9) were obtained in a single 
       day instead of the three months previously required by the photographic 
       method aroused immediate interest among certain biologists and gave rise 
       to a development which is still under way.
























                     a                     b
       erg_ 0: Images a si.unplos Wpm kin a iritium-mErkod rat's kidney. The four pats of diagram 
         Welt obtained with a wig detectcr. the window, centred at three different levels, has a grey 
       scale of 2.56 The intensity spectrum is taken along the oblique line marked on the first view with        pm pixels in the sample 3:lime The gas mixture is xenon with 2.5% triethyLamine. The detaiLs 
h        pm pixels in the sample 3:lime The gas mixture is xenon with 2.5% triethyLamine. The detaiLs 
       of the renal chisels, measuring 50 prn, oar be seem This image may be obtained in 20 hours.
       (b) Awaradingraph showing the adjacent slice of rat's kidney to which a phonographic emu Lsion 
       was applied for 3 MO 16 S.

321               Piga ic.9 ISM

 Our latest experiment with gas detectors comprising parallel-grid struc- 
tures helped convince us that the controlled multiplication of avalanches in 
gases, in structures as diverse as wires or parallel surfaces, by selecting pho- 
tocathodes compatible with gas amplification is still a source of fruitful 
development& in many fields this multiplication may sin result in progress 
in all fields where radiation must be imaged, from ultraviolet photons to 
y-rays and the hiOest-energy particles. At the current stage of high-eriergy 
physics, however, simply "flaking use of the location of free electrons near 
the wires of proportional chambers and the drift-time of the electrons 
provides an image of configurations rivalling in complexity those provided 
by bubble chambers. This is shown in fig. 10, the image of an event 
generated in the ALEPH detector installed at one of the intersections of 
LEP, the large e-e- collider operated at CERN.
























Fig_ I& Image of an 4:1 c. collision obtained at the ALEPH experiment at LEP using an 
instrument making use of the drift-time in a Large volume and the read-out of coordinates 
projected in a wire thanker. Auxilia-y outside detectors provide the information on the energy 
of the particles, the trajectory of which was dispLa.*.

                            iSsorias Chirpak

BIBLIOGRAPHY
A very comprehensive historical study with most referenCea COrreOpOildio$ to the 
period covered by this article is to be found in
    Cardbaro, The development of electron detectors. at CERN (1966 - It 19714 
  CERN .Ffistary Study Na Ci-.15.39, January 1992_
00 first article that described the properties of rfluItiwire structures is.
  G. Charpak, R. Boucher, T. Rressani, 1. Favier and IC .Z.Lipanc, The use Of 
  multiwire proportional chambers to select and localize charged particles, Nuclear 
  Instruments and itifethogs 62 (1968) 202 -26..
ft w,4 followed by several &beim, one of than Ovih$ a description Of the prOpeOa 
we made during our first year Of studies. of the wire chambers. and the drift

chamberCharpak, 11 Rahra gmd H, Steiner, Some developments in the operatiOn Of 
  ranItiwirc proportional chambers, i'ilmelostp- Instruments rid Methods RI (1970) 18 -


Tide refge the reader to highly detailed works such as
  F. Saki% Principles of operation of muItiwire proportional and drift chambers, 
  CERN 77419 (1977).
  P. Rice-Evans, Srpark., strostnter, proportioned acrd drift diarnliErs (Richelieu, London, 
  1974),
  T. Feriae., Techniques istrid concepts of high-energy physic's (Plenum. press, New York, 
  1987),
and to a book giving a good analysis of the development of detectors in relation to 
the gvOthili011 Of particle physic
  E Cole,  Maria and C Sutton,. air eepixiva   (Oxford University Press,
  1987).

