          ANTOINE H. BECQUEREL

    On radioactivity, a new property of matter
          Nobel Lecture, December 11, 1903


The subject which I propose to speak to you about has become, in only a 
few years, so vast that in order to deal with it in a single lecture I should 
have to confine myself to listing the main facts following the chronological 
order of their discovery. But as M. and Mme. Curie are to describe to you 
their fine work on radium, I will simply summarize the subject and give 
some account of my own research.
 At the beginning of 1896, on the very day that news reached Paris of the 
experiments of Röntgen and of the extraordinary properties of the rays emit- 
ted by the phosphorescent walls of Crookes' tubes, I thought of carrying out 
research to see whether all phosphorescent material emitted similar rays. The 
results of the experiment did not justify this idea, but in this research I en- 
countered an unexpected phenomenon.
 Of all the phosphorescent materials, uranium salts seemed particularly 
suitable for the investigations, because of the exceptional structure indicated 
by the harmonic series of the bands making up their absorption and phos- 
phorescence spectra. Thus I placed sheets of double sulphate of uranium and 
potassium on photographic plates enveloped in black paper or protected by 
a sheet of aluminium and exposed them to light for several hours. On de- 
veloping the plates, I found that the uranium salt had emitted rays which re- 
produced the silhouettes of the crystalline sheets through the black paper and 
various screens of metal or thin glass laid on the plates.
 Under these conditions the phenomenon could be ascribed to a trans- 
formation of solar energy, like phosphorescence, but I soon recognized that 
the emission was independent of any familiar source of excitation, such as 
light, electricity or heat.
 We were thus faced with a spontaneous phenomenon of a new order. 
Figure 1 shows the first print, which revealed the spontaneity of the radiation 
emitted by the uranium salt. The rays passed through both the black paper 
which enveloped the plate, and a thin sheet of copper in the shape of a cross. 
Figure 2 shows the radiograph of an aluminium medal; the non-uniform 
absorption of the radiation by the different thicknesses of metal reveals the

     RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 53
             f* •
           & 










                    Fig.1.
effigy. As the uranium salts used had been prepared a very long time before- 
hand, it was to be supposed that the intensity of the phenomenon was in- 
dependent of time, and hence that the emission was constant. All the later 
experiments have shown that the activity of uranium does not diminish ap- 
preciably with time.
 In obtaining these first results I noticed that the radiation of uranium dis- 
charged electrically-charged materials located some distance away, and this 
phenomenon provided a second method of studying the new rays. The pho-














                    Fig. 2.

        54          1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
        tographic method was primarily a qualitative one, the electrical method gave 
        numerical data, and the early measurements revealed the constancy of the 
        radiation with time.
         The two methods showed that all uranium salts, whatever their origin, 
        emitted radiation of the same type, that this property was an atomic prop- 
        erty connected with the element uranium, and that metallic uranium was 
        about three and a half times as active as the salt used in the first experiments.        A sphere of charged uranium, which discharges spontaneously in the air 
.        A sphere of charged uranium, which discharges spontaneously in the air 
        under the influence of its own radiation, retains its charge in an absolute 
        vacuum. The exchanges of electrical charges that take place between charged 
        bodies under the influence of the new rays, are the result of a special con- 
        ductivity imparted to the surrounding gases, a conductivity that persists for 
        several moments after the radiation has ceased to act.
         These fundamental properties of the radiation emitted by uranium were 
        verified later by numerous investigators; of these I will only mention Ruther- 
        ford, who established that the conducting properties of the gases through 
        which the radiation of uranium passes, are completely equal to the ioniza- 
        tion caused by other factors.
         During the course of these first experiments, the observation of a number 
        of phenomena that were hitherto unexplained led me aside from the path to 
        which my later experiments were to bring me back. Various samples of 
        phosphorescent calcium sulphide resting on small plates of glass and covered 
        with a small bell-jar of glass had been laid on a photographic plate protected 
        by a sheet of aluminium 2 mm thick, as shown in Fig. 3. The print developed 
        after 48 hours (Fig. 4) revealed silhouettes of the plates of glass, reproduced         with the details which would have been produced by refraction and total
        with the details which would have been produced by refraction and total











                        Fig. 3.

      RADIOACTIVITY. NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 55











                     Fig. 4.

reflection of the light rays. Although at the same time Troost and Niewen- 
glowski observed the emission of penetrating rays by phosphorescent mate- 
rials, the above experiment could not be reproduced; the cause of the mo- 
mentaneous appearance and the disappearance of the activity of these prod- 
ucts is unknown. But since, in the experiments with uranium, the sil- 
houettes of all the screens put in between are edged with white lines outlin- 
ing projected shadows, and similar to those of the print which we have just 
mentioned, I was led to attribute the properties of light to the radiation from 
uranium, while all later experiments have shown that this radiation cannot 
be reflected or refracted like light rays.
  In 1898 Schmidt and Mme. Curie observed almost simultaneously that 
thorium has properties similar to those of uranium; these properties were 
studied by Owens and by Rutherford. Mme. Curie, after measuring, by 
means of the ionization of air, the radioactivity of a large number of minerals 
containing uranium or thorium, noted the remarkable fact that some mine- 
rals were more active than metallic uranium. After having verified the fact 
that the activity accompanied the uranium molecule in its various combina- 
tions, M. and Mme. Curie concluded from this that there must be present in 
the minerals mentioned a substance more active than uranium, and they set 
about isolating it. They treated one of the most active of these minerals, 
Joachimsthal pitchblende, and first separated from it active bismuth which 
they supposed contained a new substance, polonium, and then soon after- 
wards they obtained extremely active barium, associated with a new ele- 
ment, radium. These products were obtained by fractional crystallizations in 
conjunction with electrometer readings. The activity of the products in-

56           1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
creased with their richness in new elements. The activity of pure radium is 
about one million times greater than that of uranium.
 Giesel has succeeded in obtaining very active preparations, and Debierne 
has studied a product intimately associated with thorium, which he has called 
actinium.
 Of these different preparations, radium alone has the characteristics which 
we associate with simple substances; it has an emission spectrum formed of 
lines not belonging to any other known element, and the molecular weights 
of radium salts increase with their radium content.
 The intensive radiation of radium excites the phosphorescence of different 
materials and restores the ability of crystals to phosphoresce under heat, when 
they have lost this as a result of a previous rise in temperature; moreover, 
radium salts become luminous spontaneously under the influence of their 
own radiation.
 The first samples of polonium and radium that M. and Mme. Curie were 
good enough to lend me, revealed a striking difference in the nature of the 
radiation emitted by each of these substances. They were put into small paper 
cylinders closed at the bottom by very thin flakes of mica or aluminium, and 
the cylinders were placed on a photographic plate. The print in Fig. 5 shows 
that the radium radiation has easily passed through the various envelopes 
while the polonium radiation has not penetrated the wall of the paper cyl- 
inder; thus the polonium rays are only slightly penetrating.
 Towards the end of 1899, first Giesel and then Meyer and von Schweidler 
observed that the radiation of active preparations is deflected by a magnetic









                        •


                Fig. 5.

      RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 57
field. At the same time, unaware of these experiments, I noted the same in 
the case of radium radiation, after first having noted that in a non-uniform 
field the radiation is concentrated on the poles, as are cathode rays in the 
experiment of Birkeland. Figures 6 and 7 show some pictures which were 
obtained in the following way:








          Fig. 6.                Fig. 7.
  Several grains of radio-active matter are put on a photographic plate 
enveloped in black paper and placed horizontally between the poles of a 
magnet; on developing the plate after a few moments' exposure, it will be 
seen that beside the mark indicating the position of the active source a strong 
impression has been produced due to the radiation reflected by the field and 
collected on the plate, on one side only.
  Almost at once I realised that the rays emitted by polonium were not 
deflected under the above experimental conditions and that there are two 
kinds of rays, one highly deflected by a magnetic field, and the other ap- 
parently not deflected. When studying the emission from radium, M. and 
Mme. Curie observed the simultaneous presence there of the two types of 
rays and saw that the rays from polonium, in common with those of the 
same type emitted by radium, were increasingly absorbable according as 
they had passed through a greater thickness of absorbent material: the in-








                     Fig. 8.

58         1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
verse occurs in the case of the heterogeneous beams of the other rays. The 
photograph in Fig. 8 shows the two types of rays known nowadays as oc -rays 
for those emitted by polonium, and 13 -rays for the magnetically deflectable 
part of the radiation from radium. I further found that thorium emits the 
two types of rays and that, even in a vacuum, uranium emits only p-rays 
(Fig. 9) not excluding the existence of much less active, non-deflectable rays.

                     P.A01..t

               Fig. 9.
 There is, in fact, a third type of rays, y-rays, not deflected by a magnetic 
field, attention to which was first drawn by an experiment conducted by 
Villard and which seem analogous to X-rays.
 The action of a magnetic field enables the various components of the 
radiation from radioactive substances to be separated and analysed.
 -Rays behave like cathode rays; it may be assumed, as has been for the 
latter, that they are made up of masses m carrying at velocity v negative 
charges e. In a uniform magnetic field of intensity H the trajectories normal 
to the field must be circular paths, the radius R of which is given by the 
relation RH = (m/e)v.
 For an original direction making an angle with the lines of force, the 
trajectories are helices which wind on cylinders of radius R sin a. I have 
verified the various geometrical consequences of this similarity.
 The beam of p-rays is made up of an infinity of rays with trajectories 
having different radii of curvature; the magnetic field disperses them as a 
prism disperses the light rays of various colours. A photographic plate with- 
out black paper wrapping can be placed in, and parallel to, a uniform, hor- 
izontal magnetic field, for instance, then on the plate a small lead dish con-  
taining a few grains of radiferous barium forming a source of very small di- 
ameter. The radiation is directed at the plate and produces an image on just 
one side. If small strips of different substances - paper, aluminium or various 
metals - have been placed on this side it will be found that in the diffuse 
image which represents a kind of spectrum there are rays with varying pene- 
tration which, under each screen, give images whose limits are different and 
which constitute absorption spectra. It will be seen in the following that the  
image is mainly caused by the secondary radiation which originates at the 
face where the incident rays emerge. Figure 10 is an example of the photo-

      RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER59





         Fig.10.                Fig.11.
graphs obtained; the screens are: a strip of black paper, a strip of aluminium 
0.1 mm thick, and a platinum foil 0.03 mm thick. To secure what might be 
termed a pure spectrum, i.e.such that each point on the plate is struck by a 
single beam, all of whose trajectories have the same curvature, the radiation 
from the point source must be made to pass through a narrow aperture. The 
result is the same as the foregoing (Fig. 11). The photograph shows, more- 
over, an image produced by the secondary rays emitted by the inside face of 
a lead semi-cylinder which covered the source and in which was pierced the 
small aperture in question. Finally, when the radiation is gathered through a 
second small aperture, the result is a single ray.
  Each single ray may be defined by the value of the product RH corre- 
sponding to it. In the above tests, the RH values of the active rays ranged 
from 600 to about 2,500.
  A more complete analysis of the radiation can be made by applying the 
following general method:
  The active material is placed at the bottom of a deep, narrow groove in a 
small block of lead to produce a very thin vertical beam issuing from a linear 
source a few millimetres long. This system is placed in, and parallel to, the 
uniform field of a magnet. A photographic plate is then arranged above the











                     Fig.12.

60       1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
           Fig. 13.
     Fig. ILI.. 1, Fig. is.

     RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 61
source, at right angles to the field and intercepting the deflected beam. The 
very oblique rays reaching the plate produce thereon an image which differs 
very little from the actual trajectory of a skimming ray emitted normally to 
the field. On the photographic plate are placed a number of screens pierced 
by small slits normal to the plate; these then allow either portions of pure 
spectra or single rays to pass. To eliminate the light emitted by the source, 
the latter is covered with a thin aluminium foil. In practice the screens are 
fixed by means of an adhesive to a glass plate which serves to press them 
against the photographic plate. Figures 12, 13, 14 and 15 show the arrange- 
ment of the screens and some of the photographs obtained by this method. 
For two of these photographs an aluminium foil 0.1 mm thick, concentric 
with the pierced screen, was mounted beyond the pure spectra. It can be 
seen that the least deflectable rays pass through this foil as if it were not there; 
other more deflectable rays produce, on emerging, secondary rays which 
are photographically more active than the incident rays, and lastly the most 
deflectable rays do not pass through the aluminium foil and produce at the 
entry face secondary rays which give an intense image. The general image 
within the contours of the screens is also attributable to secondary radiation. 
The magnetic field had an intensity of 859 c.g.s. units. In these tests the a— 
rays were blocked but the y -rays give straight line images revealing a dis- 
continuity between these rays and the less deflectable 0 -rays; for these latter 
the product RH is about 104. In general the not very deflectable 13 -rays are 
very penetrating and the rays which are highly deflected are also very readily 
absorbed. These tests illustrate the advantages of this method for analysing 
the effects produced for each single ray.
 When applied to secondary radiation this method has shown that the rays 
were deflected by a magnetic field in the same direction as the cathode rays.
 While I was conducting these experiments, M. and Mme. Curie demon- 
strated that the 13-rays from radium actually carry negative electrical charges; 
the bodies which receive the radiation become negatively charged while 
the source itself becomes positively charged. For this double phenomenon to 
be observed, all the conductors and the source itself must be completely 
surrounded by insulating materials, e.g. paraffin, or be placed in a vacuum.
 On the other hand I have shown that the 13-rays from radium were de- 
flected by an electrostatic field. When F is the intensity of this field, the 
trajectory of a single ray, as characterized by the quantities in, e and v defined 
above, is a parabola with parameter (m/e) (v2/F), and the size of this parameter 
combined with that of the radius of curvature of the same ray's trajectory in

62          1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
a known magnetic field enables m/e and v to be determined. The experiment 
performed with the apparatus in Fig. 16 provided the image shown in Fig.17 
which reveals the electrical deflection by the shadow projected by a vertical 
screen normal to the field. By combining for a single beam the crossed elec- 
trical and magnetic deflections, Kaufmann has made much more precise 
measurements than the ones that can be deduced from the earlier experi- 
ments. His measurements showed him that the ratio e/m was a function of 
the velocity v which, for the least deflectable -rays, tends towards the speed 
of light. Interpretation of this fact in terms of Max.Abraham's concepts sug- 
gests that the mass of the electrons is at least in part, if not entirely, the out- 
come of electromagnetic reactions - a result which prompts fresh ideas 
about the nature of the inertia of matter.
 Apart from the -rays, identical with cathode rays, a -rays make up an 
important part of the radiation from active substances. I mentioned earlier 
how I had observed them for the first time with polonium, and how their 
apparent non-deflectability and the peculiarities of their low penetrability













                 Fig.16.







                 Fig.17.

      RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 63
had caused them to be classified apart. By means of a very delicate electrical 
 experiment, Rutherford discovered that the a -rays could be deflected very 
 slightly by a very strong magnetic field, and that the deflection was in the 
 opposite direction to that of -rays. They hence behave as if carrying posi- 
 tive electrical charges and appear identical with Goldstein's <<Kanalstrahlen>>.










                     Fig.18.
  Using the above arrangement I recorded photographically the trajectory 
 described in a magnetic field by a -rays from radium and the rays from polo- 
 nium which are identical. Figure 18 shows a photograph (enlarged) obtained 
 in a magnetic field of 10,000 c.g.s.units. The two concurrent paths each 
 correspond to a direction of the magnetic field which has been reversed in 
 the middle of the exposure. They do not present any trace of dispersion, 
 which allows us to regard the active beam as homogeneous. It is noted, 
 moreover, that the radius of curvature calculated for the different points of 
 the trajectory continues to increase as the path in the air increases. This 
 phenomenon can be attributed to the fact that the positive charges, with a 
 velocity which is ten times less than that of the 13 -rays and a real or supposed 
 mass a thousand times larger, attract the neutral molecules of the air, or are 
 discharged progressively in the ionized air.
  As the a -rays are very absorbable, they appear in consequence to con- 
 stitute the most active part of the radiation when this is measured by the 
 ionization of the air in the neighbourhood of the source. These rays are also 
 the most active in exciting the phosphorescence of zinc blende, and of dia- 
 mond, whereas barium platinocyanide becomes equally luminous under the 
 influence of the a - and p -rays and the phosphorescence of the double sul- 
 phate of uranium and potassium is particularly excited by the -rays. The 
 curious effect of Sir W. Crookes' spinthariscope should be attributed to the

64          1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
cc-rays, and this effect seems due to the cleavages accompanied by flashes 
identical with those produced when various crystals are fractured.
 The third kind of rays, i -rays, are characterized by their great penetrabil- 
ity and their non-deflectability in a magnetic field. In the attached illustra-  
tion (Fig. 19) made by the method described earlier, the oc -rays have been 
stopped near their source, the -rays are deflected by the magnetic field, 
whilst the y -rays and the light emitted by the radium salt form a rectilinear 
beam which falls upon a quartz prism. The luminous rays are deflected, 
whereas the y -rays leave a trace which can be followed without deflection 
not only past the prism but even through the prism itself.
 The great penetrability of the y -rays and also of the less deflectable -rays 
means that neither the ionization of the air nor the photographic plate can 
give an exact idea of their intensity, since they pass through the gases and the 
silver salts without being absorbed.
 If fairly thick metal plates are placed in their path, these rays are trans- 
formed and, either on the entry face or on the exit face, give rise to second- 
ary rays which are more absorbable, so much so that the effect observed 
immediately behind these screens is more intense than if this screen did not



















               Fig. 19.

      RADIOACTIVITY, NEW PROPERTY OF MATTER 65
exist. This transformation reminds one of the effect produced by placing a 
fluorescent screen in the path of a beam of invisible radiations.
  A photographic plate receiving the radiation of radium filtered by lead 1 
cm thick is affected more under a strip of lead 1 mm thick than in the regions 
not covered by this screen. Figure 20 shows the effect produced by the radia- 
tion leaving through the walls of a lead parallelepiped after passing through 
5 to 12 mm of metal.














                     Fig. 20.
  These secondary phenomena can account in part for the appearance of 
cast shadows on the edges of all the more or less transparent screens placed on 
the photographic plates.
  Uranium and polonium emit penetrating rays which appear to be iden- 
tical with y-rays.
  Radiation of radioactive substances produces various chemical actions; it 
acts upon the substances used in photography, and the 0C- and 13 -rays are the 
most active in this respect; it colours glass violet or brown, and the alkaline 
salts are coloured yellow, violet, blue or green. Under its action paraffin, 
celluloid and paper turn yellow; white phosphorus is transformed into red 
phosphorus. This transformation has been noted with f3 -rays, but it is prob- 
able that a -rays are equally active. Ozone is produced in the air around active 
bodies. Not only gases but also liquid dielectrics (petroleum, liquid air) and 
insulating solids like paraffin are ionized when they have been penetrated 
by radium radiation, and they preserve their conductive properties for a few

66           1903 A.H.BECQUEREL
moments after the radiation has ceased to act. Giesel has observed that an 
aqueous solution of radium bromide continuously liberates oxygen and hy- 
drogen at the rate of approximately 10 cm3 per gram per day. According to 
Ramsay and Soddy these gases would also contain helium.
 M. Curie has discovered moreover that radium salts continually emit heat; 
pure radium would emit approximately 80 calories per gram per hour. Curie 
and Dewar observed that in plunging a tube containing radium into liquid 
hydrogen there was a continuous release of hydrogen gas; with 0.7 g of ra- 
dium bromide 73 cm' of hydrogen were obtained per minute.
 Various physiological effects have been observed with radium rays; they 
excite phosphorescence in the interior of the eye; when an active product is 
brought near to the temple, a sensation of light is perceived. They act upon 
the epidermis and profoundly disorganize the skin, as do X-rays. The effect 
is produced without any sensation being felt at first and it only develops 
after several weeks; it then produces more or less deep lesions which can take 
several months to heal and which leave scars. At present an effort is being 
made to utilize this action in the treatment of lupus and cancers.
 Radium rays have an active effect on the nerve centres and can then cause 
paralysis and death; they seem to act with particular intensity on living tis- 
sues in the process of evolution.

Up to now we have only spoken of the radiation which is transmitted 
through glass, mica, opaque bodies and metals. In the emission of radioactive 
bodies there is another phenomenon of a different nature which appears to 
be intimately connected with radioactivity, if it is not the primordial phe- 
nomenon. Thorium and radium emit energy in a particular form; the resul- 
tant activity is propagated in the form of an active vapour which has been 
called emanation and which is arrested by any covering, however thin, which 
is impermeable to gases.
 This emanation seems to settle upon all bodies in order to make them 
radioactive, but the activity disappears when the latter are no longer under 
the influence of the active source, even when they are in a closed chamber. 
These facts were discovered simultaneously at the end of 1899 by Ruther- 
ford for thorium, and by M. and Mme. Curie for radium. Rutherford when 
studying the activity of thorium saw that besides the ordinary radiation there 
was an effect produced by an emanation comparable with an active vapour. 
This latter is deposited on all bodies, principally on those which are neg- 
atively charged, and it makes them momentarily active.

