                                           449


QUASI-ELECTRIC FIELDS AND BAND OFFSETS: 
TEACHING ELECTRONS NEW TRICKS

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000 
by
HERBERT KROEMER
ECE Department, University of California, Santa Barbara, CA 93106, USA.




I. INTRODUCTION
Heterostructures, as I use the word here, may be defined as heterogeneous 
semiconductor structures built from two or more different semiconductors, 
in such a way that the transition region or interface between the different ma- 
terials plays an essential role in any device action. Often, it may be said that 
the interface is the device.
  The participating semiconductors all involve elements from the central por- 
tion of the periodic table of the elements (Table I). In the center is silicon, the 
backbone of modern electronics. Below Si is germanium. Although Ge is 
rarely used by itself, Ge-Si alloys with a composition-dependent position play 
an increasingly important role in today's heterostructure technology. In fact, 
historically this was the first heterostructure device system proposed, although 
it was also the system that took longest to bring to practical maturity, largely be- 
cause of the 4 % mismatch between the lattice constants of Si and Ge.

Table I. Central portion of the periodic table of the elements, showing the element from 
columns H through VI actively used in current heterostructure technology.
II       III      IV      V        VI
         Al       Si      P        S
Zn       Ga       Ge      As       Se
Cd       In               Sb       Te 
Hg

Silicon plays the same central role in electronic metallurgy that steel plays in 
structural metallurgy. But just as modern structural metallurgy draws on 
metals other than steel, electronics draws on semiconductors other than sili- 
con, namely, the compound semiconductors. Every element in column III 
may be combined with every element in column V to form a so-called III—V 
compound. From the elements shown, twelve different discrete III—V com- 
pounds may be formed. The most widely used compound is GaAs — gallium 
arsenide — but all of them are used in heterostructures, the specific choice de- 
pending on the application. In fact, today the III-V compounds are almost al- 
ways used in heterostructures, rather than in isolation.

450             Physics 2000

 Two or more discrete compounds may be used to form alloys. A common 
example is aluminum-gallium arsenide, Al.Gai_,As, where x is the fraction of 
column-III sites in the crystal occupied by Al atoms, 1—x is occupied by Ga 
atoms. Hence we have not just 12 discrete compounds, but a continuous 
range of materials. As a result, it becomes possible to make compositionally 
graded heterostructures, in which the composition varies continuously rather 
than abruptly throughout the device structure.
 Similar to the 111—V compounds, every element shown in column II may be 
used together with every element in column VI to create II—VI compounds, 
and again alloying is possible to create a continuous range of the latter.


II. BAND DIAGRAMS AND QUASI-ELECTRIC FORCES
Whenever I teach my semiconductor device physics course, one of the central 
messages I try to get across early is the importance of energy band diagrams. 
I often put this in the form of "Kroemer's Lemma of Proven Ignorance":
 If, in discussing a semiconductor problem, you cannot draw an Energy 
 Band Diagram, this shows that you don't know what you are talking about, 
with the corollary
 If you can draw one, but don't, then your audience won't know what you 
 are talking about.
Nowhere is this more true than in the discussion of heterostructures, and 
much of the understanding of the latter is based on one's ability to draw their 
band diagrams — and knowing what they mean.
 To illustrate the idea, consider first a homogenous piece of semiconductor, 
say, a piece of uniformly doped silicon, but with an electric field applied. The 
band diagram then looks like the top diagram in Fig. 1, consisting simply of 
two parallel tilted lines representing the conduction and valence band edges. 
The separation between the two lines is the energy gap of the semiconductor; 
the slope of the two band edges is the elementary charge e multiplied by the 
electric field E. When an electron or a hole is placed into this structure, a 
force —eE is acting on the electron, eE on the hole; the two forces are equal in 
magnitude and opposite in direction, their magnitude is the slope of the 
bands, just the signs differ.
 In a heterostructure, the energy gap becomes position-dependent, and the 
two band edge slopes are no longer equal, hence the two forces are no longer 
equal in magnitude. It would, for example, be possible to have a force acting 
only upon one kind of the carriers (Fig. lb), or to have forces that act in the 
same direction for both types of carriers (Fig. lc). Purely electrical forces in 
homogeneous crystals can never do this. This is why I call these forces "quasi- 
electric." They present a new degree of freedom for the device designer to enable him 
to obtain effects that are basically impossible to obtain using only "real" electric 
fields.
 This is the underlying general design principle of all heterostructure de-

                   Herbert Kroemer          451













                       Fe s0
               //1//////////////////11/11/11/














                       +qFti
Figure 1. Quasi-Electric Fields: (a) A true electric field simply tilts the bands; (b) quasi-electric 
fields, with no force on electrons, but a force on holes; (c) quasi-electric fields forcing electrons 
and holes in the same direction. From Kroemer (1957a).



vices, first spelled out in a 1957 paper of mine (Kroemer, 1957a). In fact, the 
preceding paragraph is an only slightly edited version of a key paragraph in 
that paper.
 When I wrote those lines, I did not know about Shockley's famous 1951 
patent (Shockley), where the possibility of a bipolar transistor with an emitter 
of wider energy gap is explicitly mentioned. However, the wide-gap emitter 
idea appears to have been presented principally to cover alternative design 
possibilities, a procedure typical in patents. The patent gives no indication 
why such a design would have distinct advantages over a homostructure de- 
sign, much less a general design principle extending to other kinds of de- 
vices. My own formulation might be viewed as a broad generalization of the 
idea in Shockley's patent. But my point of departure was different: not an 
abrupt energy gap change with accompanying band offset steps, but explicitly 
a continuous energy gap variation of "designable" width, of which the abrupt 
gap change is simply a limiting case.
 Returning to Fig. lb, it should be emphasized that the zero conduction 
band slope shown there does not imply a zero electric field. A true electric 
field is of course present, and it can in principle be determined by the inte- 
gration of Poisson's equation, provided the local space charge densities are

452            Physics 2000

known, often a non-trivial task. But this true field is not part of the band dia-  
gram. Nor do the electrons care: The band edge slopes are what matters, not 
the true electric field. The difference between the two becomes even more 
drastic in Fig. lc, where we could not guess even the direction of the true field, 
much less its magnitude.

III. HETEROSTRUCTURE BIPOLAR TRANSISTORS
A. Graded-gap transistor
I had been led to the 1957 principle by a very practical question dating back 
to 1953/54, when I was working at the telecommunications research labora- 
tory (Fernmeldetechnisches Zentralamt; FTZ) of the German Postal Service: 
The early bipolar junction transistors were far too slow for practical applica- 
tions in telecommunications, and I set myself the task of understanding the 
frequency limitations theoretically — and what to do about them. One ap- 
proach — not the only one — was to speed up the flow of the minority carriers 
from the emitter to the collector by incorporating an electric field into the 
base region. This could be done by using, not a uniform doping in the base, 
but one that decreased exponentially from the emitter end to the collector 
end — the so-called drift transistor (Kromer, 1953). While working out the de- 
tails, I realized that
 "... a drift field may also be generated through a variation of the energy gap 
 itself, by making the base region from a non-stoichiometric mixed crystal of 
 different semiconductors with different energy gaps (for example, Ge-Si), 
 with a composition that varies continuously through the base." [Translated 
 from Kromer (1954) ]
This was not yet the full general design principle, but it constituted the origi-  
nal conception of what has become known as the heterostructure bipolar 
transistor (HBT), and ultimately of the heterostructure device field in gene- 
ral.
 The appropriate band diagram (Fig. 2) followed in the 1957 paper men- 
tioned earlier, where I gave the 1954 idea as one example of the general de- 
sign principle. Note that Fig. 2 shows a flat conduction band, as would be the 
case for a sufficiently heavy uniform doping; the band diagram of Fig. lb re- 
presents essentially the base region of that early concept. The case of Fig. lc 
illustrates the generality of the design principle.
 Note that the original proposal explicitly gave the Ge-Si system as an exam- 
ple, rather than a III/V compound system. It was to take some four decades 
until Ge-Si HBTs were finally becoming commercially available, long after de- 
vices based on III/V compounds had done so.

B. Wide-gap emitter
The proposed graded-gap base structure was far beyond the technologies 
then available, a situation that was to remain unchanged for decades. The 
only possibility one of my colleagues — Mr. Alfons Hahnlein — could envisage

                   Herbert Kroemer         453



















Figure 2. P-n-p transistor with a base region with a graded gap, to speed up minority carrier flow  
from emitter to collector [from Kroemer (1957a)]. P-n-p transistors were the preferred design 
for the Ge-based transistors of the mid-50's.


was a design in which the emitter was made from a wider-gap semiconductor 
than the base, with a quasi-abrupt transition at the interface between the two, 
leading to a band diagram as in Fig. 3, in essence — but unknowingly — re-in- 
venting Shockley's design.
  It was of course obvious that the objective of putting a drift field into the 
base of the transistor could not be achieved in this way. But on reflecting 
about what exactly might be the properties of such a structure, I realized that 
a wide-gap emitter has advantages of its own (Kroemer, 1957b; 1982): One of 
the problems with all bipolar transistors is minimizing the highly undesirable 
back-injection of majority carriers from the base (electrons in a p-n-p transis-



















               --
Figure 3. Wide-gap emitter. The energy gap variation has been compressed into a quasi-abrupt 
transition at the emitter-to-base interface. The base region still has a uniform energy gap without 
the transport-aiding quasi-field, but there is now a potential barrier for the escape of electrons  
from the base into the emitter that is larger than the barrier for holes entering the base from the 
emitter.

454            Physics 2000

tor) into the emitter. In a homojunction transistor, this requirement sharply 
limits the base doping, which has other undesirable consequences, like a 
large base access resistance. A wide-gap emitter greatly suppresses this back- 
injection current: Expressed in terms, not of the quasi-electric forces, but of 
the associated potentials, any electrons escaping from the base into the emit- 
ter must overcome a higher potential barrier than the holes entering the base 
from the emitter. As a result, the electron escape current density is reduced 
roughly by a factor exp(—AEG/kT), where AEG is the difference in energy 
gaps. This is very effective: An easily achieved energy gap difference of 0.2eV
 8k7) implies a reduction by a factor e-8= 1/3000.
 Given this reduction, it now becomes possible to dope the base much more 
heavily, to reduce the base resistance. But in the presence of the inevitable 
junction capacitances, a reduction of base resistance reduces the RC time 
constants of the device, and thereby enhances its speed .
 Because of the much greater technological simplicity of the wide-gap emit- 
ter design over the graded-base design, it was the wide-gap emitter design that 
dominated HBT technology until recently, but the highest-performance 
HBTs now use both approaches (Kroemer, 1983).

C. Follow-up
Because of the absence of any credible technology, I did not follow up the 
above 1954 ideas until three years later, after I had joined RCA Laboratories 
in Princeton, NJ. I realized the generality of the design principle outlined 
above, and wrote the RCA Review paper referred to earlier (Kroemer, 1957a). 
The paper was almost totally ignored, not only because the RCA Review was a 
somewhat obscure journal, but probably even more because I myself some- 
how never explicitly referred to the paper (nor to its 1954 precursor) in my 
own subsequent work until about 40 years later (Kroemer, 1996). The general 
design principle itself was extensively discussed in a 1982 HBT review 
(Kroemer, 1982), but without reference to the 1954 paper and the 1957 RCA 
Review paper.
 The 1957 paper of mine that is widely cited was a second paper in that year, 
which gives a detailed analysis of the wide-gap emitter version of the HBT 
(Kroemer, 1957b). Having been published in a more visible journal, it drew 
considerable attention, and stimulated several attempts by others to realize 
the wide-gap emitter version of the HBT during the '60s. Unfortunately, 
technology was still not ready, and none of these early attempts led to any- 
thing useful. By 1970, people seemed to have largely given up.
 While at RCA, I also made an unsuccessful attempt to build a Ge transistor 
with a Ge-Si alloy emitter, which might be sufficiently amusing (and charac- 
teristic of the primitive state of 1957 technology) to be told here (Kroemer, 
1957c). The idea was to utilize the fact that the Au-Si phase diagram exhibits 
a low-melting (370 °C) eutectic. I prepared such a eutectic, smashed the fair- 
ly brittle material with a hammer into a coarse powder, placed small grains of 
the powder onto a Ge chip, and alloyed the combination at a temperature 
somewhere between 500 °C and 600 °C. The Au-Si alloy would then melt and

                    Herbert Kroerner        455


penetrate into the G-e chip, dissolving some Ge. Upon cooling, a Ge-Si alloy 
emitter would re-crystallize (Fig. 4). I actually got one or two transistors to 
work, but as a rule, the large thermal strains generated during the solidifica- 
tion of the eutectic caused the Ge chip to crack. The attempt was sufficiently 
unsuccessful that I never published the work. It was followed up by Diedrich 
and rotten (1961), who knew about my work, but the technology clearly was 
unpromising, and Si-Ge HIM had to wait several decades for their practical 
realization.


                   Au-Si Eutectic




           Cracks              Cracks


                       Re-Grown Si-Ge Alloy
           Ge Substrate      I 


Figure 4. Attempt to realize a Ge transistor with a Ge-Si alloy emitter. A piece of Au-Si eutectic was 
alloyed into a Ge base, forming a Si-Ge alloy emitter upon cooling. From Kroemer (1957c).



IV. DOUBLE-HETEROSTRUCTURE LASER

Neither the graded-gap HBT nor the wide-gap emitter HBT draw on the full 
power of the idea expressed in the general design principle that the quasi- 
electric fields `enable the device designer to obtain effects that are basically impos- 
sible to obtain using way "real" electric fields.' They represent major improve- 
ments, alright, but do they represent something basically impossible otherwise?
 An example of something that was indeed truly impossible to achieve 
otherwise emerged abruptly in March 1963. I was working at Varian 
Associates in Palo Alto at the time, and a colleague of mine — Dr. Sol Miller — 
had taken a strong interest in the new semiconductor junction lasers that had 
emerged in 1962, a topic then outside my own range of interests. In a collo- 
quium on the topic he gave a beautiful review of what had been achieved, not 
failing to point out that successful laser action required either low tempera- 
tures or short low-duty-cycle pulses, usually both. Asked what the chances 
were to achieve continuous operation at room temperature, Miller replied 
that certain experts had concluded that this was fundamentally impossible.
 It is instructive to review this argument here. Consider the (highly over- 
simplified) energy band diagram of a GaAs p-n junction, heavily doped on 
both sides, and forward-biased to the point that flatband conditions were 
reached (Fig. 5). Electrons then diffuse from the n-type side to the p-type 
side, and holes diffuse in the opposite direction, creating a certain concen- 
tration of electron-hole pairs in the junction region proper; their recombina- 
tion would cause light emission. But in order to obtain laser action, a popula-

456                Physics 2000


         Electrons
    •■••••■••••• 
    000ceoiD0000
          Donors


                                   Light


                              Acceptors
                          ocepocaciooisca 
                        oo 0 00 0 000 0
                                Holes
Figure 5. Schematic energy band diagram of a p-n hornojunction forward-biased to flatband con- 
ditions, creating a high concentration of electron-hole pairs in the vicinity of the junction plane, 
leading to emission of recombination radiation.



Lion inversion has to be achieved, which means that, in the active region, the 
occupation probability of the lowest states in the conduction band has to be 
higher than that of the highest states in the valence band. A necessary condi- 
tion for such a population inversion is a forward bias larger than the energy 
gap. But even then, a population inversion is hard to achieve in an ordinary 
p-n junction. First of all, the electron concentration in the active region will 
always be lower than in the n-type doped region, with an analogous limitation 
for the holes. Inversion, therefore, requires degenerate doping on both sides. 
But even with degenerate doping, both the electrons and holes would diffuse 
out of the active region immediately into the adjacent oppositely doped re- 
gion, preventing a population inversion from building up. Increasing the 
forward bias would not help much, because it would increase the rate of out 
  just as much as the rate of injection.
 I immediately protested against this argument with words somewhat like 
"but that is a pile of ..., all one has to do is give the injector regions a wider 
energy gap ." As is shown in Fig. 6, such a change would cause an electron-re- 
pelling quasi-electric field to be present on the p+ side, and a similar hole-re- 
pelling barrier on the n+ side. Carrier confinement would thus be achieved.
 By increasing the forward bias further, potential wells develop for both the 
electrons and the holes (Fig. 7), with quasi-electric forces on both sides push- 
ing both electrons and holes towards the active region. As a result, electron 
and hole concentrations can become much larger than the doping levels in 
the contact regions, and it becomes readily possible to create the population 
inversion necessary for laser action. This double-heterostructure (DH) laser 
finally represented a device truly impossible with only the real electric fields 
available in homostructures; note that the idea for it arose essentially at the 
instant I had been made aware that there was a problem.
 I wrote up a paper describing the DH idea, along with a patent application.

                  Herbert Kroemer         457


         Electrons
    ••••••••••••• •000ecleGoeioe


          Donors


                                  Light


                             Acceptors 
                          0000e000000
                   00 0000000000000
                               Holes
Figure 6. Carrier confinement in a double heterostructure, due to the presence of quasi-electric 
potential barriers at the ends of the light-emitting active region, preventing the outflow of in-  
jected electrons and holes, without interfering with the flow of majority carriers from the injec- 
tor regions.



-The paper was submitted to Applied Physics Letters, where it was rejected. I was 
persuaded not to fight the rejection, but to submit the paper to the 
Proceedings of the IEEE instead, where it was published (Kroemer, 1963) — but 
largely ignored. Fig. 8 shows the band diagram actually published.
 The patent was issued in 1967 (Kroemer, 1967). It is probably a better pa- 
per than the Proc. EEEletter. It expired in 1985.




       Electrons
    • • • • •
      o ® o ®     O. ••
        Donors




                                  Light



                              Acceptors


                             o 0 0 0 io 
                               Holes
Figure 7. With a further increase of the forward bias, potential wells form for both electrons and 
holes, which permit the accumulation of the injected carriers to degenerate concentrations 
much higher than the values in the injector regions.

458                                                                                     Physics 2000



                                                                                                           AB
                                                 t,
                                                 0 I _I                  _ _                               Electron Flow                                                      Electron Quasi
                                                 i                                                                   /            I                                              Fermi Level


                                                                                                                                 0                    CII


                                                     F 

       Hole Quasi                                                  Hole Flow
       Fermi Level                                                                                                                                       1 
                                                                                        AB

Figure 8. Band diagram of the double-heterostructure laser, as originally published (Kroemer, 
1963).




       Once again, here was an idea far ahead of any technology to realize it. DH 
lasers operating continuously at room temperature were finally demonstrated 
in 1970, first by Alferov et al. (1970), and shortly afterwards by Hayashi et al. 

(1970). For the history of the experimental work, see Alferov (2001); Alferov 
(1996); Casey and Panish (1978).
       For reasons discussed below, I myself was not able to be a participant in the 
technological realization of the idea. For the next 10 years I worked on re- 
search on the Gunn effect, to return to heterostructures in the mid-70s.



V. ON HOW NOT TO JUDGE NEW TECHNOLOGY

When I proposed to develop the technology for the DH laser, I was refused 
the resources to do so, on the grounds that "this device could not possibly 
have any practical applications," or words to that effect. By hindsight, it is of 
course obvious just how wrong this assessment was.
       It was really a classical case of judging a fundamentally new technology, not 
by what new applications it might create, but merely by what it might do for 
already-existing applications. This is extraordinarily short-sighted, but the 
problem is pervasive, as old as technology itself. The DH laser was simply an- 
other example in a long chain of similar examples. Nor will it be the last. I 
therefore believe it is worthwhile to say a few words about this kind of argu- 
ment here.
       Any detailed look at history provides staggering evidence for what I have 
called, on another occasion (Kroemer, 1995), the Lemma of New Technology:

                                                            The principal applications of any 
                       sufficiently new and innovative technology always have been 
                                                                     — and will continue to be — 
                                                     applications created by that technology.

As a rule, such applications have indeed arisen — the DH laser is just a good 
recent example — although usually not immediately.

               Herbert Kroemer     459

 But this means that we must take a long-term look when judging the appli- 
cations potential of any new technology: It must not be judged simply by how 
it might fit into already existing applications, where the new discovery may 
have little chance to be used in the face of competition with already-en- 
trenched technology. Dismissing it on the grounds that it has no known ap- 
plications will only stifle progress towards those applications that will grow out 
of that technology.
 I do not think we can realistically predict which new devices and applica- 
tions may emerge, but I believe we can create an environment encouraging 
progress, by not always asking immediately what any new science might be 
good for (and cutting off the funds if no answer full of fanciful promises is 
forthcoming). In particular, we must educate our funding agencies about this 
historical fact. This may not be easy, but it is necessary. We must make it an ac- 
ceptable answer to the quest for applications to defer that answer, and that at 
the very least a search for applications should be considered a part of the re- 
search itself, rather than a result to be promised in advance. Nobody has ex- 
pressed this last point better than David Mermin in his recent put-down of so- 
called "strategic research" (Mermin, 1999):
"I am awaiting the day when people remember the fact that discovery does not 
    work by deciding what you want and then discovering it."
What is never acceptable — and what we must refrain from doing — is an at- 
tempt to justify the research by promising credibility-stretching mythical im- 
provements in existing applications. Most such claims are not likely to be rea- 
listic and are easily refuted; they only trigger criticism of just how unrealistic 
the promises are, thereby discrediting the whole work.
 Ultimately, progress in applications is not deterministic, but opportunistic, ex- 
ploiting for new applications whatever new science and technology happen to 
be coming along.

VI. CONSTRAINTS
1. Lattice Matching
Let me now turn to some of the problems in implementing heterostructures.
 When two materials with significantly different lattice parameters are 
grown upon each other, whether graded or not, huge strains rapidly build up 
with increasing thickness, and eventually misfit dislocations will form, a defect 
without any redeeming features. As a result, the need for lattice matching is 
all but obvious. The problem is somewhat less severe in modern structures 
calling for very thin layers (see below); but even there, the lattice-matched 
case serves as the conceptual point of departure.
 Historically, the importance of lattice matching was recognized almost 
from the beginning, especially for bipolar devices such as lasers. In my 1967 
DH laser patent (Kroemer, 1967), I gave a table listing numerous semicon- 
ductors in the order of increasing lattice parameter (see Table II); the ac- 
companying text in the patent called for semiconductor pairs with a lattice

460                     Physics 2000

mismatch below 0.01A 0.2 %) as the most promising ones, indicating a
recognition of the stringency of the lattice matching demand. The possibility 
to achieve lattice matching by alloying was explicitly recognized, though.

Table H. Partial copy of the 1963 table of semiconductors ordered by lattice constant (sec- 
ond column) from ref. (Kroemer, 1967). The third column gives the increase in lattice con- 
stant relative to the preceding material. Note that no distinction is made between column- 
IV elements, the III-V compounds, and the II-VI compounds. Also, the 1963 lattice constant 
of AlAs was significantly in error: The correct room-temperature value (5.661A) is actually 
0.02A larger than the GaAs value, and the difference is much less at typical crystal growth 
temperatures. [Only the semiconductors up to ZnSe are shown here; the complete 1963 
table can be found in Kroemer (1996)].
Semiconductor         a [A]       Aa [A]
ZnS                   5.406
Si                    5.428       .022
GaP                   5.450       .022
A1P                   5.46        .01
AlAs                  5.63        .17
GaAs                  5.653       .02
Ge                    5.658       .005
ZnSe                  5.667       .009


Ironically, the 1963 literature value for the lattice constant of AlAs was incor- 
rect. As a result, the GaAs-AlAs pair initially did not seem to meet the pro- 
posed stringent criterion, and the known poor stability of (binary) AlAs 
against oxygen did not help. It took some time to recognize its promise, not 
so much as a binary material, but as an alloy with GaAs, which greatly reduced 
the oxidation problems, and reduced the lattice mismatch to a completely 
negligible level.
  A more instructive way to represent the information of Table II, including 
energy gaps as well, is in terms of what some of us call The Map of the World, a 
display of the energy gaps of semiconductors of interest vs. their lattice con- 
stants (Fig. 9), with interconnect lines shown to represent binary alloys.
  Much of the reason for the continued dominance of the (A1,Ga)As alloy 
system in heterostructure studies is precisely the "Great Crystallographic 
Accident" that AlAs and GaAs have essentially the same lattice parameter. 
This natural lattice matching means, in particular, that an ideal substrate is 
readily available for the growth of such heterostructures, namely bulk GaAs, 
obtainable as high-quality single crystals with low dislocation densities, espe- 
cially in semi-insulating form. If there remains one bad aspect to the (A1,Ga)As 
system, it is the obnoxious chemical affinity of aluminum to oxygen, the 
source of many residual defects in (A1,Ga)As. Following a 1983 suggestion by 
myself (Kroemer, 1983), the use of (Ga,In)P lattice-matched to GaAs has re- 
cently drawn some attention as an alternative to (A1,Ga)As, especially in 
HBTs, for which the band lineups at the (Ga,In)P-GaAs interface are more 
favorable than those of (A1,Ga)As-GaAs.
  A second natural substrate is InP, widely used for both optoelectronic and

Herbert Kraemer	
461
Lattice Constant [A]
Figure 9. Partial "Map of the World," plotting the energy gap of various III-V compounds vs. lat- 
tice constant. The map omits the "Old-World Continents" of the column-IV and the II-VI semi- 
conductors, and the "New World" of the nitrides.
high-speed device applications that call for energy gaps less than that of GaAs.  
There is no binary III-V compound lattice-matched to InP, but InP is widely  
used in devices, combined with a wide variety of alloys ranging from  
(Ga,In)As to Al (As,Sb).
With the emergence of quantum wells, superlattices, and other structures  
calling for very thin layers, the issue of strain induced by lattice mismatch has  
lost some of its tyrannical dominance. In sufficiently thin structures, remark- 
ably large strains can be accommodated without dislocation formation, to the  
point that the modification of the energy band structure of a heterostructure  
by deliberate introduction of strain has become an important device design  
principle in its own right. The recent evolution of successful Si-Ge HBTs is  
perhaps the most dramatic triumph of this idea (see, for example, Abstreiter  
(1996); Konig (1996), but other examples are close behind, both in field- 
effect transistors (FETs) and in photonic devices. Some of the recent develop- 
ments in self-assembling quantum dots are explicitly based on utilizing strain  
already during the crystal growth process.
2. Valence Matching
If lattice matching were the only constraint, the Ge-GaAs system would be the 
ideal hetero-system, as was in fact believed by some of us — including myself — 
in the early-'60s. At that time, the most successful heterojunctions that had
5.6 5.7 5.8 5.9 6.0 6.1 6.2 6.3
6.4 6.5
5.4 5.5
III-V Semiconductor Materials
2.5
GaP
1.0
0.5
Energy Gap [eV]
•
• 
•

462            Physics 2000

been demonstrated were the Ge-on-GaAs heterojunctions studied by Ander- 
son (1960), suggesting a bright future for this system (the term heterojunction  
seems to have appeared first in Anderson's papers). Table II reflects this idea, 
in the form of combining III—V compounds, II—VI compounds, and group-W 
semiconductors into a common table, making the GaAs-Ge system appear to 
be the most promising candidate It took a few years to realize that this was a 
blind alley — and why.
 It is not a questions of chemical incompatibility, or even of cross-doping ef-  
fects. Covalent bonds between Ge on the one hand, and Ga or As on the 
other are readily formed, but they are what I would like to call valence-mis- 
matched, meaning that the number of electrons provided by the atoms is not 
equal to the canonical number of exactly two electrons per covalent bond. 
Hence the bonds themselves are not electrically neutral, as first pointed out 
in a 1978 "must-read paper" by Harrison et al. (1978).
 Consider a hypothetical idealized (001)-oriented interface between Ge and 
GaAs,.with Ge to the left of a mathematical plane, and GaAs to the right (Fig. 
10). In GaAs, an As atom brings along 5 electrons (= 5/4 electrons per bond), 
and expects to be surrounded by 4 Ga atoms, each of which brings along 3 
electrons (3/4 per bond), adding up to the correct number of 8/4 = 2 elec- 
trons per Ga-As covalent bond. But when, at a (001) interface, an As atom has 
two Ge atoms as bonding partners, each Ge atom brings along 1 electron per 
bond, which is one-half electron too many. Loosely speaking, the As atom 
"does not know" whether it is a constituent of GaAs, or a donor in Ge.
 As a result, each Ge-As bond acts as a donor with a fractional charge, and 
each Ge-Ga bond as an acceptor with the opposite fractional charge. To be 
electrically neutral, a Ge-GaAs interface would have to have equal numbers of 
both charges, not only averaged over large distances, but locally. Given chem- 
ical bonding preferences, such an arrangement will not occur naturally dur- 
ing epitaxial growth. If only one kind of bonds were present, as in Fig. 10, the 
interface charge would support an electric field of 4 x 10 7 V/cm. Such a 
huge field would force atomic re-arrangements during growth, trying to 
equalize the number of Ge-As and Ge-Ga bonds. However, these re-arrange- 
ments will never go to completion, but will leave behind ill-defined locally 
fluctuating residual charges, with deleterious consequences for any device ap- 
plication. Interfaces with perfect bond charge cancellation are readily drawn 
on paper; but in practice there are always going to remain some local devia- 
tions from the perfect charge compensation, leading to performance-de- 
grading random potential fluctuations along the interface.
 Although Harrison et al. discuss only the GaAs-Ge interface, their argument 
applies to other interfaces combining semiconductors from different 
columns of the periodic table. In the specific case of compound semiconduc- 
tor growth on a column-IV elemental semiconductor, the additional problem 
of antiphase domains on the compound side arises (see, for example, Kroe- 
mer (1987) ).
 The above discussion pertained to the most-widely used (001)-oriented in- 
terface. The interface charge at a valence-mismatched interface actually de-

                  Herbert Krvemer         463



























               ► C001]
Figure 10. Departure from electrical neutrality at a "mathematically planar" (001)-oriented 
Ge/GaAs interface. The different atomic species — Ga or As atoms (white and black circles) and 
Ge atoms (shaded circles) — do not bring along the correct number of electrons to form electri- 
cally neutral Ga-Ge or As-Ge covalent bonds of 2 electrons per bond. From Harrison et al. (1978).



pends on the crystallographic orientation. It has been shown by Wright et al. 
that an ideal (112) interface exhibits neither an interface charge, nor anti- 
phase domains, and it was in fact possible to demonstrate GaP-on-Si inter- 
faces that had a sufficiently low defect density that they operated as emitters 
in a GaP-on-Si HBT (Wright et al., 1982; 1984). However, the performance 
was still sufficiently poor that the approach was not pursued further.


VII. MOLECULAR BEAM EPITAXY AND ABRUPT HETEROSTRUCTURES
The 1970 DH laser demonstration was accomplished by liquid-phase epitaxy 
(LPE), a beautifully simple technology, but with severe limitations. The big 
technological breakthrough for heterostructures came only with the emer- 
gence of molecular beam epitaxy (MBE) as a practical crystal growth tech- 
nology, largely pioneered by Al Cho (followed later by organometallic vapor 
phase epitaxy). In contrast to LPE, MBE permitted combining a wide range 
of semiconductors, even such hetero-valent combinations as GaP and GaAs 
on Si. Moreover, it offered a very high degree of control over the local com- 
position, almost on an atomic layer scale. Suddenly, we could realize experi- 
mentally almost any band diagram we could draw, at least in the growth di- 
rection (lateral control on a similar scale remains an elusive goal to this day). 
By 1980, the progress in heterostructures had been so large, that I was able to

