474

TURNING POTENTIAL INTO REALITIES:
THE INVENTION OF THE INTEGRATED CIRCUIT

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000 
by
JACK S. KILBY
Texas Instruments Incorporated, 12500 TI Boulevard, Dallas, TX 75243-4136, 
USA.



Thank you for that kind introduction and welcome. It is an honor to share 
the Nobel Prize in Physics and to speak with you today. My title for this lecture  
is "Turning Potential into Realities: The Invention of the Integrated Circuit."
 The field of electronics had strong potential when I invented the integrat- 
ed circuit in 1958. The reality of what people have done with integrated cir- 
cuits has gone far beyond what anyone — including myself imagined possible 
at the time.
 Charles Townes won the Nobel for his work with laser technology, and he 
summed up how I feel. Townes said, "It's like the beaver told the rabbit as 
they stared at the Hoover Dam. 'No, I didn't build it myself. But it's based on 
an idea of mine! —
 At its most basic level, the integrated circuit manipulates the characteristics 
of electricity. In fact, the entire field of electronics is about manipulating the 
flow of electrons — in other words, making electricity perform advanced kinds 
of work. A long line of people have been involved in harnessing electricity, 
from William Gilbert, who first used the word "electricity" 400 years ago, to 
Thomas Edison, who built one of the first practical electrical generators in 
the 1880s.
 The invention of the vacuum tube launched the electronics industry. 
Sometimes called "electron tubes," these devices controlled the flow of elec- 
trons in a vacuum. They initially were used to amplify signals for radio and 
other audio devices. This allowed broadcast radio to reach the masses in the 
1920s. Vacuum tubes steadily spread into other devices, and the first tube was 
used as a switch in calculating machines in 1939.
 By the end of World War II, it was obvious that the cost, bulk and reliabili- 
ty of vacuum tubes would limit commercial and military electronic systems. A 
naval destroyer built in 1937 had 60 vacuum tubes on board. Even the B-29, 
probably the most complex equipment used in the war, had only around 300 
vacuum tubes. Most of those were single-function tubes.
 Integration was a low priority at that point. However, electronic systems 
rapidly grew more complex. The post-war destroyers of 1952 had more than 
3,200 vacuum tubes. And, of course, the ENIAC computer of 1946 was a va- 
cuum tube monster. It was the world's fastest computer for years, but it con-

               Jack S. Kilby      475



























Figure 1. Vacuum tube.
tained more than 17,000 vacuum tubes, weighed 60,000 pounds, occupied 
16,200 cubic feet, and consumed 174 kilowatts of electricity — equivalent to 
233 horsepower.
 Vacuum tubes clearly could not support any significant evolution of com- 
puters. People were able to visualize and design systems that — if realized with 
the prevailing technology — would be too big, too heavy, consume too much 
power and simply get too hot to work. And because these components would 
have to be assembled from tens or hundreds of thousands of individual parts, 
they would have been unreliable and unaffordable [11.
 By the mid-1950s, these problems were visible to many in the industry, and 
many researchers began seeking a solution. Military applications played a ma- 
jor role in the development of electronics. I think the Nobel Peace Prize is 
important, because it honors people who work to bring peace. And peace 
means we can use electronics to benefit mankind rather than wage war.
 Having said that, the early proponents of miniaturized electronic systems 
were the U.S. military and space agencies. Most of the approaches tended to 
make individual components smaller, so collectively these were called minia- 
turization programs. Each had a common objective — to build complete elec- 
tronic circuits.

476             Physics 2000






















Figure 2. Circuit components.

  T.R. Reid has pointed out that building a circuit is like building a sentence [2]. 
There are certain standard components — nouns, verbs and adjectives in a 
sentence, and resistors, capacitors, transistors and diodes in a circuit. Each 
has its own function By connecting the components in different ways, you 
can get sentences, or circuits, that perform in different ways. Over the years, 
each component had developed a specialized set of manufacturing processes.
  A huge step forward came in 1948, when Bell Labs unveiled the transistor. 
And in creating solid-state components, the race for miniaturized electronic 
circuits intensified.
  Transistors rely on the nearly free travel of electrons through crystalline 
solids known as semiconductors. Semiconductors, such as silicon or germa- 
nium, have electrical properties that are between conductors and insulators. 
Not surprisingly, that's why they're called "semi" conductors.
  We can change the electrical characteristics of semiconductors through a 
process called "doping," which carefully adds impurities to predetermined 
areas [3] . Starting with pure silicon, one dopant will add electrons to a par- 
ticular area. A different dopant will take electrons away to create holes in an 
area. In either case, we increase the conductivity of the basic material.
  Semiconductor material that conducts by free electrons is known as n-type 
material. Semiconductors that conduct through electron deficiencies are 
called p-type material. At its simplest level, a transistor is a "sandwich" of these 
materials, and the components are frequently encased in ceramic.
  As with most technologies, the techniques for making transistors made

                  Jack S. Kilby         477

            Semiconductor material




Emitter C           P               Collector



                    U
                    Base
Figure 3. Creating a transistor.

steady progress. The first transistors were known as point contact. They were 
very primitive by subsequent standards, but they did provide the initial break- 
through.
 Later techniques included the grown-junction transistor — pictured here, 
and which will crop up again later in the lecture. In these transistors, a single 
crystal of germanium was grown and doped at the same time.
 The crystal was pulled from a melt containing n-type impurities, and then 
p-type impurities were added to the molten germanium. Later, more n-type 
was added. This created an n-doped crystal with a thin p-type layer within it. 
The crystal was then cut into small blocks, and each block formed a single 
NPN transistor.
 Subsequent developments included grown-diffused, alloy, surface barriers 
and eventually the mesa and planar types.

















     .   ; -
Figure 4. Grown junction transistor.

478            Physics 2600

  The earliest transistors were made from germanium. But silicon offered 
some big advantages in terms of much higher operating temperatures, break- 
down voltage and power-handling ability. The problem was that silicon was 
more difficult to refine because of its higher melting point.
  Shortly before I joined Texas Instruments, that company solved the puzzle, 
making silicon transistors commercially available in the mid-1950s. But, I'm 
getting ahead of my story.
  In 1947, I graduated from the University of Illinois with a degree in electri- 
cal engineering. That was one year before Bell Labs unveiled the transistor. 
That meant that I started my career at a very exciting time. But my formal 
training was in electrical power, though I had taken some vacuum-tube clas- 
ses.
  Fortunately, I also had studied engineering physics, because I felt it might 
be more useful than knowing how to connect three-phase transformers! 
Looking back, I'm glad I took those physics classes.
  I wanted to work in electronics, in part because of a childhood interest. My 
dad ran a power company that served a wide area in rural Kansas, and he 
used amateur radio in his work. I found it very interesting.
  In fact, it was during an ice storm during my teens, when customers 
throughout his area lost power, that I first saw how radio — and by extension, 
electronics — could really impact people's lives, keeping them informed and 
connected, giving them hope.
  After graduation, I was hired by Centralab, a Milwaukee-based electronics 
manufacturer. They made parts for radios, televisions and hearing aids. 
Centralab was a fortunate choice for me, because they worked with hybrid cir- 
cuits — an early form of miniaturization.
  Centralab also developed what would become known as thick-film hybrid 
circuits. In this process, silver paint was deposited on a ceramic substrate — or 
base layer — to form conductors. Carbon-based inks formed resistors. Small 
capacitors were formed in the substrate, and larger ones were attached. The 
necessary vacuum tubes could then be attached with sockets or soldered di- 
rectly to the substrate [4].
  Centralab was ideal for me in another way. The group I worked in was 
small, so I saw the entire process, from engineering through sales and pro- 
duction. My initial duties included the design and product engineering work 
on hearing aid amplifiers and resistor-capacitor networks for television sets.
  Since it was a new field, making inventions was easy. Almost anything that 
departed from previous designs was novel and probably could be patented. In 
this period, I received about a dozen patents, the most notable being a ca- 
pacitor design using the first reduced titanates and a technique for automat- 
ically adjusting resistors using sandblasting.
  In 1951, Bell Labs held their first transistor symposium and began licensing 
transistor technology for a $25,000 fee. At this time, Centralab became inter- 
ested in making transistors and acquired a license.
  I felt the transistor pointed the way to the future, and I wanted to be there. 
After some home study and some formal training that included Bell Labs

                Jack S. Kilby      479

symposia, I became the leader of a three-man project to build transistors and 
incorporate them into Centralab products.
 We built a reduction furnace, crystal puller and zone refiner. This was rela- 
tively complex at the time, but growing semiconductor crystals is similar in 
principle to the crystal-growing kit you might buy for a child today.
 We used our new equipment to make germanium alloy devices. We mount- 
ed unprotected transistors in a plastic carrier, which was a novel design. 
Environmental protection was achieved by using the ceramic substrate as part 
of the hermetic seal.
 By 1957, Centralab had established a small production facility that sold 
small quantities of amplifiers for hearing aids and some other applications. 
They were even marginally profitable. It was clear, however, that major ex- 
penditures would soon be required, especially for the military market that was 
becoming a major opportunity. The military required silicon devices, which 
added to the necessary capital expense.
 By 1958, I had decided to leave and began looking for another job. I talked 
with several companies and found that IBM had committed to technology 
similar to the thick-film work I had done at Centralab. I felt they had made a 
basic mistake by choosing a substrate that was much too small. Motorola was 
quite interested and thought I could work part-time on my own ideas about 
miniaturization.
 Texas Instruments was more enthusiastic than the others and offered me a 
job working in miniaturization full-time.
 When I started at TI in May of 1958, I had no vacation coming that year. 
So I worked through the period when about 90 percent of the workforce took 
what we called "mass vacation." I was left with my thoughts and imagina- 
tion [5] .
 I already had reviewed the earlier attempts at miniaturization. The vast ma- 
jority of existing transistors held no potential for integration since their elec- 
trodes were on different surfaces — offering no realistic possibility of inter- 
connecting them.
 In the early 1950s, the Englishman Geoff Dummer of the Royal Radar 
Establishment suggested that all electronics could be made as a single block. 
He mentioned the use of amplifying layers, resistive layers and things of that 
sort. The electrical functions would be connected directly by cutting out areas 
of the various layers [6]. It was a remarkable statement. But Dummer gave no 
proposal for how to do it.
 In 1956, Dummer gave a small contract to a British manufacturer to build 
such a device. They were completely unsuccessful, partly because they worked 
with the grown junction technology I mentioned earlier and tried to connect 
the various layers.
 While his device failed, Dummer was on target in general. The body resis- 
tance of the semiconductor itself — and the capacitance of the junctions be- 
tween the positive and negative regions that could be created within it — 
could be combined with transistors to make a complete circuit out of the 
same material.

480             Physics 2000

  My contribution was taking this idea and making it a practical reality.
  While my first duties at TI were not precisely defined, I was free to choose 
an approach in the general area of miniaturization. The company made tran- 
sistors, resistors and capacitors. Since the company could make semiconduc- 
tors cost effectively, I thought it would be worthwhile to try and make every- 
thing from semiconductors.
  This was contrary to most other major efforts at the time, which fell into 
three basic categories.
  One group felt the main problem was the assembly of individual parts, and 
that by making all parts the same size and shape, they could automate the as- 
sembly process. A second group thought that thin-films were the way to go — 
a more modern form of the thick-film technology used at Centralab. Both of 
these approaches would have used conventional transistors and assembled 
them to the other components.
  A third group felt a more radical approach must be taken. They felt that 
our knowledge of material was now complete enough so that entirely new 
structures could be invented to perform circuit functions. A quartz crystal, 
which performed the functions of an inductor and capacitor, was the favorite 
example [7]
  It was clear to me that one of the major problems with all of the existing ap- 
proaches to microminiaturization was that they involved different materials 
and fabrication processes. I began to consider an approach that would reduce 
the number of both.
  It was obvious that transistors and diodes could be made of semiconductor 
materials. Discrete — or standalone — resistors and capacitors could also be 
made from semiconductors. However, that would be relatively expensive, and 
neither would perform as well as the best ones made with more conventional 
techniques and materials. For example, titanium nitride was better for resis- 
tors, and Teflon made better capacitors.
  Even so, since all components could be made with a single kind of material, 
it was possible to consider making them all within a single piece of material. By 
connecting them properly, complete circuits could be formed.
  On July 24, 1958, I described in my lab notebook what would come to be 
known as "The Monolithic Idea." It stated that circuit elements such as resis 



            -

           -

             f.



Figure 5. First integrated circuitinotebook.

                Jack S. Kilby       481

tors, capacitors, distributed capacitors and transistors — if all made of the 
same material — could be included in a single chip.
 I quickly sketched a proposed design for a flip-flop circuit using compo- 
nents all made from silicon. Resistors were provided by the bulk resistance in 
the silicon, and capacitors were formed at the p-n junctions [8].
 I showed the design to my direct supervisor, Willis Adcock, upon his return 
from vacation. He was enthused, but skeptical. He asked for proof that cir- 
cuits made entirely from semiconductors would work.
 Therefore, I built up a circuit using discrete — or separate — silicon ele- 
ments, starting with packaged grown-junction transistors. I formed resistors 
by cutting small bars of silicon and etching them to the required values. 
Meanwhile, capacitors were cut from diffused silicon power transistor wafers, 
which had been metallized on both sides.
 Once assembled, the unit was demonstrated to Adcock on August 28, 1958. 
Fortunately, the test proved that all circuit elements could be built of semi- 
conductor materials.
 But since I had used discrete components, it was not, of course, an inte- 
grated circuit. I immediately set out to build a truly integrated structure.
 At the time, TI was very strong in grown-junction devices and had just 
begun to work seriously on diffused structures. One silicon transistor, a pow- 
er device with an alloyed emitter, was in production. Several small-signal ger- 
manium devices also were in production. The emitter and base contacts were 
evaporated through metal masks. Mesas were etched after hand masking with 
black wax.
 I obtained several of these wafers, already diffused and with the contacts in 
place. By choosing the circuit, I was able to lay out two structures that would 
use the existing contacts on the wafers.
 The first circuit attempted was a phase-shift oscillator, a favorite demon- 
stration vehicle for linear circuits at the time. Technicians Pat Harbrecht and 
Tom Yeargan cut the wafers into bars about 0.12 inches by 0.4 inches. Metal 
tabs were alloyed to the back of the bar to provide contacts to the bulk resis- 
tors.
 Black wax was applied by hand to mask the mesas, one for the transistor, 
and a larger one for a diffused region forming a distributed resistor-capacitor 
network.
 On September 12, 1958, the first three oscillators of this type were com- 
pleted. When power was applied, the first unit oscillated at about 1.3 mega- 
hertz.
 To show that digital circuits could be built, the same techniques were used 
to build a flip-flop. That unit was completed on September 19.
 By early October, we had begun designing a new germanium flip-flop inte- 
grated circuit. This unit was the first to be built entirely from scratch. It used 
bulk resistors, junction capacitors and mesa transistors. The first working 
units were completed early in 1959 and were later used to publicly announce 
the "Solid Circuit" concept in March of 1959.
 Shortly thereafter, Robert Noyce of Fairchild Semiconductor showed the

482            Physics 2000

desirability of using the planar process with metal leads over the oxide, and 
several others, such as folks from Westinghouse, contributed to the integrated 
circuit field.
 Today, it is a little hard to believe, but in 1959 as we began to announce this 
idea — and Fairchild publicly discussed Noyce's innovations — there was tre- 
mendous criticism.
 At the time, it was not obvious that the monolithic semiconductor ap- 
proach was going to succeed over the others I outlined earlier. Gordon 
Moore, Noyce, a few others and myself provided the technical entertainment 
at professional meetings for the next five years as we described and debated 
the merit of the various miniaturization systems.
 There were three basic objections [9] . The first was a belief that production  
yields would always be too low to be profitable. At the time, less than 10 per-  
cent of all transistors manufactured actually worked properly. Another group 
of people felt it did not make very good use of materials, since the best resi-  
stors and transistors were not made with semiconductors. Also, the true tran- 
sistor people did not want to see their elegant devices messed up with all the 
other stuff on the chip. These arguments were difficult to counter, since they 
were basically true.
 And finally, many people working in the large companies thought if semi- 
conductor technology succeeded, all of the world's circuit designers would be 
out of work. Of course, employment of circuit designers has actually in- 
creased over the years, but they are doing their work differently than in the 
transistor era.
 The turning point came from two highly visible military programs in the 
1960s — the Apollo moon mission and the Minuteman missile. The adoption 
of integrated circuit technology by these programs was a strong endorsement.
 By 1964, a few adventurous companies had begun docking integrated cir- 
cuits into their commercial equipment. To help popularize integrated cir- 
cuits, I participated in a TI team that developed the first handheld electronic  
calculator.














Figure b. Handheld calculator.

               Jack S. Kilby      483

 Digital Equipment Corporation also was a very early user, and by the late 
1960s, most engineers had accepted the fact that integrated circuits were here 
to stay.
 As the concept was accepted, hundreds and later thousands of the best en- 
gineers in the world began to work on it.
 My lecture has focused on the environment immediately preceding and fol- 
lowing the invention of the integrated circuit.
 The innovation and development that has followed in the past 40 years has 
been more remarkable and far more rapid than all the developments in the 
prior 400 years after William Gilbert first coined the term "electricity."




















Figure 7. Increasing ICs per wafer.

 Thanks to the work by hundreds of thousands of the world's best engi- 
neers, we've not only created new applications for integrated circuits, we've  
also gotten much better at making them. New manufacturing processes have 
been devised, better transistors have been invented, and sophisticated tech- 
niques for computer-aided design have been developed. Consequently, 
progress in the field was rapid.
 The early simple chips with a dozen components grew to chips with 10,000 
components by 1970 and more than a hundred million components today. 
This progress has been accompanied by a rapid decrease in the cost of elec- 
tronic circuitry[10].
 In 1958, a single transistor cost about $10. Today, you can buy a chip with 
over 100 million transistors for about that price. Costs are almost certain to 
continue declining in the future. This decrease in cost of 100 million to one  
has greatly expanded the field of electronics.

484	
Physics 2000
Global IC Sales ($B)
Minimum Feature Size (pm)
2000
1990
1980
1970
1 000
109
2010
100
10
0.1
0.01
1960
Figure 8. Smaller features, lower cost, larger market.
Today, powerful personal computers sell for less than $1,000. And these are  
far more capable than the $10 million versions of the 1960s.
While integrated circuits are used for military applications, many more are  
used to improve the quality of life for everyone [11]. Automobiles are safer  
and emit fewer pollutants because of their integrated circuit systems. Radio  
and TV have become nearly universal, and hundreds of millions of people are  
united by the networking power of the Internet. Wireless communications  
keep people in contact with information and other people anywhere they go  
on the planet.
I believe the best is yet to come.
Today, approximately 1,000 electrons are necessary to turn an individual  
transistor on or off. By 2010, it's estimated this will be accomplished by only  
100 electrons. The 2010 projection assumes that higher dielectric constant  
materials will be introduced.
If they were not, then the continuation of geometrical scaling would ex- 
trapolate the reduction to a mere 10 electrons per transistor by 2010 and just  
one electron by 2020.
That, of course, would present a fundamental physical limitation.
Some proposed approaches around this obstacle include quantum-cellular  
automata and molecular switches, among others [12]. When we reach this  
nanometer-length scale, many people think chemically assembled configura- 
tions will begin replacing today's patterned and etched structures.
I don't really know how all that will play out. I do know that engineers in all  
corners of the world continue to refine integrated circuits while others are  
working on what might come next.
I know how they feel. In 1958, my goals were simple: to lower the cost,  
simplify the assembly, and make things smaller and more reliable. Although I  
do not consider myself responsible for all of the activity that has followed, it  
has been very satisfying to witness the integrated circuit's evolution.
I am pleased to have had even a small part in helping turn the potential of  
human creativity into practical reality.

                   Jack S. Kilby          485

REFERENCES
[1] Murphy, Bernard T., Haggan, Douglas E., Troutman, William W., From Circuit 
   Miniaturization to the Scalable IC, Proceedings of the IEEE, Vol. 88, No. 5, May 2000.
[2] Reid, T.R., The Chip: How Two Americans Invented the Microchip and Launched a Revo- 
   lution, Simon and Schuster, New York (1984).
[3] Kilby, J.S., Silicon FEB Techniques, Solid/State Design, July 1964.
[4] Roup, R.R., and Kilby, J.S., US Patent 2,841,508, issued July 1958.
[5] Kilby, J.S., Invention of the Integrated Circuit, IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, 
   Vol. Ed-23, No. 7, July 1976.
[6] Kilby, J.S., Invention of the Integrated Circuit, IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, 
   Vol. Ed-23, No. 7, July 1976.
[7] WADD Technology Notes, Molecular Dendritic Approach, Westinghouse Electric Corp. 
   Reports, February 1960 and July 1960.
[8] Kilby, J.S., Semiconductor Solid Circuits, presented at American Rocket Society 14th 
   Annual Meeting, November 1959.
[9] Kilby, J.S., Invention of the Integrated Circuit, IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, 
   Vol. Ed-23, No. 7, July 1976.
[10] Nishi, Yoshio and Doering, Robert, editors, Handbook of Semiconductor Manufacturing 
   Technology, Marcel Dekker, New York (2000).
[11] Doering, Robert, Implications of Scaling to Nanoelectronics, Workshop on Societal 
   Implications of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology.
[12] Jasinksi, J., Petroff, P., Applications Nanodevices, Nanoelectronics, and Nanosensors as re- 
   ported in Nanotechnology Research Directions: IWGN Workshop Report, Vision for Nano- 
   technology R&D in the Next Decade, 1999.

