EXPERIMENTS WITH 
HIGH-ENERGY NEUTRINO BEAMS

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1988
by
JACK STEINBERGER
CERN, Geneva, Switzerland, and Scuola Normale Superiore, Pisa, Italy






1. INTRODUCTION
High-energy neutrino beams have found intensive and varied application in 
particle physics experimentation in the last decades. This review is con- 
strained to a few of the most fruitful examples: the discovery of neutral 
currents, the measurement of the Weinberg angle, the study of weak 
currents and the consequent test of the electroweak theory, the study of 
nucleon quark structure, and the testing of quantum chromodynamics 
(QCD). Other studies such as the production of "prompt" neutrinos, the 
search for finite neutrino masses and neutrino oscillations, the search for 
heavy leptons or other new particles, or the measurement of proton and 
neutron structure functions, elastic and pseudoelastic cross-sections, and 
other exclusive processes, are not discussed here. Neutrino experiments 
have been pursued vigorously at the Brookhaven National Laboratory, at 
Fermilab, and at CERN. It is fair to say that they have made large contribu-  
tions to our understanding of particle physics.
2. NEUTRINO BEAMS
Present neutrino beams are produced in four steps: i) production of secon- 
dary hadrons in the collision of high-energy protons on a fixed target; 
ii) momentum (charge) selection and focusing of the hadrons; iii) passage of  
the beam through an (evacuated) decay region, long enough to permit a 
substantial fraction of the hadrons to decay; iv) absorption of the remaining 
hadrons and the muons that are produced along with the 'neutrinos in a 
shield of adequate thickness. The two-body decays 7r±(-)—>au±(-)-1- v(V) and  
K+ (-)--->,u+ -.-.)-F v(V) account for - 97% of the neutrino flux in present  
beams. Positive hadrons produce neutrinos, negative hadrons produce 
antineutrinos. Figures la and lb give an impression of the two hadron 
beam-forming options that are available, side by side, at CERN: a conven- 
tional, so-called narrow-band beam (NBB), and an achromatic, Van der 
Meer horn-focused, wide-band beam (WBB). The neutrino spectra pro- 
duced by these two beams are very different, as shown in Figure 2. The

488                            Physics 1988








NARROW-BAND NEUTRINO BERM
                                FLUX 
               MOMENTUM        MONITORS 19.R,L
    TARGET      SLIT






LOO GeV                                                             E
PROTON                                                              v v
BERM




                                   DECRY TUNNEL MOON SHIELD NEUTRINO
              MOMENTUM AND SIGN    nr 3011.       1,00.     DETECTOR
              SELECTION OF tr,K




WIDE-RANO NEUTRINO BERM


        TARGET HORN  REFLECTOR



   WO GeV            N
   PROTON 1=1,. 
   BERM



                  Y

               FOCUSING SIGN 
               SELECTION OF Tr,K




Figure la Sketch of narrow-band and wide-band neutrino beam layouts at CERN, showing 


disposition of primary target, focusing elements, decay region, shielding, and monitoring 


devices.






















































































Figure lb View of the neutrino beam tunnel at the CERN SPS in 1976, before operations began. 

The NBB line is seen in the centre; on the right is the pulse transformer for the WBB horn, but 

the horn itself, destined for the pedestal on the left, is not yet installed. At the far end, the 2.5 m 


diameter titanium window of the evacuated decay region can be seen.

                               Steinberge,                       489



   low
                   v Rol spectra
                   for CDHS detector 
   109             pp = 400 GeV/c
                   PLK = 200 GeV/c



g 108
0.


   io7



> 610

13


   105




   10' o 50   100  150 200  250  300
                E v [GeV]

Figure 2 Neutrino and antineutrino energy spectra, calculated for the horn-focused WBB and 
the more conventional NBB.



WBBs are characterized by high intensity, a steep (generally undesirable) 

energy fall-off, and a substantial contamination of wrong-"sign" neutrinos. 

The NBBs have lower intensity, a flat energy dependence in the contribu- 

tion from each of the two decays, and small wrong-sign background. They 

also have the important feature that the energy of the neutrino can be 

known, subject to a twofold Tc-K dichotomy, if the decay angle is known. In 

general this can be inferred from the impact parameter of the event in the 

detector.



3. DETECTORS

The low cross-sections of neutrinos are reflected in two general features of 

neutrino detectors:

   i) they are massive;

   ii) the target serves also as detector.

In the seventies, the most successful detectors were large bubble chambers. 

The most splendid of these were the cryogenic devices built at CERN and 

Fermilab, each with a volume of — 15 m', in large magnetic fields, and 

capable of operating with liquid hydrogen, deuterium, or neon. A picture 

of a typical neutrino event in the CERN chamber is shown in Figure 3. It is 

an example of the "charged-current" (CC) reaction v+Np.--Fhadrons. 

However, one of the major discoveries at CERN was made not in this but in 

a large Freon-filled bubble chamber, affectionately called Gargamelle. The 

active volume was a cylinder 4.8 m long and 1.9 m in diameter, for a volume 

of about 13 m3, inside a magnet producing a field of 2 T. Figure 4 gives 

some impression of its size.

   The bubble chamber has now been largely replaced by detectors based on 

electronic detection methods. As an example, I mention here the CDHS

490                              Physics 1988
























Figure 3 A typical neutrino event as ob- Figure 4 Preparation of the interior of the 
served in the Big European Bubble Cham-  13 m'bubble chamber Gargamelle, later to 
ber (BEBC) filled with neon at the CERN  be filled with Freon. It is with this detector 
450 GeV Super Proton Synchrotron (SPS)   that the neutral currents were discovered.
accelerator. The muon can be seen on the 
left. It has been tagged by an external muon 
identifier. The many-particle hadron shower 
is to the right.


(CERN-Dortmund-Heidelberg-Saclay Collaboration) detector used at 
CERN from 1977 to 1985. It consists of 19 modules made of iron plates 
3.75 m in diameter, each with total iron thickness of 75 cm and a weight of 
— 65 t. The iron is toroidally magnetized to a field of 1.7 T by means of coils 
that pass through a hole in the centre.

  Interleaved with the 5 cm thick iron plates are scintillator strips, which 
serve to measure the energy of the secondary hadrons by sampling the 
ionization. The typical hadron shower is — 25 cm in radius and — 1 m long, 
so the shower dimensions are very small compared with the size of the 
detector. The muon momenta are determined on the basis of curvature in 
the magnetic field, with the help of drift chambers inserted between the 
iron modules. These measure the positions of traversing tracks in three 
projections. The useful target weight is — 800 t. Figure 5 shows the CDHS 
experiment and Figure 6 a typical event of the same type as that shown in 
Figure 3.

                                                                                    J. Steinberger                                                                                     491















































Figure 5 View along the 19 modules of the CDHS electronic neutrino detector at the SPS. The 
black light-guides and phototubes, which are used to measure the hadron energy, can be seen 
sticking out of the magnetized iron modules. The hexagonal aluminium structures are the drift 
chambers that measure the muon trajectories




u            .     .0 11010 76.0
                                        SONTILLA TOR 
                                        PULSE
                                        HEIGHTS



  NUJ      111.1..200 ""'° °°'°         PROJECTION x

            -                                    I   .    .        ,   1
                                                                                                    Figure 6 Computer reconstruction of a typi- 
                                                                                                    cal event of the reaction v + Fe + X. 
0.1,40.,   01 mu-2000.0 rulx. 2000.0                                                                Four views are shown, with the horizontal 
                                        PROJECTION u                                                axis along the beam direction. The top view 
                 •                                                                 .                shows the s cintillator pulse height, or had- 
                                                                                                    ron energy, and its distribution along the 
                                                                                                    detector. The next view shows the scintilla- 
  -Pm .1   . u..2000 0 rlk. 1000.0      PROJECTION v                                                tar hits as well as the horizontal wire hits 
                                                                                                    and the reconstructed track in the x projec- 
                                                                                                    tion. The other two views show the wire hits 
                                                                                                    and the reconstructed track for the +60° 
                                                                                                    projections.

492	
Physics 1988
4. NEUTRAL CURRENTS
4.1 Discovery
The evolution of the electroweak unified gauge theory in the late sixties and  
early seventies was a miraculous achievement, but one that had no immedi- 
ate impact on the majority of particle physicists - certainly not on me - 
perhaps because it was a theoretical construct which left the existing experi- 
mental domain intact. However, it predicted some entirely new pheno- 
mena, and of these the neutral weak currents were the first to be discov- 
ered. The verification of neutral currents (NCs) established the theory  
overnight, and subsequent experiments on their detailed structure rein- 
forced this. This observation' of neutral weak currents at CERN in 1973 by  
the Gargamelle group was the first great discovery made at CERN. It was  
followed 10 years later by the second-also a prediction of the same  
theory - the intermediate boson.
-200
-100
100
200 (cm)
NC events
-11	
al•
0 NC events
lj—Lr	
■
Measured neutron stars 
100., E< 500 MeV
Monte Carlo calculation for 
induced background
dl
10
5 
0
5
Arbitrary units
Figure 7 A "muonless" event in Gargamelle.  
All tracks stop or interact in the chamber.  
None could be a muon. The neutrino pro- 
duces one I(' and one K° meson. The I('  
meson interacts in the liquid and then de- 
cays. The invisible 1‹.' meson decays to two  
pions.
Figure 8 Distribution of the origin of muon- 
less events along the beam direction in Gar- 
gamelle. Neutrino events are expected to be  
uniformly distributed, whereas neutron  
events should decrease with distance be- 
cause of their absorption in the Freon. The  
nuclear mean free path in Freon is about  
80 cm. The expected and observed distribu- 
tions of neutron interactions are shown in  
the bottom two histograms. The muonless  
events are consistent with neutrino and in- 
consistent with neutron origin (Ref. 1).

                                                                        J. Steinber ger                                                                           493



    The bubble chamber, built under the direction of A. Lagarrigue at the 

Ecole Polytechnique in Paris, was exposed to neutrino and antineutrino 

WBBs at the CERN 24 GeV proton accelerator. The normal CC reactions,


                                                v(P) N —> kt–(p+) hadrons, 


were found as usual, but NC "muonless" reactions,


                                                    v(P)           N -+ v(')                   hadrons,


which had hardly been looked for before-and therefore had not been 

found- were there as well. Such an event is shown in Figure 7. These events 

were selected on the basis of no muon candidate among the observed 

particles. The main experimental challenge was to show that they were not 

due to stray neutrons in the beam. I myself was a sceptic for a long time, and

I lost a bottle or two of good wine on this matter. However, the neutron 

background would be expected to decrease exponentially along the length 

of the chamber, roughly with the neutron mean free path in Freon. Instead, 

the event distribution was flat, as expected for neutrino events (see Fig. 8.).

I have never enjoyed paying up a debt more than at the dinner we gave for 

the winners, very good friends, Jacques Prentki, John Iliopoulos and Henri 

Epstein.

    The ratios of the cross-sections

                                                              UNC                                             0.-NC
                                                R,, — 'a                       and              RT, - 
                                                                 CC                                              ( C
                                                                 p                                            u- '
are given in the electroweak theory in terms of the Weinberg angle



                                       R. = 1 — —                                                                5 + (1 + r) — sin40„                                (1) 
                                                       2                                                         9

 and

                                                                                                         1) 5
                                                                     sin B,, + 1 + — —                                                  ,                            (2) 
                                                       2                                                 r 9

where r is, the ratio of antineutrino to neutrino, CC total cross-sections: 

r= acc'/cfccv= 0.48 ± 0.02 experimentally. On the basis of these ratios, 

the experiment yielded a first measure of sin' w, that was not very different 

from present, more precise determinations. In the same exposure a beauti- 

ful example of another NC process, the scattering of an antineutrino on an 

electron, was also found*.



4.2 Precision measurement of sin2 Ow and right-handed neutral currents

The higher energies that became available a few years later at Fermilab and 

CERN made the study of NC processes much easier. The muons of the CC 

background had now a greater penetration power, which permitted cleaner 

separation of NC and CC events. Also, with the advent of the higher 

energies, the advantage in the study of inclusive neutrino scattering had 

shifted to electronic detection techniques. In the period 1977 to 1985, 

hadronic NC neutrino scattering was studied extensively by the CDHS

494                                      Physics 1988



 16000                                 CDHS


 12000 



k 8000
                                                   Figure 9 Identification, by the CDHS Col- 
               NCCC                                laboration, of NC events by their short 
  4000 -         Long MONITOR                      event length. The peak at small event 
                                                   lengths is due to NC events. The long tail is 
           1X9ff((i/                               due to muonic events, which must be sub- 
     0          1   1.4   2   2.4    3        4    tracted under the peak to give the NC rate 
                        L/L1ut                     (Ref. 3).





Collaboration at CERN in order to get a more precise value for 0,3 and to 

check the prediction of the electroweak theory for the ratio of right-handed 

to left-handed NCs4. The NC events are selected on the basis of short event 

length, i.e. the short penetration of the hadronic shower compared with 

that of the muon of CC events. This is illustrated in Figure 9. A 15% 

background of CC events is subtracted. The neutrino NC-to-CC ratio R, 

yielded the most precise value of the weak mixing angle available at present, 

sin20, = 0.227 ± 0.006. Once sin20, is known, the antineutrino ratio 

Ri-, follows from Eq. (2). Its measurement provided a sensitive test of the 

electroweak theory, and confirmed it in its simplest form. The presence of 

right-handed NCs (CCs are purely left-handed) in the amount predicted by 

the theory could be demonstrated by comparing the hadron energy distri- 

butions of the NC and CC processes. The result is shown in Figure 10.


  030 
                    a =,-ifq.010
  025


  020
9,                                                  Figure 10 Strengths of the left- and right- 
  01                             3a CONTOUR         handed neutral currents. If the NC were 
                                 (STATISTICAL ONLY) purely left-handed, as is the case for the CC, 
  010                                               the experimental point would be expected 
  0 05                                             to fall on the V-A line. The experiment 
                                                    shows a right-handed component, which is 
         0 Os  010  015  0 20  0 25 0 30 035  0 40 just that expected in the electroweak theory 
                         9,                         (Weinberg-Salam model) (Ref. 4).





4.3 Neutrino-electron scattering

The elastic-scattering reactions of neutrinos on atomic electrons


           p, + e —) p, + e                 and               e —)         +  e


proceed via NCs. They are characterized by small cross - sections-smaller 

than their hadronic counterparts by the mass ratio me/mp because of the 

smaller c.m. energies - and, for the same reason, by small electron produc-

J. Steinberger	
495
tion angles, 0,. Vm,./Ev. Until now, these angles have not been resolved by  
the experiments, so only total cross-sections have been measured. The  
expectations in the electroweak theory are:
(J =
Gil. Ern,
71
16
(
1- 4 sin2 Ow + — sin4 0„
3	
i
and
Gis Ern, (1
7r	
3
416
sin]	
+	
sin- 0„) .
3	
3
These reactions can also serve to test this theory, and have the advantage  
that strongly interacting particles are not involved, so that the understand- 
ing of strong-interaction corrections is not necessary in the interpretation.  
They have the experimental disadvantage of low rates and consequent large  
background. The best results at present are from a BNL experiments using  
relatively low energy neutrinos, E 1.5 GeV, and a 140 t detector entirely  
composed of many layers of plastic scintillator and drift chambers. The  
background is subtracted on the basis of the distribution in the production  
angle of the electron shower (see Figure 11). Instead of comparing the  
neutrino and antineutrino cross-sections directly with the theory, the au- 
thors form the ratio of the two, which is less sensitive to some systematic  
errors. From this they find the result sin20, = 0.209 ± 0.032. A CERN  
group reports a similar result, with sin20, = 0.211 ± 0.037. The agreement  
with other methods of obtaining this angle is an important confirmation of  
the theory. A massive experiment to improve the precision is currently  
under way at CERN.
0.01	
002
82 (radian2)
EVENTS / 0 001 radiant
40
30
20
10
10
1011
4404
i7	
(a )
30
20
Figure 11 Identification of neutrino-elec-
tron events on the basis of their small angle
with respect to the beam in the experiment
of Ahrens et al.". The peak at small angles in  
f)7A' the two top graphs is due to neutrino-elec- 
( d ) tron scattering. The bottom graphs show
the flat distribution observed if photons
rather than electrons are detected. This  
0.02 shows the angular distribution of back- 
ground events.
C
10
0.01
92(rad
on2)
5. NEUTRINO-NUCLEON INCLUSIVE SCATTERING AND THE  
QUARK STRUCTURE OF HADRONS
5.1 Phenomenology
We consider the CC reactions,
v +N—>kt- + hadrons and	
+ hadrons,

independently of the final hadron configuration. This is called the inclusive 
process. It is assumed that the lepton vertex is described by the vector-

496                                 Physics 1988


axial vector current of the electroweak theory. Let k be the initial and k' the 
final lepton energy-momentum four vectors, p that of the incident nucleon, 
and p' that of the final hadron state:








                                                          final 
                                                          hadron 
                                                          state

Define the kinematic variables:

      Q2      (k-k')2=4EE' sin20/2,
      v = p .Q2/ mp= E„ - mp, Eh
                (the energy of the final-state hadrons in the laboratory sys- 
                tem),
      x = Q2/ 2 mpv, 0<x< 1,
               v/E     Eh/E, 0<y< 1,

where E and E' are the energies of the initial neutrino and final muon, 
respectively, and 0 is the angle between these, all in the laboratory system. 
The cross-sections can be written in terms of three structure functions, each 
a function of the variables x and Q2 that characterize the hadronic vertex:

 d203,(P)    G2 rn„E,,
                      {I-72(x,Q2) ti + (1      Y)2] — Y 2.I'L(x,Q2) (±) x-F3(x,Q2)
 dxdy
                        [1 - (1 - y)2]}


The functions F2(x,Q2), xF3(x,Q2), and FL(x,Q2) are the three structure 
functions that express what happens at the hadron vertex. The sum of 
neutrino and antineutrino cross-sections has the same structure-function 
dependence as does the cross-section for charged leptons:


    d2cr        27ra2 m,,E     r±
    dxdy            Q4       EF2 (x, Q2) [1 + (1 — y)2]       Y2FL(X,Q2) } •


5.2 Quark structure of the nucleon
In 1969, at the newly completed S-mile linear electron accelerator at SLAC, 
it was discovered' that in electron-proton collisions, at high momentum 
transfer, the form factors were independent of Q2. This so-called "scaling" 
behaviour is characteristic of "point", or structureless, particles. The inter- 
pretation in terms of a composite structure of the protons - that is, protons 
composed of point-like quarks - was given by Bjorken'and Feynman9.
   Neutrinos are projectiles par excellence for investigating this structure, in 
part because of the heavy mass of the intermediate boson, and in part 
because quarks and antiquarks are scattered differently by neutrinos owing 
to the V-A character of the weak currents; they can therefore be distin-

                                      J. Steinberger                                 497


guished in neutrino scattering, whereas in charged-lepton scattering this is 
not possible. The quark model makes definite predictions for neutrino- 
hadron scattering, which are beautifully confirmed experimentally. Many of 
the predictions rest on the fact that now the kinematical variable x takes on 
a physical meaning: it can be interpreted as the fraction of the nucleon 
momentum or mass carried by the quark on which the scattering takes 
place. The neutrino experiments we review here have primarily used iron as 
the target material. Iron has roughly equal numbers of protons and neu- 
trons. For such nuclei, the cross-sections can be expressed in terms of the 
total quark and total antiquark distributions in the proton. Let u(x), d(x), 
s(x), c(x), etc., be the up, down, strange, charm, etc., quark distributions in 
the proton. The proton contains three "valence" quarks: two up-quarks and 
one down-quark. In addition, it contains a "sea" of virtual quark-antiquark 
pairs. The up valence-quark distribution is u(x) --d(x), and the down va- 
lence-quark distribution is d(x) - d(x). The sea quarks and antiquarks have 
necessarily identical distributions, so that s(x) = §(x), c(x) = Z(x), etc. For the 
neutron, u and d change roles, but s and c are the same. Let

          q(x) = u(x) + d(x) + s(x) + c(x) +
and
          j(x) = u(x) + d (x) + s (x) + 5.(x) +

be the total quark and antiquark distributions of the proton, respectively. 
For spin-1/2 quarks interacting according to the Standard Model, for a 
target with equal numbers of protons and neutrons, and for

02 4 mw and m, 4 E:

                  d2&             Ern,,x[q(x) + (1 — y)2 Zi(x)J
                  dxdy            7r
and               d201,       GEEni„   x[q(x) + (1 — y)2       q(x)1
                  dxdy            7r



Comparison with the expression for the cross-section in terms of structure 
functions then gives these functions in terms of quark distributions: 

F2(x,Q2) = x[q(x) 4(x)1: q(x) 4(x) is the total quark + antiquark distribu-
tion;

xF3(x,Q2) = x[q(x) — 4(x)]: q(x) — 4(x) is the 'valence'-quark distribution; 

FL(x,Q2) = 0: this is a consequence of the spin-1/2 nature of the quarks. 

From these simple expressions for the cross-sections, in terms of quark
structure, several tests of the quark model are derived. For the experimen- 
tal comparisons, we take the CDHS experiments'. It should be noted that 
the measurements in the detector, i.e. the hadron energy and the muon 
momentum, are just sufficient to define the inclusive process.

498
Physics 1988
0	
20	
40	
60	
80 100 120 140 160 180 200 220 240 260 280 300
Ev (GeV)
Figure 12 Total neutrino and antineutrino cross-sections per nucleon divided by neutrino  
energy. The flat 'scaling' behaviour is a consequence of the point-like interaction of the  
constituents (Ref. 10).
0.3
0.2
CDHS
	
 ! Scale_
	
 error
Neutrino
- -

Antineutrino
Scale error
13IiI1111	
1 
1
(cm2/GeV*1038►
0 8  
07  
0.6  
05  
0.4  
03  
02  
0 1
y
05
04
0.1
Figure 13 The average of y (the fraction of  
the neutrino energy transmitted to the final  
hadron state) as a function of the neutrino  
energy, for neutrinos and antineutrinos.  
The uniformity is a consequence of scaling,  
which in turn is a consequence of the point- 
like interaction of the quark (Ref 10).
50	
100	
10	
200
Ev (GeV}
1) Scaling. The independence of the differential cross-sections with respect  
to Q2 is evident everywhere, over a large domain in Q2. As one example,  
Figure 12 shows the linearity of the total cross-sections with neutrino  
energy; as another, Figure 13 shows the uniformity of the average of y with  
respect to neutrino energy; both examples are consequences of scaling.  
Small deviations from scaling are observed in the structure functions, as we  
will see later, but these have their explanation in the strong interactions of  
the quarks.

                                          J. Steinberger                                   499



2) The y-dependence of the cross-sections. We expect

               de de
                             cc [1 + (1 — y)2] x[q(x) + q(x)] dx
               dy        dy


and


                               cc [1 — (1 — y)2] x[q(x) — q(x)] dx .
                dy       dy

The agreement with this expectation is quite good, as can be seen from 

Figure. 14. A corollary of this agreement is that FL(x) is small. It is found 

that JFL(x)dx/1F2(x)dx 0.1. Again, this deviation from the simple quark 

picture is understood in terms of the strong interactions of the quarks, as 
we will see later.



  x10-41                                                            • V
    0.3                                                             A V - V      CONS



                                                (clav/dy)• (do"/dy) 11*(1-021 (coTi)




"E 0.2





                 (day/dy)- (dcr`7/dy) —11-(1-y)21 lq-E0

     0.1








                         L 
                        0.2               0.4              0.6              0.0              1.0


Figure 14 The y-dependence of the sum and the difference of neutrino and antineutrino cross- 
sections. Spin-'/2 quarks are expected to have y-dependences 1 + (1-y)2for the sum and 
1- (1-y)2 for the difference (Ref. 10).




3) Correspondence between PV (y)andF“x). Both are proportional to q(x) 
 +  q(x), and so are expected to have the same x-dependence in the simple

quark model. They are related by the factor


                      F2 F2 (x)     1 [2 +                           5

                      F)(x)         2 L 3)                )2]        18

Here 2/3 and —1/3 are the up- and down-quark electric charges, respec- 

tively. The agreement in shape and magnitude, shown in Figure 15, not only 

supports the quark picture, but also demonstrates the third integral quark 

electric charges.

500                             Physics 1988

4) j xF3(x)dx/x = 3. Since xF3(x) = x[q(x) — 4(x)]in the quark model and
  x) - 11(X) is the valence-quark distribution, this sum rule states that there 
are three valence quarks in the nucleon. The experimental demonstration is 
not without problems, because the v and V cross-sections are finite as x —› 0, 
and the difference, which is xF3(x), has a consequent large error at small x, 
which is divided by x as x 0. However, all experiments give a value near 3,
with typical uncertainties of  10%.
  Together with the charged-lepton inclusive scattering experiments, the 
neutrino experiments leave no doubt about the validity of the quark picture 
of nucleon structure. In addition, the neutrino experiments are unique in 
offering the possibility of measuring independently the quark and antiquark 
distributions in the nucleon, shown in Figure 15.
  If the quarks were the sole nucleon constituents, we would expect J F2 dx 
= x[q(x) + q(x)] dx to be equal to 1. Experimentally, !F2(x) dx = 0.48 ± 
0.02. We should have expected that some of the nucleon momentum is 
carried by the gluons, the mesons that bind the quarks. The experimental 
result is therefore interpreted to mean that gluons account for about half of 
the nucleon momentum (or mass).




1.5







1.0







0.5








          0.1             0.3            0.5             0.7
                                   x

Figure 15 The structure functions xF3(x), F2(x), and q(x). In the simple quark picture F2(x) = 
x[q(x) 4(x)] and xF3(x) = x[q(x) — ti(x)j.

                       J. Steinberger              501



5.3 Neutrino scattering and quantum chromodynamics (QCD)
QCD is the elegant new gauge theory of the interaction of quarks and 

gluons, which describes the binding of quarks into the hadrons. Deep- 

inelastic lepton scattering provided a means of testing the predictions of 

this important theory and gave it its first experimental support. So far, no 

one has succeeded in calculating low-energy hadronic phenomena such as 

the wave functions of quarks in hadrons, because of the large coupling 

constant that frustrates perturbation methods at low energy. At high Q2, 

however, the effective coupling constant becomes logarithmically smaller, 

and perturbation calculations become credible. The theory predicts 'scaling 

violations' in the form of a 'shrinking' of the structure functions towards 

smaller x as Q2 getslarger. This is observed experimentally, as can be seen 

from Figure 16. In the theory, the 'shrinking' is the consequence of the


F2(x)







                  GGM
                   2-5 GeV





  0.5



                    SLAC
                     ed
       Colis        10 GeV
       30-200 GeV



   0.1




  0.5
                            Figure 16 Scaling is only approximately true 
                            for the structure functions. Early measure- 
                            ments of F2(x) in three different energy do- 
                            mains exhibit shrinking, as expected in the 
        025  0.50 0.75 1.00 QCD theory.





emission of gluons in the scattering process. This emission can be calcu- 

lated. The Q2 evolution at sufficiently high Q2 is therefore quantitatively 

predicted by the theory. In neutrino experiments, this Q2 evolutioncould 

be measured, and these measurements confirmed the theory and contri- 

buted to its acceptance. In the case of xF„ the theoretical predictions have 

only one free parameter, the coupling constant as. In the case of F2, the Q2 

evolution is coupled to the gluon distribution G(x,Q2). The experimental Q2 

evolutions of xF,and F2 inthe latest CDHS experiment are shown, together 

with their QCD fits, in Figure 17 and 18. The theory fits the data adequate-

