           JULIAN SCHWINGER

      Relativistic quantum field theory
          Nobel Lecture, December 11, 1965


The relativistic quantum theory of fields was born some thirty-five years ago 
through the paternal efforts of Dirac, Heisenberg, Pauli and others. It was a 
somewhat retarded youngster, however, and first reached adolescence seven- 
teen years later, an event which we are gathered here to celebrate. But it is the 
subsequent development and more mature phase of the subject that I wish to 
discuss briefly today.
 I shall begin by describing to you the logical foundations of relativistic 
quantum field theory. No dry recital of lifeless « axioms » is intended but, 
rather, an outline of its organic growth and development as the synthesis of 
quantum mechanics with relativity. Indeed, relativistic quantum mechan- 
ics - the union of the complementarity principle of Bohr with the relativity 
principle of Einstein - is quantum field theory. I beg your indulgence for the 
mode of expression I must often use. Mathematics is the natural language of 
theoretical physics. It is the irreplaceable instrument for the penetration of 
realms of physical phenomena far beyond the ordinary experience upon which 
conventional language is based.
 Improvements in the formal presentation of quantum mechanical prin- 
ciples, utilizing the concept of action, have been interesting by-products of 
work in quantum field theory. Both my efforts in this direction' and those of 
Feynman2 (which began earlier) were based on a study of Dirac concerning 
the correspondence between the quantum transformation function and the 
classical action. We followed quite different paths, however, and two distinct 
formulations of quantum mechanics emerged which can be distinguished as 
differential and integral viewpoints.
 In order to suggest the conceptual advantages of these formulations, I shall 
indicate how the differential version transcends the correspondence principle 
and incorporates, on the same footing, two different kinds of quantum dyna- 
mical variable. It is just these two types that are demanded empirically by the 
two known varieties of particle statistics. The familiar properties of the vari- 
ables qk, Pk, k= 1-- n, of the conventional quantum system enable one to derive 
the form of the quantum action principle. It is a differential statement about


                Ito

              RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY                               141

time transformation functions,


                        o<tilt2) = (iifi)<tIlo[j:Idtnit,>                     (I)


which is valid for a certain class of kinematical and dynamical variations. The 

quantum Lagrangian operator of this system can be given the very symmet- 

rical form

                  1 i dqk         dpk dqk           dpk 
      L =     ,i 41 Vk dt — qk7-1t. ± - 7 —I t Pk—  at  qk )— H(q,p, t)       (2)


The symmetry is emphasized by collecting all the variables into the 2n-com- 

ponent Hermitian vector z(t) and writing


                      L 1 za dz _ dt dz a_z _ H(z, 0 
                           4      dt         )                                (3)


where a is a real antisymmetrical matrix, which only connects the comple- 

mentary pairs of variables.

  The transformation function depends explicitly upon the choice of terminal 

states and implicitly upon the dynamical nature of the system. If the latter is 

held fixed, any alteration of the transformation function must refer to changes 

in the states, as given by


                60,1= (ilh)<tl!Gi         611-2) = —MO G,!t„)                 (4)

where G1 and G, are infinitesimal Hermitian operators constructed from dy- 

namical variables of the system at the specified times. For a given dynamical 

system, then,

                              S [I% dt.L] = GI— G ,                           (5 )

which is the quantum principle of stationary action, or Hamilton's principle, 

since there is no reference on the right hand side to variations at intermediate 

times. The stationary action principle implies equations of motion for the 

dynamical variables and supplies explicit expressions for the infinitesimal 

operators G1,2. The interpretation of these operators as generators of transfor- 

mations on states, and on the dynamical variables, implies commutation rela- 

tions. In this way, all quantum-dynamical aspects of the system are derived 

from a single dynamical principle. The specific form of the commutation re- 

lations obtained from the symmetrical treatment of the usual quantum system 

is given by the matrix statement


                               [z(t), z(t)] = iha-1                           (6)

142           1965 JULIAN SCHWINGER
Note particularly how the antisymmetry of the commutator matches the 
antisymmetry of the matrix a.
 We may now ask whether this general form of Lagrangian operator,

             4 \ dt — dt—x)
also describes other kinds of quantum systems, if the properties of the matrix 
A and of the Hermitian variables x are not initially assigned. There is one 
general restriction on the matrix A, however. It must be skew-Hermitian, as 
in the realization by the real, antisymmetrical matrix a. Only one other simple 
possibility then appears, that of an imaginary, symmetrical matrix. We write 
that kind of matrix as ioc, where a is real and symmetrical, and designate the 
corresponding variables collectively by (t). The replacement of the anti- 
symmetrical a by the symmetrical a requires that the antisymmetrical com- 
mutators which characterize z (t) be replaced by symmetrical anticommuta- 
tors for g (t), and indeed
               g(t), C(t)} = A cc- 1 (8)
specifies the quantum nature of this second class of quantum variable. It has 
no classical analogue. The consistency of various aspects of the formalism 
requires only that the Lagrangian operator be an even function of this second 
type of quantum variable.
 Time appears in quantum mechanics as a continuous parameter which rep- 
resents an abstraction of the dynamical role of the measurement apparatus. 
The requirement of relativistic invariance invites the extension of this abstrac- 
tion to include space and time coordinates. The implication that space-time 
localized measurements are a useful, if practically unrealizable idealization 
may be incorrect, but it is a grave error to dismiss the concept on the basis of 
a priori notions of measurability. Microscopic measurement has no meaning 
apart from a theory, and the idealized measurement concepts that are implicit 
in a particular theory must be accepted or rejected in accordance with the 
final success or failure of that theory to fulfill its avowed aims. Quantum field 
theory has failed no significant test, nor can any decisive confrontation be 
anticipated in the near future.
 Classical mechanics is a determinate theory. Knowledge of the state at a 
given time permits precise prediction of the result of measuring any property 
of the system. In contrast, quantum mechanics is only statistically determinate. 
It is the probability of attaining a particular result on measuring any property

        RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY  143
of the system, not the outcome of an individual microscopic observation, that 
is predictable from knowledge of the state. But both theories are causal - a 
knowledge of the state at one time implies knowledge of the state at a later 
time. A quantum state is specified by particular values of an optimum set of 
compatible physical properties, which are in number related to the number 
of degrees of freedom of the system. In a relativistic theory, the concepts of 
« before » and « after » have no intrinsic meaning for regions that are in space- 
like relation. This implies that measurements individually associated with 
different regions in space-like relation are causally independent, or compati- 
ble. Such measurements can be combined in the complete specification of a 
state. But since there is no limit to the number of disjoint spatial regions that 
can be considered, a relativistic quantum system has an infinite number of 
degrees of freedom.
  The latter statement, incidentally, contains an implicit appeal to a general 
property that the mathematics of physical theories must possess - the mathe- 
matical description of nature is not sensitive to modifications in physically 
irrelevant details. An infinite total spatial volume is an idealization of the 
finite volume defined by the macroscopic measurement apparatus. Arbitrarily 
small volume elements are idealizations of cells with linear dimensions far 
below the level of some least distance that is physically significant. Thus, it 
would be more accurate, conceptually, to assert that a relativistic quantum 
system has a number of degrees of freedom that is extravagantly large, but 
finite.
  The distinctive features of relativistic quantum mechanics flow from the 
idea that each small element of three-dimensional space at a given time is 
physically independent of all other such volume elements. Let us label the 
various degrees of freedom explicitly - by a point of three-dimensional space 
(in a limiting sense), and by other quantities of finite multiplicity. The dynam- 
ical variables then appear as
                za,x (t) a. xa (t = xo, x) (9)
which are a finite number of Hermitian operator functions of space-time co- 
ordinates, or quantum fields. The dynamical independence of the individual 
volume elements is expressed by a corresponding additivity of the Lagrangian 
operator
                   L:= I (dx) .29          (ro)
where the Lagrange function 21 describes the dynamical situation in the in-

 144               1 9 6 5 JULIAN SCHWINGER

 finitesimal neighborhood of a point. The characteristic time derivative or 
 kinematical part of L appears analogously in 2 in terms of the variables asso- 
 ciated with the specified spatial point. The relativistic structure of the action 
 principle is completed by demanding that it present the same form, inde- 
 pendently of the particular partitioning of space-time into space and time. 
 This is facilitated by the appearance of the action operator, the time integral 
 of the Lagrangian, as the space-time integral of the Lagrange function. Ac- 
 cordingly, we require, as a sufficient condition, that the latter be a scalar func- 
 tion of its field variables, which implies that the known form of the time 
 derivative term is supplemented by similar space derivative contributions. 
 This is conveyed by


               -99= 1 (XAYafa — ayZAYX) — Yf (x)         (11)
                   4

 where the AP are a set of four finite skew-Hermitian matrices. A specific 
 physical field is associated with submatrices of the Au, which are real and anti - 
 symmetrical for a field that obeys Bose-Einstein statistics, or imaginary and 
 symmetrical for a field v obeying Fermi-Dirac statistics. Finally, the bound- 
 aries of the four-dimensional integration region, formed by three-dimen- 
 sional space at the terminal times, are described by the invariant concept of 
 the space-like surface G, a three-dimensional manifold such that every pair of 
 points is in space-like relation. The ensuing invariant form of the action prin- 
 ciple of relativistic quantum field theory is (we now use atomic units, in which 
 A=c= 1)

                 (5<a lia z> = 10 1[Scerri, (dx) or 162> (12)

 Relativity is a statement of equivalence within a class of descriptions associated 
 with similar but different measurement apparatus. Space-time coordinates 
 are an abstraction of the role that the measurement apparatus plays in defining 
 a space-time frame of reference. The empirical fact, that all connected space- 
 time locations and orientations of the measurement apparatus supply equiva- 
 lent descriptions, is interpreted by the mathematical requirement ofinvariance 
 under the group of proper orthochronous inhomogenous Lorentz transfor- 
 mations, applied to the continuous numerical coordinates. There is another 
 numerical element in the quantum- mechanical description that has a measure 
 of arbitrariness and expresses an aspect of relativity. I am referring to the 
 quantum-mechanical use of complex numbers and of the mathematical 
equivalence of the two square roots of - 1, ± i. What general property of

                 RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY                                              145
any measurement apparatus is subject to our control, in principle, but offers 
only the choice of two alternatives? The answer is clear - a macroscopic ma- 
terial system can be constructed of matter, or of antimatter! But let us not 
conclude too hastily that a matter apparatus and an antimatter apparatus are 
completely equivalent. It is characteristic of quantum mechanics that the 
dividing line between apparatus and system under investigation can be drawn 
somewhat arbitrarily, as long as the measurement apparatus always possesses 
the classical aspects required for the unambiguous recording of an observation. 
To preserve this feature, the interchange of matter and antimatter must be 
made on the whole assemblage of macroscopic apparatus and microscopic 
system. Since the observational label of this duality is the algebraic sign of 
electric charge, the microscopic interchange must reverse the vector of 
electric current PI, while maintaining the tensor Tuv that gives the flux of 
energy and momentum. But this is just the effect of the coordinate transfor- 
mation that reflects all four coordinates.
   It is indeed true that the action principle does not retain its general form 
under either of the two transformations, the replacement of i with - i, and 
the reflection of all coordinates, but does preserve it under their combined in- 
fluence. In more detail, the effect of complex conjugation is equivalent to the 
reversal of operator multiplication, which distinguishes fields with the two 
types of statistics. The reflection of all coordinates, a proper transformation, 
can be generated by rotations in the attached Euclidean space obtained by 
introducing the imaginary time coordinate x4= i x°. This transformation 
alters reality properties, distinguishing fields with integral and half-integral 
spin. The combination of the two transformations replaces the original Lag- 
range function
                                --99 ((Pint, CPI/tint, Vint, V i/tint)                          (13)
with
                               --fl(Pint, ifi/zint, iVint, V i/zint)                            (14)
If only fields of the types c       o int, Wit intare considered, which is the empirical
connection between spin and statistics, the action principle is unaltered in 
form. This invariance property of the action principles expresses the relativity 
of matter and antimatter. That is the content of the so-called TCP theorem. 
The anomalous response of the field types co+ int' mint is also the basis for the 
theoretical rejection of these possibilities as contrary to general physical re- 
quirements of positiveness, namely, the positiveness of probability, and the 
positiveness of energy.

146                  1965 JULIAN SCHWINGER
  The concept of space-like surface is not limited to plane surfaces. Accord- 
ing to the action principle, an infinitesimal deformation of the space-like 
surface on which a state is specified changes that state by
                        a<cri = i<o* I fday Plvbxv                 (15)
which is the infinitely multiple relativistic generalization of the Schrodinger 
equation
                           6( tl = i<t1H(-- 6t)                    (16)
This set of differential equations must obey integrability conditions, which 
are commutator statements about the elements of the tensor T. Since rigid 
displacements and rotations can be produced from arbitrary local deforma- 
tions, the operator expressions of the group properties of Lorentz transforma- 
tions must be a consequence of these commutator conditions. Foremost 
among the latter are the equal-time commutators of the energy density T°°, 
which suffice to convey all aspects of relativistic invariance that are not of a 
three-dimensional nature. A system that is invariant under three-dimensional 
translations and rotations will be Lorentz invariant if, at equal times',
         - i[Too (x), Too (x')] = — (Tok(x) + Tok(x')) a k 6(x— x')(17)
This is a sufficient condition. Additional terms with higher derivatives of the 
delta function will occur, in general. But there is a distinguished class of physi- 
cal system, which I shall call local, for which no further term appears. The 
phrase « local system » can be given a physical definition within the framework 
we have used or, alternatively, by viewing the commutator condition as a 
measurability statement about the property involved in the response of a sys- 
tem to a weak external gravitational field. Only the external gravitational 
potential g00 is relevant here. A physical system is local if the operators Ti'v, , 
which may be explicit functions ofgoo at the same time, do not depend upon 
time derivatives ofg00. The class of local systems is limited' to fields of spin 0, 
i,1. Such fields are distinguished by their physical simplicity in comparison 
with fields of higher spin. One may even question whether consistent relativ- 
istic quantum field theories can be constructed for non-local systems.
  The energy density commutator condition is a very useful test of relativistic 
invariance. Only a month or so ago I employed it to examine whether a rela- 
tivistic quantum field theory could be devised to describe magnetic as well as 
electric charge. Dirac pointed out many years ago that the existence of mag- 
netic charge would imply a quantization of electric charge, in the sense that

       RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY 147
the product of two elementary charges, eg/ hc, could assume only certain 
values. According to Dirac, these values are any integer or half-integer. In 
recent years, the theoretical possibility of magnetic charge has been attacked 
from several directions. The most serious accusation is that the concept is in 
violation of Lorentz invariance. This is sometimes expressed in the language 
of field theory by the remark that no manifestly scalar Lagrange function can 
be constructed for a system composed of electromagnetic field and electric and 
magnetic charge-bearing fields. Now it is true that there is no relativistically 
invariant theory for arbitary e and g, so that no formally invariant version 
could exist. Indeed, the unnecessary assumption that .29 is a scalar must be 
relinquished in favor of the more general possibilities that are compatible with 
the action principle. But the energy commutator condition can still be applied. 
I have been able to show that energy and momentum density operators can be 
exhibited which satisfy the commutator condition, together with the three- 
dimensional requirements, provided eglhc possesses one of a discrete set of 
values. These values are integers, which is more restrictive than Dirac's quan- 
tization condition. Such general considerations shed no light on the empirical 
elusiveness of magnetic charge. They only emphasize that this novel theoreti- 
cal possibility should not be dismissed lightly.
 The physical systems that obey the commutator statement of locality do not 
include the gravitational field. But, this field, like the electromagnetic field, 
requires very special consideration. And these considerations make full use 
of the relativistic field concept. The dynamics of the electromagnetic field is 
characterized by invariance under gauge transformations, in which the phase 
of every charge-bearing field is altered arbitrarily, but continuously, at each 
space-time point while electromagnetic potentials are transformed inhomo- 
geneously. The introduction of the gravitational field involves, not only the 
use of general coordinates and coordinate transformations, but the establish- 
ment at each point of an independent Lorentz frame. The gravitational field 
gauge transformations are produced by the arbitrary reorientation of these 
local coordinate systems at each point while gravitational potentials are trans- 
formed linearly and inhomogeneously. The formal extension of the action 
principle to include the gravitational field can be carried out', together with 
the verification of consistency conditions analogous to the energy density 
commutator conditions. To appreciate this tour de force, one must realize 
that the operator in the role of energy density is a function of the gravitational 
field, which is influenced by the energy density. Thus the object to be tested 
is only known implicitly. It also appears that the detailed specification of the

148       1965 JULIAN SCHWINGER
spatial distribution of energy lacks physical significance when gravitational 
phenomena are important. Only integral quantities or equivalent asymptotic 
field properties are physically meaningful in that circumstance. It is in the 
further study of such boundary conditions that one may hope to comprehend 
the significance of the gravitational field as the physical mediator between the  
worlds of the microscopic and the macroscopic, the atom and the galaxy.
 I have now spoken at some length about fields. But it is in the language of 
particles that observational material is presented. How are these concepts 
related? Let us turn for a moment to the early history of our subject. The 
quantized field appears initially as a device for describing arbitrary numbers of 
indistinguishable particles. It was defined as the creator or annihilator of a 
particle at the specified point of space and time. This picture changed some- 
what as a consequence of the developments in quantum electrodynamics to 
which Feynman, Tomonaga, myself, and many others contributed. It began 
to be appreciated that the observed properties of so-called elementary particles  
are partly determined by the effect of interactions. The fields used in the 
dynamical description were then associated with noninteracting or bare par- 
ticles, but there was still a direct correspondence with physical particles. The  
weakness of electromagnetic interactions, as measured by the small value of 
the fine structure constant e2lhc is relevant here, for the same view-point 
failed disastrously when extended to strongly interacting nucleons and me- 
sons. The resulting wide spread disillusionment with quantum field theory is 
an unhappy chapter in the history of high-energy theoretical physics, al- 
though it did serve to direct attention toward various useful phenomenologi- 
cal calculation techniques.
 The great qualitative difference between weakly interacting and strongly 
interacting systems was impressed upon me by a particular consideration 
which I shall now sketch for you'. In the absence of interactions there is an 
immediate connection between the quantized Maxwell field and a physical 
particle of zero mass, the photon. The null mass of the photon is the particle 
transcription of a field property, that electromagnetism has no well-defined 
range but weakens geometrically. Now one of the most important inter- 
action aspects of quantum electrodynamics is the phenomenon of vacuum 
polarization. A variable electromagnetic field induces secondary currents, 
even in the absence of actual particle creation. In particular, a localized 
charge creates a counter charge in its vicinity, which partially neutralizes the  
effect of the given charge at large distances. The implication that physical 
charges are weaker than bare charges by a universal factor is the basis for

       RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY 149
charge renormalization. But once the idea of a partial neutralization of charge 
is admitted one cannot exclude the possibility of total charge neutralization. 
This will occur if the interaction exceeds a certain strength such that an op- 
positely charged particle combination, of the same nature as the photon, be- 
comes so tightly bound that the corresponding mass diminishes to zero. Under 
these circumstances no long-range fields would remain and the massless 
particle does not exist. We learn that the connection between the Maxwell 
field and the photon is not an a priori one, but involves a specific dynamical 
aspect, that electromagnetic interactions are weaker than the critical strength. 
It is a natural speculation that another such field exists which couples more 
strongly than the critical amount to nucleonic charge, the property carried 
by all heavy fermions. That hypothesis would explain the absolute stability 
of the proton, in analogy with the electromagnetic explanation of electron 
stability, without challenging the uniqueness of the photon.
 A field operator is a localized excitation which, applied to the vacuum state, 
generates all possible energy-momentum, or equivalently, mass states that 
share the other distinguishing properties of the field. The products of field 
operators widen and ultimately exhaust the various classes of mass states. If 
an isolated mass value occurs in a particular product, the state is that of a 
stable particle with corresponding characteristics. Should a small neighbor- 
hood of a particular mass be emphasized, the situation is that of an unstable 
particle, with a proper lifetime which varies inversely as the mass width of 
the excitation. The quantitative properties of the stable and unstable particles 
that may be implied by a given dynamical field theory cannot be predicted 
with presently available calculation techniques. In these matters, to borrow a 
phrase of Ingmar Bergman, and St. Paul, we see through a glass, darkly. Yet, 
in the plausible qualitative inference that a substantial number of particles, 
stable and unstable, will exist for sufficiently strong interactions among a few 
fields lies the great promise of relativistic quantum field theory.
 Experiment reveals an ever growing number and variety of unstable par- 
ticles, which seem to differ in no essential way from the stable and long-lived 
particles with which they are grouped in tentative classification schemes. 
Surely one must hope that this bewildering complexity is the dynamical 
manifestation of a conceptually simpler substratum, which need not be directly 
meaningful on the observational level of particles. The relativistic field con- 
cept is a specific realization of this general groping toward a new conception 
of matter.
 There is empirical evidence in favor of such simplification at a deeper dy-

150       1965 JULIAN SCHWINGER
namical level. Strongly interacting particles have been rather successfully 
classified with the aid of a particular internal symmetry group. It is the unitary 
group SU,. The dimensionalities of particle multiplets that have been iden- 
tified thus far are 1,8, and 10. But the fundamental multiplet of dimensionality 
3 is missing. It is difficult to believe in the physical significance of some trans-  
formation group without admitting the existence of objects that respond to 
the transformations of that group. Accordingly, I would describe the observed 
situation as follows. There are sets of fundamental fields that form triplets" 
with respect to the group U3. The excitations produced by these fields are 
very massive and highly unstable. The low lying mass excitations of mesons 
and baryons are generated by products of the fundamental fields. If these 
fields are assigned spin i, as a specific model, it is sufficient to consider certain 
products of two and three fields to represent the general properties of mesons 
and baryons, respectively.
 The cogency of this picture is emphasized by its role in clarifying a recent 
development in symmetry classification schemes. That is the provocative but 
somewhat mysterious suggestion that the internal symmetry group SU3be 
combined with space-time spin transformations to form the larger unitary 
group SU,. This idea, with its relativistic generalizations, has had some strik- 
ing numerical successes but there are severe conceptual problems in recon- 
ciling Lorentz invariance with any union of internal and space-time trans- 
formations, as long as one insists on immediate particle interpretation. The 
situation is different if one can refer to the space-time localizability that is the  
hallmark of the field concept' .. Let us assume that the interactions among the 
fundamental fields are of such strength that field products at practically co- 
incident points suffice to describe the excitation of the known relatively low 
lying particles. The resulting quasi-local structures are in some sense fields 
that are associated with the physical particles. I call these phenomenological 
fields, as distinguished from the fundamental fields which are the basic dy- 
namical variables of the system. Linear transformations on the fundamental 
fields can simulate the effect of external probes, which may involve both uni- 
tary and spin degrees of freedom. If these external perturbations are sufficient- 
ly gentle, the structure of the particles will be maintained and the phenome- 
nological field transformed linearly with indefinite multiplets. It is not im- 
plausible that the highly localized interactions among the phenomenological 
fields will exhibit a corresponding symmetry. Thus, combined spin and unitary 
transformations appear as a device for characterizing some gross features of 
the unknown inner field dynamics of physical particles, as it operates in the

                 RELATIVISTIC QUANTUM FIELD THEORY                                             151
neighborhood of a specific point. But these transformations can have no gen- 
eral significance for the transfer of excitations from point to point, and only 
lesser symmetries will survive in the final particle description.
   Phenomenological fields are the basic concept in formulating the practical 
calculation methods of strong interaction field theory. They serve to isolate 
the formidable problem of the dynamical origin of physical particles from the 
more immediate questions referring to their properties and interactions. In 
somewhat analogous circumstances, those of non-relativistic many-particle 
physics, the methods and viewpoint of quantum field theory' have been 
enormously successful. They have clarified the whole range of cooperative 
phenomena, while employing relatively simple approximation schemes. I 
believe that phenomenological relativistic quantum field theory has a similar 
future, and will replace the algorithms that were introduced during the period 
of revolt from field theory. But the intuition that serves so well in non-relativ- 
istic contexts does not exist for these new conditions. One has still to ap- 
preciate the precise rules of phenomenological relativistic field theory, which 
must supply a self-consistent description of the residual interactions, given that 
the strong fundamental interactions have operated to compose the various 
physical particles. And when this is done, how much shall we have learned, 
and how much will remain unknown, about the mechanism that builds matter 
from more primitive constituents? Are we not at this moment,
                          . . . like stout Cortez when with eagle eyes
                          He star'd at the Pacific - and all his men 
                          Look'd at each other with a wild surmise - 
                          Silent, upon a peak in Darien.
 And now it only remains for me to say: Tack sa mycket for uppmarksam- 
 heten.




   1Some references are: J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 82 (1951) 914, 91 (1953) 713; Proc. 
      Natl. Acad Sci.( U.S.), 46 (1960) 883.
   2. R. Feynman, Rev. Mod. Phys., 20 (1948) 36; R. Feynman and A. Hibbs, Quantum 
      Mechanics and Path Integrals, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1965.
   3. In the first two papers cited in Ref. 1 I have assumed space-reflection invariance and 
      shown the equivalence between the spin-statistics relation and the invariance of the 
      action principle under combined time reflection and complex conjugation. It was 
      later remarked by Pauli that the separate hypothesis of space-reflection invariance

152        1965 JULIAN SCHWINGER
  was unnecessary, W. Pauli, Niels Bohr and the Development of Physics, McGraw-Hill 
  New York, 1955.
 4. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 127 (1962) 324.
 5. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 130 (1963) 406.
 6. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 130 (1963) 800.
 7. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 130 (1963) 1253.
 8. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 132 (1963) 1317.
 9. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 125 (1962) 397; 128 (1962) 2425.
10. J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 135 (1964) B 816; 136 (1964) B 1821.
11. J. Schwinger, Second Carol Gables Conference on Symmetry Principles at High Energy, 
  Freeman, San Francisco, 1965; Phys. Rev., 140 (1965) B 158.
12. The general theory is described by P. Martin and J. Schwinger, Phys. Rev., 115 (1959) 
  1342.

