264

FRACTIONAL QUANTIZATION

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1998 
by
ROBERT B. LAUGHLIN
Department of Physics, Stanford University, California 94305-4060, USA



One of my favorite times in the academic year occurs in early spring when I 
give my class of extremely bright graduate students, who have mastered 
quantum mechanics but are otherwise unsuspecting and innocent, a take- 
home exam in which they are asked to deduce superfluidity from first prin- 
ciples. There is no doubt a special place in hell being reserved for me at this  
very moment for this mean trick, for the task is impossible. Superfluidity, like 
the fractional quantum Hall effect, is an emergent phenomenon — a low-ener- 
gy collective effect of huge numbers of particles that cannot be deduced from 
the microscopic equations of motion in a rigorous way and that disappears 
completely when the system is taken apartA). There are prototypes for super- 
fluids, of course, and students who memorize them have taken the first step 
down the long road to understanding the phenomenon, but these are all ap- 
proximate and in the end not deductive at all, but fits to experiment. The 
students feel betrayed and hurt by this experience because they have been 
trained to think in reductionist terms and thus to believe that everything not 
amenable to such thinking is unimportant. But nature is much more heart- 
less than I am, and those students who stay in physics long enough to se- 
riously confront the experimental record eventually come to understand that 
the reductionist idea is wrong a great deal of the time, and perhaps always. 
One common response in the early stages of learning is that superconduc- 
tivity and the quantum Hall effect are not fundamental and therefore not 
worth taking seriously. When this happens I just open up the AIP Handbook 
and show the disbeliever that the accepted values of e and h are defined by 
these effects, and that ends that. The world is full of things for which one's 
understanding, i.e. one's ability to predict what will happen in an experi- 
ment, is degraded by taking the system apart, including most delightfully the 
standard model of elementary particles itself. I myself have come to suspect 
that all the important outstanding problems in physics are emergent in natu- 
re, including particularly quantum gravity.
 One of the things an emergent phenomenon can do is create new par- 
ticles. When a large number of atoms condense into a crystal, the phonon, 
the elementary quantum of sound, becomes a perfectly legitimate particle at 
low energy scales. It propagates freely, does not decay, carries momentum 
and energy related to wavelength and frequency in the usual way, interacts by 
simple rules that may be verified experimentally, mediates the attractive in-

               Robert D. Laughlin   265

teraction responsible for conventional superconductivity, and so forth, and 
none of these things depends in detail on the underlying equations of mo- 
tion. They are generic properties of the crystalline state. The phonon ceases 
to have meaning when the crystal is taken apart, of course, because sound 
makes no sense in an isolated atom. A somewhat more esoteric example, al- 
though a more apt one, is the Landau quasiparticle of a metalB). This is an ex- 
cited quantum state that behaves like an extra electron added to a cold Fermi 
sea, but which is actually a complex motion of all the electrons in the metal. 
It is not possible to deduce the existence of quasiparticles from first prin- 
ciples. They exist instead as a generic feature of the metallic state; they cease 
to exist if the state does. This problem is not limited to solids. Even the hum- 
ble electron, the most elementary particle imaginable, carries a polarization 
of the Dirac sea with it as it travels from place to place and is thus itself a com- 
plex motion of all the electrons in the sea. In quantum physics there is no 
logical way to distinguish a real particle from an excited state of the system 
that behaves like one. We therefore use the same word for both.
 Whenever one is confronted with unpredictable emergent phenomena — 
which is to say almost always — there is need for a sound definition of sameness 
when comparing two states of matter. The one most of us prefer is the 
existence of a reversible adiabatic map. One imagines slowly changing the un- 
derlying equations of motion, checking at each stage to make sure the 
ground state and low-lying excitations have evolved in a one-to-one way. 
There is actually no need to check this if the system contains only a small 
number of particles, for the mapping is then guaranteed to be one-to-one by 
virtue of the adiabatic principle. But if the system contains a thermodynamic- 
ally large number of particles it can happen that a small change to the 
equations of motion results in a violent rearrangement of the ground state 
and low-lying excitations, and a corresponding breakdown of the one-to-one 
mapping. This is a quantum phase transition. We say that two states are the 
same phase of matter if they can be slowly transformed into each other with- 
out encountering a quantum phase transition, and different phases of matter 
if they cannot. By this definition metals, insulators, and superconductors are 
all different phases of matter, but two metals with slightly different electron- 
electron repulsion strengths are the same. This definition of sameness is one 
of the most powerful ideas in physics, for it relieves us of the need to compute 
the properties of complex systems from first principles to understand them. 
Instead we can just find a prototype that is easy to solve and then map our so- 
lution backward adiabatically.

SOLITONS
The idea that particles carrying parts of an elementary quantum number 
might occur as an emergent phenomenon is not new. Already in the 
late 1970s there was a serious theory literature on this subject stemming from 
a key paper of Jackiw and Rebbilli, but more generally from the rapid advan- 
ces in field theory made in association with the solution of the strong inter-

266                     Physics 1998


  /C\ /C\ /C\ /C\

 C      C      C      C      C


         /C\ ,C\ ,C\ 

 CCCCC




 C      C                                1  4   1 
                                    -2 -1 0     1   2  3
                                           E/t
Figure 1. Physics of polyacetylene. The symmetric configuration of the atoms shown in the upper 
left is absolutely unstable to a distortion that contracts every other bond. This causes the 1-elec- 
tron density of states, shown on the right, to acquire a gap. Formation of a domain wall results in 
the development of a state at mid gap (dotted curve on the right), and a net electric charge of +e 
if this state is empty.

actions. The topological soliton or kink particle of Jackiw and Rebbi is con- 
ceptually similar to the 't Hooft-Polyakov monopole [2, 31 and the skyrmion [4], 
both of which were proposed as simplified models of real elementary par- 
ticles. Solid state physicists first became aware of these ideas through a paper 
by Su, Schrieffer and Heeger[51 in which it was proposed that solitons might 
be the charge carriers of the conducting polymer polyacetylene. I first heard 
about this through my colleague Gene Mele, who was at the time working on 
the theory of polyacetylene in collaboration with Michael Rice at the Xerox 
Webster Research Center[61. Gene was obsessed with solitons and had gone to 
such lengths to make realistic models of them that he could convince any 
reasonable person of their existence, and quickly convinced me. This is, of 
course, a theorist's statement. People who were not experts in quantum me- 
chanics tended to find the idea outrageous, particularly since the experi- 
mental evidence for the existence of solitons was always indirect. It eventual- 
ly came to pass that enthusiasm for the soliton idea among funding agents 
waned, the particle theorists diverted their energies to strings, and solitons 
were effectively forgotten. It is difficult nowadays to find anyone younger 
than I am who knows anything about them. I have always found the history of 
solitons to be a poignant comment on the effect of fashion on scientific 
thought, for there was no doubt among well-informed physicists that the idea 
was right and of potentially great importance.
  The basic idea of the soliton is illustrated in Fig. 1. Polyacetylene is a zig-zag 
planar chain of CH units with every other bond contracted slightly. Because 
there are two equivalent ways of contracting the bonds, there is a possibility of 
domain walls between even-contracted regions and odd-contracted ones. 
These are the solitons. Realistic modeling reveals that these domain walls 
should be quite mobile, with an acceleration mass of about 10 times the elec-

                     Robert D. Laughlin            267


tron mass, and that they should carry either a net electric charge of e and no 
net spin, or a spin of 1/2 and no charge. This breakup of the charge and spin 
quantum numbers of the electron is the important new effect, for an exci- 
tation carrying charge but no spin, or vice versa, cannot be adiabatically de- 
formed into a free electron as a matter of principle. The excitations of a con- 
ventional insulator, on the other hand, are necessarily deformable into free 
electrons, and thus always have charge e and spin 1/ 2. The alleged properties 
of solitons were therefore quite unprecedented and extraordinary.
  The property of polyacetylene that causes solitons to exist is its discrete 
broken symmetry. If one wraps a molecule with an even number of segments 
into a ring, one discovers that it has two equivalent quantum-mechanical 
ground states rather than one, and that these transform into each other un- 
der clockwise rotation by one segment, a symmetry of the underlying equa- 
tions of motion. A conventional insulator would have only one ground state 
and would transform under this operation into itself. These two states acqui- 
re classical integrity in the thermodynamic limit. When the ring is small, local 
perturbations, such as a force applied to one atom only, can mix the two 
ground states in arbitrary ways, and in particular can tunnel the system from 
the even-doubled state to the odd-doubled one. But this tunneling becomes 
exponentially suppressed as the size of the ring grows, and eventually be- 
comes insignificant. Classical integrity and two-fold degeneracy together 
make the broken-symmetry state fundamentally different from the conven- 
tional insulating state; one cannot be deformed into the other in the ther- 
modynamic limit without encountering a quantum phase transition.
  The peculiar quantum numbers of the soliton are caused by the formation 
of a mid-gap state in the electron spectrum. The N-electron model Hamil- 
tonian [5]
           N
         = E to 
                           a

                  h2 82
                  2M (94 + 2k(x1+1 sj)2}           (1)


is solved in the limit of large M by picking fixed displacements xi + 1 — xi = ± 81 
and then minimizing the expected energy per site;

      <7.1>             21r
           = ik(16)2 - Z V (1 62) + (1 — 52) cos(8) de . (2)

A nonzero value of S is obtained for any value of k, as the chain is absolutely 
unstable to symmetry breaking by virtue of the Peierls effect. The gapped 
electron spectrum shown in Fig. 1 is the density of states for 6 = 0.1. When the 
equation is solved again for the soliton one finds an extra state in the center 
of the gap. The soliton has charge +e when this state is unoccupied. The re- 
maining charge and spin states just reflect the various ways the mid-gap state 
can be populated with electrons.

268             Physics 1998

 The fact that the soliton has charge +e when unoccupied was first discover- 
ed numerically[71 and then subsequently explained by Schrieffer using his 
now-famous adiabatic winding argument[8]. This idea is critical to the theory 
of the fractional quantum hall effect, so I shall review it here briefly. One im- 
agines adding a perturbation Hamiltonian that forces the order parameter to 
have a certain phase 4 far from the origin. One then imagines locking the 
phase at the left end of the molecule to zero and then adiabatically advancing 
4 at the right end from 0 to K. While this is occurring the entire ground state 
at the right end is slowly sliding to the right, pumping electric charge out to 
infinity as it does so. The amount pumped by winding by it must be one elec- 
tron, half the charge of the unit cell, since winding by twice this much just 
moves the unit cell over. But there is no net transfer of spin, as the system is a 
gapped singlet at every step in the operation. Since the operation also creates 
a soliton, we conclude that the soliton can have spin. 0 and charge +e. It is 
deeply important that this argument is completely model-independent and 
relies only on the discrete broken symmetry of the bulk interior and the pos- 
sibility of deforming the Hamiltonian into something simple at the ends of 
the sample without collapsing the gap.
 There was an important variant of the soliton idea that foreshadowed the 
fractional quantum Hall discoveries, namely when the polyacetylene was ima- 
gined to be so severely p-type {loped that the number of electrons in the iv 
band is 2N/3 rather than 1V181. Then the instability is to contract every third 
bond, and there are two kinds of soliton — one winding forward by 27r/3 and 
the other winding backward by the same amount — with charges +2e/3 and 
+4e/3 when all their mid-gap states are empty. So the separation of the spin 
and charge degrees of freedom of the electron in native polyacetylene is a 
special case of a more general effect in which the charge quantum number is 
fractionalized. The tendency of the Peierls instability to commensurate is ac- 
tually so strong that fractionalization is expected to occur at other rational fil-  
lings as well, for example 3N/4 and 3N/5. Indeed the only reason it would 
not occur at all rational fillings is that the gap for most of these states is small 
and thus susceptible to being overwhelmed by the ion kinetic energy (which 
we have neglected), finite temperature, or dirt. These effects all favor frac- 
tions with small denominators.
 The fact that these beautiful and reasonable ideas of Schrieffer and Su 
never became widely accepted may be traced in the end to one key difficulty: 
Long-range bond-contraction order was never found in polyacetylene. It is 
perfectly possible for solitons to exist if the discrete symmetry breaking has 
not set in globally — for example if it is interrupted every now and again by 
sample imperfections — and many experiments were done in highly defective 
and disordered polyacetylene with just this idea in mind. But the existence of 
solitons is inescapable only if the sample orders. This is a beautiful example of 
the special role ordering phenomena play in solid state physics, for while not 
always necessary they are often sufficient to demonstrate the truth of a thing. 
The problem with polymers in this context is that they owe most of their 
unique properties to noncrystallinity and are intentionally designed to tangle

               Robert D. Laughlin  269

and disorder, i.e. not to do the one thing that would prove the existence of 
solitons. So in this sense the hope of demonstrating fractional quantization in 
real polyacetylene was doomed from the start.

LOCALIZATION
The 2-dimensional electron gas of a silicon field-effect transistor or a GaAs 
heterostructure, the venue of the integral and fractional quantum Hall ef- 
fects, is notoriously imperfect. This is important because it immediately eli- 
minates the possibility that microscopic details are responsible for Klaus von 
Klitzing's magnificent effect, the highly accurate quantization of the Hall con- 
ductance to integral multiples of e2/ . The field-effect transistor, for exam- 
ple, is made by oxidizing the surface of a piece of silicon, an operation that al- 
ways results in microscopic strain and bond disorder at the surface because 
the silicon and SiO2 lattice parameters do not match. This problem is so 
troublesome that it is customary to oxidize in the presence of a small partial 
pressure of water so that hydrogen is available to tying up the occasional 
dangling silicon bond. GaAs heterostructures are better in this regard, as the 
interface between the GaAs and the Alpal _ ,As alloy is nominally epitaxial, 
but the Al atoms are still substituted at random in the GaAs lattice and are 
thus scattering centers. In either system there is the problem of the dopant 
ions, which are always strong scatterers because they are stripped of their car- 
riers and thus Coulombic. The technique of modulation doping, invented by 
my co-winner Horst Stormer, mitigates this effect enormously but does not 
eliminate it. And of course there are chemical impurities gettered to the in- 
terface in unknown amounts. It is true that modern heterostructures have 
huge mobilities undreamed of in the old days, but they are not perfect.
 Nor, as it turns out, would one want them to be. Imperfection is required 
for the quantum Hall effect to occur in the customary experimental confi- 
guration. Consider the sitution, illustrated in Fig. 2, of a translationally in- 
variant strip of charge density p in a normal magnetic field B. Because of 
translational invariance, flowing current along the strip is the same as 
Lorentz boosting by speed v, which gives a current j= vp, an electric field E= 
vB/c, and a Hall conductance

               Cr" = J pc          (3)

In a real field-effect transistor or heterostructure p is fixed by doping and the  
gate voltage and is not accurately quantized. Often it is the variable against 
which the Hall plateaus are plotted. Thus this result is inconsistent with all 
quantum Hall experiments. Sample imperfection is implicated in the for- 
mation of plateaus because it is the only agent in the problem, other than 
sample ends, capable of destroying translational invariance.
 The most obvious thing for disorder to do is cause Anderson localiza- 
tiontl°1. Localization is the underlying cause of the insulating state that result

270                                                                                                                Physics 1998







Figure 2. When a disorder-free 2-d electron gas is placed in a magnetic field it can be Lorentz 
boosted to generate a current and a transverse electric field. The ratio of these then gives Eqn. 
(3), which is inconsistent with all quantum Hall experiments. This shows that disorder is essential 
for plateau formation.


when an idealized noninteracting metal is subjected to a sufficiently large 
random potential. It simply means that all the eigenstates of the 1-electron 
Hamiltonian below a certain energy have finite spatial extent, so that occupy- 
ing them with electrons contributes nothing to the zero-frequency conduc- 
tivity. Real metals, in which the electrons interact, have a similar metal-insula- 
tor transition, and it is believed that the two states of matter in question are 
adiabatically continuable to their noninteracting counterparts. Already at the 
time of the quantum Hall discovery there was a large literature on localiza- 
tion in 2-d metals, particularly those occurring in semiconductors, and it was 
known that localization effects were so strong in the absence of a magnetic 
field that only the insulating state should exist at zero temperature[11]-[14]. 
So there were many reasons to suspect the quantum Hall effect of being an 
emergent phenomenon that, like the Anderson insulator, could be under- 
stood solely in terms of 1-electron quantum mechanics and localization.
        There are two important exact results that are particularly important for 
developing this idea. The first is the solution of the trivial model

                                                                               N                                                                                           2
                                                                   = Ef [7— — :Am)] + Eey•                                                                                                                                                                              (4) 
                                                                               I               "in

where
                                                                                                               A(r) = Byi .                                                                                                                                             (5) 
With lengths measured in multiples of

                                                                I = h                   mac                          Vhe     eB                                    k             = , e w eBme) ,                                                                        (6) 

one finds this to be a Slater determinant of the orbitals

                                 ,n(X                        =          V2nnVii:L.                                     eikze0i+vo-k)2/2(8 8 /2( Ine-(y+yo-kr                     'ay'                                                                     ,             (7)
where yo = eE 1/hco, the energies of which are

                                                   Ek = (n 1/2)hwc hck(-)—                                                                                 E mc2                                     E 2 •                                                              (8)

                          Robert D. Laughlin                    271



If the electric field E is small, so there is a large gap between Landau levels n 
and n + 1, and the chemical potential is adjusted to lie in this gap, then the 
number of electrons in the sample is N= n LL727a2, the charge density is 
p = ne/27a2, and Eqn. (3) becomes ox, = pc/ B = ne2 / h. As a check on this 
result we note that

         1    I          he
        771    14,„(x,y)(-0--x- —Az)          dxdy = c    .     (9)

Thus the current carried by each orbital is e times classical drift velocity cE/B. 
Adding these up and dividing by the sample area, we find that

                            J= ne2                             (10)


The second important result is the exact solution of the Hamiltonian


                        = 71 v0t2 Eo2(,::)




originally worked out by R. E. Prange [151. The &function impurity potential is 
found to bind a single localized state down from each Landau level, and this 
state does not carry electric current, consistent with one's intuition. However, 
the remaining delocalized states turn out to be carrying too much, and the 
sum of the excess just exactly cancels the loss of a state! So the presence of the 
impurity has no effect on the Hall conductance. I have always found this 
result astonishing, for it is as though the remaining delocalized states under- 
stood that one of their comrades had been killed and were pulling harder to 
make up for its loss.
  In the light of hindsight it is possible to prove that the Prange effect occurs 
for a broad class of impurity potentials. For this we must invoke some more 
general principles, for it is scarcely practical to diagonalize all possible im- 
purity Hamiltonians and compute the current carried by their thermodynam- 
ically large number of orbitals one by one. Instead we notice that the current 
operator is formally the derivative of the Hamiltonian with respect to vector 
potential[161. That is if we let


                                 +                             (12)

where A0 is a constant, then


                  e     pia e                ON
                  —     7— —fiztri = —C                        (13)
                          OZ C               49Ao


This is actually true when the particles interact as well, a fact that will prove 
useful later. Normally this relation is of little help, for the addition of a con- 
stant vector potential is simply a gauge transformation, which has no physical 
meaning. But if the sample is wrapped into a loop, as shown in Fig. 3, then Ao 
acquires the physical meaning of a magnetic flux q5 = AoLx forced through the

 272              Physics 1998









                        ■••■■■nimuu

                        ■1111M1111111r1111■■11M■

                        smnimummumm

                        R•11•11■■■111111•111■

                        0


Figure 3. Illustration of thought experiment identifying quantum of Hall conductance with the 
electron charge. As magnetic flux AO = Weis adiabatically forced through the loop, one electron 
per Landau level is transferred from one edge to the other. In the absence of disorder the trans- 
fer is accomplished by a mechanical shift of the 1-body wavefunctions that evolves each wave- 
function into its neighbor. When small amounts of disorder are present the number of electrons 
transferred must be exactly the same, but the mechanism of transfer is not, for the wavefunctions 
are violently distorted by even the smallest perturbation.




loop. Let us now imagine picking a sequence of flux values and solving the 

problem


               n#1414,>= Eolifo> ,       (14)


for each one, so that the many-body ground state IVio > and corresponding 

energy eigenvalue EE are tabulated functions of 0. Then by Hellman-Feynman 

theorem we have

                    00 a        az 0 *
         <,01—Iwo>= — <4'4,17.1014'0>=   (15)
          _ 00                   0


That is, the total current at any given value of of 0 is just the adiabatic deriva- 

tive of the total energy with respect to 0. This is actually not surprising, for 

slowly changing 0 creates an electromotive force around the loop, which 

does work on the system if current is flowing. If there is no dissipation then 

the energy eigenvalue must increase accordingly. The effect is just Faraday's 

law of induction. Now if the loop is large, so that Aharonov-Bohm oscillations 

are suppressed and the current changes negligibly during the insertion pro- 

cess, the adiabatic derivative may be replaced by a differential




                  / = cLIE               (16)
                      AO



where the denominator is the flux quantum hc/e. The advantage of this is that 

7i.40 is then exactly equal to Ho up to a gauge transformation. This means that 

the energy can have increased only through repopulation of the original 

states. How this comes about in the translationally-invariant case is shown in 

Fig. 3. The orbitals in the presence of nonzero 0 are




  th,n(z,    1 = eikze(v+yo-k-003/2(tre-(y+yo-k-a)2 , 07)
         V2n

                                    Robert D. Laughlin                                 273



 where a = el00/hcLx. As 0 is advanced from 0 to AO they simply slide over like 

 a shift register, the net result being to transfer one state per Landau level 

 from the left side of the sample to the right, i.e.to transfer one electron across 

 the sample per occupied Landau level. If the potential difference between 

 the two sides is V 

 we thus have                            neV        e2
                                  I= C-AO = n— .                                      (18)



 Now we can imagine turning on a small impurity potential in the interior of 

 the ribbon. If the potential is sufficiently small that the gaps between Landau 

 levels remain clean then there can be no change in the outcome of this 

 thought experiment, for adiabatic evolution of 0 stuffs exactly one state per 

 Landau level into the disordered region on the left side and pulls exactly one 

 out on the right. Conservation of states requires that they get through some- 

 how. This applies not only to random potentials but non-random ones as well, 

 including the &function used by Prange. Thus we have shown that any 1-elec- 

 tron Hamiltonian that can be adiabatically evolved into ideal Landau levels 

 without having states cross the fermi level has an exactly quantized Hall con- 

 ductance.

   This previous argument can be significantly strengthened if the potential is 

 random. In Fig. 4 we plot the 1-electron density of states of the Hamiltonian


                                                      2
                               I [ h
                    = Et_ _v 2m i        --e c24(ri)1 Vrando„,M )                     (19)


 for various stengths of Vrandom• The exact shape of this density of states is 

 model-dependent, but the basic features are not. When Kandorn is small its 

 primary effect is to break the degeneracy of the Landau level. The states in 

 the tails of the distribution that results are localized. This is easiest to see in 

 the limit that Vrandom is slowly-varying and smooth, for then the 1-body eigen-











   D(E)







                 0.5 1.5 2.5 3.5                            0.5 1.5 2.5 3.5
                        E/hwc                                      E Ihurc

Figure 4. Effect of disorder on the 1-body density of states. Landau levels at (n + 1/2) hco c, which 
are highly degenerate, first broaden slightly without filling in the gap, thus maintaining the quan- 
 tum Hall sum rule without the need to invoke localization. The states in the tails are localized, 
however, so the fermi level may be moved down into them with no ill effects. Additional disorder 
broadens the spectrum further until the tails grow together. The quantization is still exact, how- 
ever, because all the states at the fermi surface are localized. This enables the quantum Hall ef- 
fect to occur even when there are no true gaps.

274                     Physics 1998


states are well approximated as racetracks that travel along equipotentials. 
The analogy commonly drawn is with a mountainous landscape filled up to a 
certain height with water[171. If the water level is low one gets small, isolated 
lakes, which become increasingly isolated as the water level drops because the 
deepest valleys occur rarely. If it is high one gets small, isolated islands, which 
become increasingly isolated as the water level rises because the tallest moun- 
tains occur rarely. Somewhere in the middle is a percolation point dominated 
at long length scales by a vast, crenylated shoreline which cannot distinguish 
islands from lakes. The significance of localization in the tails is that localized 
states are "not there" in the flux-winding thought experiment, in the sense 
that a state confined to one side of the loop cannot tell that the vector po- 
tential being added adiabatically is associated with flux (1) through the loop. It 
thinks that we are doing a gauge transformation, so it simply changes its 
phase. It does not move in response to addition of (/), and its energy does not 
change. This means that it contributes nothing to the sum rule, and that 
whether it is occupied or not is irrelevant to the thought experiment. Thus 
the theorem of exact quantization is true not only if there are no states at the 
Fermi level, but also if all the states at the Fermi level are localized.
  The ability of the exact quantization theorem to be extended to cases 
where the density of states does not have true gaps is crucial for accounting 
for real quantum Hall experiments. A field-effect transistor is basically a capa- 
citor. It stores charge in response to the application of a gate voltage by the 
rule Q= CVO, where Cis determined by the oxide thickness, sample area, and 
little else. Accordingly, a sweep of the gate voltage is really a sweep of Q not of 
chemical potential. The chemical potential in a real experiment simply ad- 
justs itself to whatever is required to fix the charge at Q Thus, if it were not 
for localization, the chemical potential would always be pinned in a Landau 
level, this Landau level would always be only partially occupied, and the con- 
ditions for observing the quantum Hall effect would never be achieved. But if 
the Fermi level lies in a region of localized states then the chemical potential 
can move about freely, populating or depopulating the localized states at will 
with no effect whatsoever on the Hall conductance. Another aspect of the ex- 
periments nicely accounted for by localization is lack of parallel resistance. In 
the limit that the electrons do not interact the parallel conductance cr. is due 
to electric dipole transitions from states just below the Fermi level to just 
above. If the states in question are localized, cr. must be zero. Localization 
causes insulation. However, the resistivity and conductivity tensors are inver- 
ses of each other, so that if csxy= ne2/h we also have



           Pzz Psy      Ozz Ozy        h    0 —1
           Pyz PYY      Crliz frYY    ne2   1   0       (20)

Note that experiments that tune the magnetic field strength instead of Vg are 
not fundamentally different, as they simply vary the length scale against 
which the charge density is measured. This still requires the chemical poten- 
tial to adjust itself to keep Qfixed.

              Robert D. Laughlin   275

 The flux-winding experiment also demonstrates that small amounts of dis- 
order cannot completely localize all the states in a Landau level. There must 
be extended states, for if there were not, the whole Landau level would be 
"not there" and therefore incapable of carrying current. This is a very non- 
trivial result, for the arguments that all states should be localized in 2 dimen-  
sions in the absence of a magnetic field are sound. Just exactly where the ex- 
tended states reside in the weak-disorder limit is a matter of some debate. 
Most experiments are consistent with the idea, originally proposed by Levine, 
Libby, and Pruisken[181, that there is a scaling theory of localization for this 
problem, although a different one from the field-free case, and that the ex- 
tended states occur at one and only one energy somewhere near the center of 
the broadened Landau level. The strong-disorder limit is not controversial at 
all, however, for it is clear that complete localization must occur in this case.  
Another important implication of the flux-winding result therefore is that ex- 
tended state bands cannot simply disappear but must "float" through the 
fermi surface as the disorder potential is increased, for only when extended 
states appear at the Fermi energy does the argument fail. The floating effect, 
which was predicted simultaneously by David Khmel'nitzkii and mer19' 20], was 
eventually observed experimentallyr211.
 The larger idea underlying these arguments is that the quantum Hall effect 
is an emergent phenomenon characterized by the ability of the matter in 
question to pump an integral number of electrons across the sample in a flux- 
winding experiment. The noninteracting models we have been discussing are 
nothing but prototypes; having understood them we identify the real experi- 
ments as their adiabatic continuations. This is not a very radical idea, for ex- 
cept for the presence of a magnetic field the ideal Landau level is not that dif-  
ferent from a band insulator, a state of matter known to be continuable to its 
noninteracting prototype or, more precisely, defined by this property. The in- 
tegrity of the low-lying excitations in either case is protected by the existence  
of the gap, which assures there are no other states into which a low-energy ex- 
citation can decay. This does not prove that other states are impossible — 
which is fortunate since the discovery of the fractional quantum Hall effect 
proves otherwise — but it does show that it makes sense, particularly since 
there are plenty of experimental instances of adiabatic continuability from an 
interacting system to a noninteracting one in solid state physics. If the state in 
question does map to a noninteracting prototype then a flux-winding experi- 
ment either dissipates or pumps an integral number of electrons across the 
sample. When the latter occurs, the Hall conductance is accurately quantized. 
The reason is that it measures the charge of the particle being pumped, in 
this case the charge of the electron.

FRACTIONAL QUANTUM HALL STATE
The fractional quantum Hall state is not adiabatically deformable to any non- 
interacting electron state. I am always astonished at how upset people get 
over this statement, for with a proper definition of a state of matter and a full

276                                         Physics 1998


understanding of the integral quantum Hall effect there is no other possible 
conclusion. The Hall conductance would necessarily be quantized to an in- 
teger because it is conserved by the adiabatic map and is an integer in the 
noninteracting limit by virtue of gauge invariance and the discreteness of the 
electron charge. So the fractional quantum Hall state is something unprece- 
dented — a new state of matter.
   Its phenomenology, however, is the same as that of the integral quantum 
Hall state in almost every detai1r221. There is a plateau. The Hall conductance 
in the plateau is accurately a pure number times e2/h. The parallel resistance 
and conductance are both zero in the plateau. Finite-temperature deviations 
from exact quantization are activated or obey the Mott variable-range hop- 
ping law, depending on the temperature. The only qualitative difference be- 
tween the two effects is the quantum of Hall conductance.
   Given these facts the simplest and most obvious explanation, indeed the 
only conceivable one, is that the new state is adiabatically deformable into 
something physically similar to a filled Landau level except with fractionally- 
charged excitations. Adiabatic winding of a flux quantum — which returns the 
Hamiltonian back to itself exactly — must transfer an integral number of 
these objects across the sample. Localization of the objects must account for 
the existence of the plateau. All the arguments about deformability and ex- 
actness of the quantization must go through as before. As is commonly the 
case with new emergent phenomena, it is the experiments that tell us these 
things must be true, not theories. Theories can help us better understand the 
experiments, in particular by providing a tangible prototype vacuum, but the 
deeper reason to accept these conclusions is that the experiments give us no 
alternative.
   My prototype ground state for the original 1/3 effect discovered by Tsui, 
Stormer, and Gossard isr231



                           ...,ZN) =            (z, - zk)m exp [-4y                  1,121              (21)
                                         i<k>

where m is an odd integer, in this case 3, and zi = aci + is the location of the 
jth particle expressed as a complex number. Horst likes to joke that his whole 
effect fits in one tiny equation, and I am deeply flattered every time he makes 
this joke in public, but the truth is that the equation is simple only because he 
and Dan had the good fortune to find the 1/3 state first. Most of the other 30- 
odd fractional quantum Hall vacua that have now been discovered do not 
have prototypes this simple, and I would be remiss in not pointing out that 
there are now reasonable alternatives[241. These ground states are all adia- 
batically deformable into each other, however, and are in this sense funda- 
mentally the same. My wavefunction was originally conceived as a variational 
ground state for the model Hamiltonian


                          2m                c   11 = Et 1 - v • - e -Av.) 2 ] + Vion(Fj)} E -        , (22)
                                                                               j<k

                         Robert D. Laughlin                  277


where

        ti
           = 2(x9 - 0)        Von(r) = -p      v(F -      . (23)
                                         sample

The ion potential is present only because one of the electron-electron repul- 

sions we wish to consider is the coulomb interaction v(r) = e2/ r, which must 

be neutralized by a background charge density p for the system to be stable. 

This wavefunction was subsequently shown by Duncan Haldane to be an ex- 

act ground state of a class of Hamiltonians with nonlocal potentials1251.

  The most important feature of this wavefunction is that it locks the electron 

density at exactly 1/ 2/rm/ 2 in the limit that N becomes thermodynamically 

large. We know this to be true because the square of the wavefunction is 

equivalent to the probability distribution function of a classical one-compo- 

nent plasma. Letting



                 IW(zi, • ••, zN)I2 = e-134(zt,--,zN)       (24)


and choosing ie =1/ m to make the analogy transparent, we obtain


                             N              171N
          0(Zi, ..., Z N) = -2.2 E In Izi - zk I + — E 1,12 (25)
                                           212 
                            :1<k               i

This is the potential energy of particles of "charge" m repelling each other 
logarithmically - the natural coulomb potential in 2 dimensions - and being 

attracted to the origin a uniform "charge" density 1/2,r12. In order to have 

local electrical neutrality, which is essential in a plasma, the particles must 
have density p= I/ 27rm /2.

 It is also very important that the state is not crystalline when m is small. This 

is obvious for the case of m = 1, for then the wavefunction is just a full Landau 

level, but for other values of m one must appeal to the extensive literature on 

the classical one-component plasma1271. Numerical studies have shown that 

crystallinity - or, more precisely, power-law correlations, for true crystallinity 

is impossible in 2 dimensions at finite temperature - occurs when the thermal 

coupling constant 1"" =2m is about 140. Thus we are deeply in the liquid range 

at m = 3, and generally when m is a small odd integer. It was partially on the 

basis of this that I predicted the existence of a fractional quantum Hall state 

at 1/5, which was eventually found experimentally1281.

 Another important feature of this state is the gap in its excitation spectrum, 

which it to say its preferred density. This gap is indicated by the experiments 

and also by the functional form of Vim, which gives only densities 1/ 27rm t2, 

but was demonstrated rigorously to exist only when Haldane and Rezayi nu- 
merically diagonalized Eqn. (22) on a small sphere1291. Exactly the same value 

for this gap - about 0.08 e2/ /for the coulombic case at m = 3 - was obtained by 

Girvin, MacDonald and Platzman1301 using hydrodynamic arguments. This is 

important because it identifies the lowest-energy excitation to be a quantum 

of compressional sound. In most quantum fluids the density operator pq, ap-

278                       Physics 1998


propriately projected, has a large amplitude to create a phonon. If one as- 
sumes this to be the only significant amplitude then one can exploit a sum 
rule to express the excitation energy Eq in terms of ground state properties 
solely[311. Thus letting



                         = P [Eeif-6 p                      (26)



where Pis the projector onto the lowest Landau level, and denoting by I x > 
an arbitrary excited state of the Hamiltonian of energy E above the ground 
state, we have



     Fiq      Ex1 <x10,14,.,> 12 1 < AkmIV-g,  kglliWrn >   (27)
            E. 1 <z1/34/11P.> 12 2   <*mlii-gAgitim >


The rigidity of the classical plasma implicit in Vin, causes the denominator of 
this expression to vanish unusually rapidly as -4 -) 0, the result being that Eq 
comes in at a finite constant. The dispersion relation has a shallow minimum 
at q= 1.4//for m = 3, a value close to the ordering wavevector q= 1.56/ /of the 
competing Wigner crystal. This minimum is aptly analogous to the roton of 
liquid 4He. Eq is quite similar to the dispersion relation the conventional ex- 
citon in a filled Landau leve11321.
  The existence of an energy gap is sufficient to prove that the state has ele- 
mentary excitations that carry a fraction of the electron charge. One ima- 
gines a thought experiment, illustrated in Fig. 5, in which the sample is poked 
with a thin magnetic solenoid through which magnetic flux is adiabatically 
inserted. What happens near the solenoid in this process is complicated and























Figure 5. Illustration of thought experiment demonstrating the existence of fractionally-charged 
excitations. A fractional quantum Hall ground state is pierced with an infinitely thin magnetic 
solenoid, through which magnetic flux p is inserted adiabatically. The effect far away from the 
solenoid is to move states toward the solenoid. Advancing the phase all the way to Ap = hc/e 
returns the Hamiltonian to its original state, up to an unimportant gauge transformation. This 
means that exactly one state must be transported through the surface of a large Gauss's law pill- 
box centered at the solenoid, and also that the solenoid may be removed at the end with no ill ef- 
fects. The net result is the creation of an eigenstate of the original Hamiltonian with charge e/m, 
the average charge per state at infinity.

