          RUDOLF L. MOSSBAUER

    Recoilless nuclear resonance absorption 
           of gamma radiation
          Nobel Lecture, December 11, 1961

It is a high distinction to be permitted to address you on the subject of 
recoilless nuclear resonance absorption of gamma radiation. The methods 
used in this special branch of experimental physics have recently found ac- 
ceptance in many areas of science. I take the liberty to confine myself essen- 
tially to the work which I was able to carry out in the years 1955 to 1958 
at the Max Planck Institute in Heidelberg, and which finally led to estab- 
lishment of the field of recoilless nuclear resonance absorption. Many in- 
vestigators shared in the preparations of the basis for the research we are 
concerned with in this lecture. As early as the middle of the last century 
Stokes observed, in the case of fluorite, the phenomenon now known as flu- 
orescence - namely, that solids, liquids, and gases under certain conditions 
partially absorb incident electromagnetic radiation which immediately is re- 
radiated. A special case is the so-called resonance fluorescence, a phenomenon 
in which the re-emitted and the incident radiation both are of the same wave- 
length. The resonance fluorescence of the yellow D lines of sodium in so- 
dium vapour is a particularly notable and exhaustively studied example. In 
this optical type of resonance fluorescence, light sources are used in which 
the atoms undergo transitions from excited states to their ground states (Fig. 
1). The light quanta emitted in these transitions (A--->-B) are used to initiate 
the inverse process of resonance absorption in the atoms of an absorber 
which are identical with the radiating atoms. The atoms of the absorber un- 
dergo a transition here from the ground state (B) to the excited state (A), 
from which they again return to the ground state, after a certain time delay, 
by emission of fluorescent light.
 As early as 1929, Kuhn' had expressed the opinion that the resonance ab- 
sorption of gamma rays should constitute the nuclear physics analogue to 
this optical resonance fluorescence. Here, a radioactive source should replace 
the optical light source. The gamma rays emitted by this source should be 
able to initiate the inverse process of nuclear resonance absorption in an ab- 
sorber composed of nuclei of the same type as those decaying in the source.

                cceti.

        RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION 585
Again, the scheme of Fig. 1 would hold here, but the radiative transitions 
would now take place between nuclear states. Nevertheless, all attempts in 
the next two decades to find this nuclear resonance absorption proved fruit- 
less. Before I can approach the subject of my talk, it is appropriate to consider 
the reasons why the discovery of nuclear resonance absorption was so long 
delayed.
                       A Emission            AbsorptionE.



                       B                               O
                     Fig. 1. Scheme of resonance absorption.

   For simplicity, we shall first consider a nuclear transition of a free nucleus
at rest. The gamma quantum emitted in the transition             imparts a recoil 
momentum p to the emitting nucleus and consequently a kinetic energy 
which is given by

                           AE = F2 i 2M = E„212Mc2                           (1)

where M is the mass of the nucleus and c is the velocity of light. The energy 
liberated in this nuclear transition is divided, in accordance with the law of 
conservation of momentum, the larger part being carried away by the emit- 
ted quantum, the other part going to the emitting nucleus in the form of re- 
coil energy. This recoil-energy loss of the quantum has the consequence that 
the emission line does not appear at the position of the transition energy E, 
but is displaced to lower energy by an amount (Fig. 2). The absorption 
line, on the contrary, is displaced to a higher energy by the same amount
    , because in order for the process of resonance absorption to occur, a 
quantum must provide, in addition to the transition energy E, the amount 
of energy      which is taken up by the absorbing nucleus in the form of a
recoil kinetic energy. Typical values for the line shifts lie in the range 
from 10-2 eVto 102 eV; they are therefore very small in comparison with 
the energies of the gamma quanta, which frequently are of the order of mag- 
nitude of millions of electron volts.
   Since there is an uncertainty in the energies of the individual excited states

I586         1961 R.L.MOSSBAUER

  Emission line         Absorption line


















 Fig. 2. Position and shape of the emission and absorption lines of a free nucleus (shown 
      in the case of the I29-keV transition in 191Ir for T = 300°K).


 of the nuclei, the lines associated with transitions between an excited state 
 and the ground state have a certain minimum width. This so-called natural 
 width I' is, according to the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, connected 
 with the lifetime ti of an excited nuclear state by the relation Fr = h. The 
 usual values for the lifetimes z of the low-lying excited nuclear states lie in 
 the range from 10' to 10' second, corresponding to an interval of 108 
 to 10 4eV for the natural line widths appearing in ground-state transitions. 
 Such extraordinarily sharp lines exhibiting the natural line width are nor- 
 mally not observed. Rather, a series of side effects always exist, which lead 
 to considerable broadening such that the line widths ordinarily associated 
 with low-energy gamma transitions exceed the natural minimum width by 
 many orders of magnitude. The most important broadening mechanism is 
 the thermal motion of the nuclei in the source and in the absorber; this leads 
 to Doppler shifts in the energy of the gamma quanta and therefore produces 
 corresponding line broadenings. Even a temperature drop to absolute zero 
 does not extinguish this thermal broadening, since the existence of zero- 
 point energy at absolute zero frequently produces, at least in solids, line

      RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION 587
widths of the same order of magnitude as the ones existing at room tem- 
perature.
  Usually the line shifts are large in comparison to the thermal line
widths, and they are also always very large in comparison to the natural line 
widths associated with the low-energy nuclear transitions we are concerned 
with here. As a consequence, the energy of an emitted quantum is usually 
too small for the inverse process of resonance absorption to be carried out, or 
in other words, the probability of occurrence of nuclear resonance absorp- 
tion is so small that the process escapes detection. Therefore the long and un- 
 successful search for nuclear resonance absorption is to be blamed on the high 
recoil-energy losses of the gamma quanta.
   On the other hand, entirely different conditions hold for optical resonance 
 absorption. There, because of the much lower energies of the light quanta, 
 the recoil-energy losses produced by light quanta are small in comparison 
with the line widths. Emission and absorption lines therefore overlap in an 
ideal manner, the resonance condition is satisfied, and the optical effect is, at 
 least in principle, easily observable.
   The unsatisfactory situation with respect to nuclear resonance absorption 
 first changed in 1951, when Moon' succeeded in demonstrating the effect 
 for the first time, by an ingenious experiment. The fundamental idea of his 
 experiment was that-of compensating for the recoil-energy losses of the gam- 
 ma quanta: the radioactive source used in the experiment was moved at a 
 suitably high velocity toward the absorber or scatterer. The displacement of 
 the emission line toward higher energies achieved in this way through the 
 Doppler effect produced a measurable nuclear fluorescence effect.
   After the existence of nuclear resonance fluorescence had been experi- 
 mentally proved, a number of methods were developed which made it pos- 
 sible to observe nuclear resonance absorption in various nuclei. In all these 
 methods for achieving measurable nuclear resonance effects the recoil-energy 
 loss associated with gamma emission or absorption was compensated for in 
 one way or another by the Doppler effect.
   At this point, let me speak of my esteemed teacher, Heinz Maier-Leibnitz, 
 who in 1953 directed my attention to this newly advancing field of nuclear 
 resonance fluorescence, and who stimulated me to turn to this area of re- 
 search. He was, also, the one who made it possible for me to conduct my re- 
 search throughout the years 1955 to 1958 at the Heidelberg Max Planck In- 
 stitute, in an undisturbed and fruitful atmosphere - research which finally led 
 to the discovery of recoilless nuclear resonance absorption. I want to express

588          1 9 6 1 R.L.MOSSBAUER
  Pb           Pb

           A






           10 cm
Fig. 3. Experimental arrangement. A, absorber-cryostat; Q, cryostat with source; D, 
          scintillation detector; K, lead collimator.

my warmest thanks to my esteemed teacher for his efforts on my behalf.
 The method which I shall now proceed to discuss differs fundamentally 
from the methods described above in that it attacks the problem of recoil- 
energy loss at its root in a manner which, in general, insures the complete 
elimination of this energy loss. The basic feature of this method is that the 
nuclei in the source and absorber are bound in crystals. The experiments 
described in the following paragraphs exclusively employed radioactive 
sources which emitted the 129-keV gamma line leading to the ground state 
in "'I r
 The first experiment3 aimed at measuring the lifetime of the 129-keV state 
in 191Ir by utilizing methods of nuclear resonance absorption known at that 
time. The experimental set-up used for this purpose is shown schematically 
in Fig. 3. A method first employed by Malmfors4appeared to be especially 
suitable for the planned measurement. In this method, a broadening of the 
emission or absorption line, leading to a corresponding increase in the degree 
of overlap of the two lines, is achieved by increasing the temperature. If the 
relative shift of the emission and the absorption lines resulting from the 
recoil-energy losses is only of the order of magnitude of the line widths, a 
temperature increase leads, under favourable conditions, to a measurable nu- 
clear absorption effect. In the case of the 129-keV transition in 191r, there is 
considerable overlap of the two lines even at room temperature as a con- 
sequence of the small energies of the quanta and the small line shifts resulting 
therefrom (see Fig. 2). In this case, not only an increase but also a decrease 
in temperature can result in a measurable change in the nuclear absorption.

    RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION       589
My decision between these two possibilities was made in favour of a tem- 
perature decrease. It was motivated essentially by the consideration that at 
low temperature, effects of chemical binding would be more likely than at 
elevated temperatures. This hypothesis was vindicated in an unexpected way 
during the course of the experiments. The simultaneous cooling of the source 
and the absorber with liquid air led to inexplicable results, for which I first 
blamed effects associated in some way with the cooling of the absorber. In 
order to eliminate these unwanted side effects, I finally left the absorber at 
room temperature and cooled only the source. In very tedious experiments, 
which demanded extremely stable apparatus, a small decrease in the absorp- 
tion with respect to the value at room temperature was in fact obtained - a 
result consistent with my expectations. The evaluation of these measurements 
finally led to the determination of the lifetime sought for.
 In a second series of experiments I attempted to explain the side effects 
which had appeared in the simultaneous cooling of the source and the ab- 
sorber during the earlier experiments. The result of this attempt was striking :



     0°10
                i                i            f


     -1%




     -2°10




     -3%so°       160°      240°       320°
                                   Temp (*K)
Fig. 4. Temperature dependence of the absorption. Relative intensity change AIR- in 
           comparison with that of a non-resonant absorber.

590         1 9 6 1 R.L.MOSSBAUER
instead of the decrease expected, a strong increase in the absorption clearly 
manifested itself when the absorber was cooled. This result was in complete 
contradiction to the theoretical expectation. The observed temperature de- 
pendence of this absorption is shown in Fig. 4.
 In considering the possible sources of the anomalous resonance effect, I 
now began to subject the hypothesis of the existing theory to a critical exam- 
ination.
 The views originally held as to the shape and energy of the emission and 
absorption lines were based on the assumption that the emitting and ab- 
sorbing nuclei can be treated as free particles. It was therefore natural to 
modify this assumption, taking into account the fact that source and absorber 
were each used in crystalline form. Therefore, I first attempted to explain 
the observed anomalous resonance absorption by assuming that the recoil 
momentum was not transferred to the single nucleus. It should rather be 
transferred to an assembly of nuclei or atoms which include nearest or next- 
nearest neighbours surrounding the nucleus under consideration. After the 
failure of this and other attempted explanations, based on a purely classical 
point of view, I turned my attention to a quantum-mechanical treatment of 
the problem.
 Let me here introduce some concepts from crystal physics, by means of 
which I will develop the reasoning that finally led to a solution of the prob- 
lem. All the internal motions of the particles forming the crystal lattice can 
be described in terms of a superposition of a large number of characteristic 
vibrations whose distribution is called the frequency spectrum of the crystal. 
The nature of the binding of the particles forming the crystal determines the 
structure of the lattice vibrational spectrum, this spectrum often being very 
complicated. Nevertheless, the substitution, for the true vibrational spectrum 
of the lattice, of a much simpler frequency distribution often suffices for 
qualitative considerations.
 This first, still purely classical picture of the internal motions in a crystal 
corresponds, in the quantum-mechanical description, to a system of uncoup- 
led harmonic oscillators with quantized energy states. While the vibrational 
spectrum describes only the distribution of the fundamental frequencies of 
these oscillators, the temperature determines the so-called occupation num- 
bers of these crystal oscillators; these occupation numbers simply tell which 
of the possible energy states the particular oscillators occupy.
 The recoil energy appearing in the emission or absorption of a quantum 
by a nucleus bound in a crystal is taken up by the crystal partly in the form

    RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION 591
of translational energy and partly in the form of internal energy. The result- 
ant increase in translational energy is always negligible because of the enor- 
mous mass of the crystal as a whole in comparison to the mass of a single 
nucleus. An increase in the internal energy leads to changes in the occupation 
numbers of the individual crystal oscillators. Because of the quantization of 
the oscillator energies, the crystal can absorb the recoil energy only in dis- 
crete amounts. The nuclear transitions of the bound nuclei are normally 
accompanied by simultaneous transitions of the crystal oscillators. Thus, for 
example, a gamma quantum can be emitted and simultaneously one of the 
crystal oscillators can undergo a transition to a neighbouring energy state. 
Likewise, a gamma emission process can be accompanied by simultaneous 
transitions of two crystal oscillators, and so forth. As a consequence of the 
quantization of the oscillators, there also exists in principle the possibility 
that the gamma transition takes place with none of the crystal oscillators 
changing their states.
 The problem now was to compute the probabilities of the various pro- 
cesses. Significant was the calculation of the probability of nuclear transitions 
leaving the lattice state unchanged - that is, transitions in which no recoil en- 
ergy is transferred to the lattice in the form of internal energy. Similar prob- 
lems had already been solved much earlier. The coherent scattering of X-rays 
from crystals had been known for decades; in that case a momentum transfer 
to the reflecting lattice takes place without simultaneous transfer of internal 
energy to the crystal. And for a long time the analogous problem of the 
elastic scattering of slow neutrons from crystals had been thoroughly studied, 
both experimentally and theoretically. Lamb' had, as early as 1939, devel- 
oped a theory for the resonance capture of slow neutrons in crystals. This 
theoretical work was somewhat premature, inasmuch as Lamb assumed con- 
siderably smaller values for the widths of the neutron lines than were ob- 
served in later experiments. For this reason, this extraordinarily beautiful 
work was of no practical significance in the area of application originally 
intended. It remained only to apply this Lamb's theory to the analogous 
problem of the resonance absorption of gamma radiation. This indeed ena- 
bled me to show that under the conditions chosen in the experiments des- 
cribed above there exists a high probability of nuclear transitions with no 
simultaneous change of the lattice state. Since these nuclear transitions are 
not associated with any energy losses caused by recoil phenomena, I shall in 
the following discussion characterize these particular transitions as «recoil- 
less» transitions, and the lines associated with such transitions, as «recoilless

592         1961 R. L. MOSSBAUER
 lines». In such a recoilless emission process, the entire excitation energy is 
therefore transferred to the emitted quantum, and the corresponding situa- 
tion holds for the recoilless absorption. Here the notation «recoilless» relates  
only to recoil energy transferred in a nuclear transition, and not to the 
transferred momentum. The value of this transferred momentum is deter- 
mined by the energy of the gamma quantum and is essentially a constant, in- 
dependent of any change in the internal state of motion of the crystal. This 
momentum is, therefore, transferred to the lattice in all emission or absorption  
processes, even in the recoilless processes. It is always taken up by the crystal 
as a whole, and therefore the corresponding translational velocity is negli- 
gibly small.
 What are the conditions under which the recoilless nuclear resonance ab- 
sorption can be observed? In answering this question, I wish to develop here, 
without presenting the mathematical formulation of the theory, a detailed 
picture of the processes which take place in radiative transitions in nuclei 
bound in crystals. The recoil-energy loss that occurs in a nuclear transition 
of a free nucleus is given by Eq. (1). It can be shown that in a transition of 
a nucleus bound in a crystal, Eq. (1) is no longer valid for the individual 
process but holds in the means over many processes; that is, instead of Eq. 
(I), we now have
               zIE = E02/2Mc2      (2)
Let us now consider a very simple model, in which we describe the vibra- 
tional state of the crystal by a single frequency co, the so-called Einstein fre- 
quency. It is instructive to consider the two limiting cases, in which the 
mean recoil energy is either large or small in comparison to the transition 
energy of the Einstein oscillator:

              dE > taw (case 1) 
              dE < ha) (case 2)

In case 1, many oscillator transitions are required to take up the energy con- 
tribution dE in the lattice. The nuclear processes will therefore in general 
be accompanied by simultaneous transitions of many oscillators. The prob- 
ability of a nuclear transition taking place without any oscillator transition -  
that is, the probability of a recoilless process - is correspondingly small. The  
situation is entirely different in case 2. Here it is immediately evident that

      RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION 593

             w
             lO-





             08-



             0.6-                         E •c<tiw




             0.4 -





             0.2-





              O    0

                 HEE H-

             w 


             0.4-                        E »tuu



             02-


                              .1i1
              0            0111111111i-              r
                            5ts cr., 10 tu.    15110,

                         E 


Fig. 5. Relative probability for a gamma transition associated with simultaneous transi- 

tions of o, 1, a, ... n crystal oscillators, for two different values of SE for the temperature 
                               T o°K.



a nuclear transition which is accompanied by an oscillator transition occurs 

relatively seldom, leading under these circumstances to a high probability 

for recoilless processes. The probabilities, under these conditions, for the 

occurrence of gamma emission processes accompanied by 0, 1, 2, . . . n os- 

cillator transitions are shown in Fig. 5 for these two cases.

  For qualitative considerations this simple picture can well be applied to 

the case of the real crystal. The frequency spectrum of the real crystal ex- 

hibits an increasingly high oscillator density at high frequencies. It is suffi- 

cient, for this simplified consideration, to replace the Einstein frequency by 

the upper frequency of the vibrational spectrum of the real crystal. This

594         1 9 6 1 R .L.m s sB AuER
limiting frequency Cog is related, approximately, to the characteristic tem- 
perature 0 of the crystal by the equation hwg= kO.
 The essential condition for a high probability of recoilless nuclear transi- 
tions now has the form

               E2012Mc2 < k0      (3 )
The condition given here is quite restrictive because it limits the observation 
of recoilless resonance absorption to nuclear transitions of relatively low en- 
ergy; the upper limit lies at about 150 keV.
 if dE = E20/2Mc2 is small in comparison to the upper energy limit of the 
frequency spectrum, the percentage of recoilless processes that occur is high 
even at room temperature. However, if is about equal to the upper en- 
ergy limit of the frequency spectrum, then the probability of transitions of 
the crystal oscillators must be correspondingly reduced by the use of low 
temperatures in order to arrive at measurable effects.
 After the appearance of the observed strong resonance absorption in 
had been traced back to the phenomenon of recoilless nuclear resonance 
absorption, the next step was to compute the probability of the effect in a 
general form. This probability, also known as the Debye-Waller factor, in 
analogy with the terminology used in X-ray scattering, is, as I have already 
pointed out, strongly dependent on the temperature and the energy of the 
nuclear transition. This dependence is illustrated in Fig. 6 by two examples.
 The shape and location of the emission and absorption lines, as shown in 
Fig. 2 for the case of a free nucleus, are modified considerably by the influ- 
ence of the chemical binding. While the centres of the lines as given by Eq. 
(2) are retained, each of them shows a complicated structure which reflects 
different single and multiple oscillator transitions, hence the notion « line » is 
applied here in a more generalized sense.
 The most interesting prediction of the theory is the appearance of a strong 
line with the natural line width appearing in the structure of both « lines » at 
the position of the transition energy E. This line represents the recoilless 
processes. The strong prominence of these lines with the natural line width 
within the total line structure is not so surprising when one considers that 
all the recoilless processes in the emission and absorption spectra appear with- 
in an energy range of the order of magnitude of the natural line width. The 
gamma transitions associated with the oscillator transitions appear, on the 
other hand, in an energy range of the order of magnitude of the Debye

    RESONANCE ABSORPTION OF GAMMA RADIATION595



100°I.


                                 14.4 key
                                 = 420°K 
                                 57Fe

10./.

                     134 key
                     8 - 310°K 
                     187Re










0.1°/.     10      102     103      104
                                         Temp (° K )

Fig. 6. Fractions of recoil-free nuclear transitions (Debye-Waller factors) in 'Fe and 
          l'Re, shown as functions of the temperature.



temperature of the crystal; this energy range is always broader than the 
natural line width by many orders of magnitude.
 All these considerations provided a very plausible explanation of the or- 
igin of the observed resonance absorption in 191Ir at low temperatures. The 
agreement between the experimentally observed temperature dependence of 
the absorption (Fig. 4) and the theoretically computed dependence was 
satisfactory when one considered that in the first calculation the Debye ap- 
proximation was used for the frequency spectrum because the actual fre- 
quency spectra of the crystals used were not known. Notwithstanding this 
qualitative agreement between experiment and theory, the situation still 
appeared to be somewhat unsatisfactory. The theory predicted that under 
the prescribed conditions lines of natural width should appear in the struc- 
ture of the emission and absorption lines at the value of the transition en- 
ergy E0.
 While the assumption of the existence of these lines made it possible to 
explain the experiments thus far carried out, the keystone was evidently still 
missing - namely, direct experimental proof of the existence of these lines 
and, especially, a demonstration that their widths were indeed the natural

596         1 9 6 1 R. L. MOSSBAUER
line widths. It was necessary to find a detector which had the necessary en- 
ergy resolution to measure the profiles of these extremely sharp lines. The 
use of conventional detectors was excluded from the start. For example, the 
scintillation detectors frequently used for gamma-ray measurements in the 
relevant energy region have resolutions of the order of magnitude of 104 
eV, while the natural line widths of the observed lines were only about 10' 
eV. The possibility of using the atomic nuclei themselves as detectors was 
suggested as a way out of this situation. As was shown above, an essential 
prediction of the theory was that the recoilless lines in both the emission 
and the absorption spectra should appear at the same position - that is, at the 
value of the transition energy.
 Both lines would, therefore, overlap completely, this being the reason for 
the strong absorption effect. If one could succeed in partially removing the 
perfect overlap by a relative displacement of the lines, the absorption effect 
of the recoilless lines should disappear correspondingly.
 In the experiment carried out to test the validity of this prediction, the 
idea was to accomplish the relative shift of the lines by means of the Doppler 
effect, so that a relative velocity would be imparted to the nuclei of the 
source with respect to the nuclei of the absorber. Here we had a sort of 
reversal of the experiment carried out by Moon. Whereas in that experiment 
the resonance condition destroyed by the recoil-energy losses was regained











         •



    10 cm    Pb
Fig. 7. Experimental arrangement. A, absorber-cryostat; Q, rotating cryostat with 
           source; D, scintillation detector.

            RESONANCE                  ABSORPTION                  OF GAMMA RADIATION                                        597

                      I     -2-105                                     2.10-5               4-10-5                E

                                  -4                                +4               +E cmisec                   V


                 - 0.4 'V. -


                 - Q8% -


                   -12% -

Fig. 8. Relative intensity ratio JI/I of gamma radiation measured behind the resonant 
iridium absorber, in comparison with intensities measured behind a nonresonant 
                                                           absorber.

by the application of an appropriate relative velocity, here the resonance 
condition fulfilled in the experiment was to be destroyed through the ap- 
plication of a relative velocity. And yet there was an essential difference be- 
tween this and Moon's experiment. There, the width of the lines that were 
displaced relative to one another was determined by the thermal motion of 
the nuclei in the source and absorber; here, the line widths were sharper by 
four orders of magnitude. This made it possible to shift them by applying 
velocities smaller by four orders of magnitude. The indicated velocities were 
in the region of centimeters per second.
    Fig. 7 shows the experimental arrangement'. For simplicity, I decided to 
move the source by means of a turn-table. Only the part of the rotational 
motion marked by the heavy line in Fig. 7 was used for the measurement - 
namely, that part in which the source was moving relative to the absorber 
with approximately constant velocity. The intensity at the detector was 
measured as a function of the relative velocity between the source and the 
absorber. Since the preparation of the conical-gear assembly necessary for 
adjusting the various velocities caused a disagreeable delay in this experiment 
which was so exciting for me, I took advantage of the existence in Germany 
of a highly developed industry for the production of mechanical toys. A

598         1961 R.L.MOSSBAUER
 day spent in the Heidelberg toy shops contributed materially to the accelera- 
 tion of the work.
  Fig. 8 shows the result of this experiment, a result which was just what 
 had been expected. As the figure demonstrates, a maximum resonance ab- 
 sorption was actually present at zero relative velocity as a result of the com- 
 plete superposition of the recoilless emission and absorption lines; therefore, 
 minimal radiation intensity passing through the absorber was observed in 
 the detector. With increasing relative velocity the emission line was shifted 
 to higher or lower energies, the resonance absorption decreased, and the ob- 
 served intensity correspondingly increased. The necessary relative velocities 
 were manifestly only of the order of centimeters per second. Since the ex- 
 periment consisted essentially of producing a shift of an emission line of 
 width T relative to an absorption line of width I', the observed line possessed 
a width which, with a small correction, was equal to 2 I'. It was especially 
 satisfying that the line width thus obtained agreed with the width determined 
 in the first experiment3 under much more difficult conditions. While ab- 
 sorption effects of the order of 1 per cent were observed in the second ex- 
 periment, an effect of the order of a hundredth of 1 per cent had been 
 achieved in the earlier work. Thus, direct proof of the existence of recoilless 
 absorption was achieved.
  The significance of the new method was immediately apparent, although 
 not all of its consequences were immediately realized. With 4.6 .10 'eV 
 the line width observed in the 129 keV gamma transition of 191Ir was already 
 smaller than the usual thermal line widths by many orders of magnitude.
 Let us define the energy resolving power E8E by the ratio of the energy E, 
 of the nuclear transition and the natural width r of the line; that is, E/oE =  
 Eo/F. Then we obtain in the present case E/oE = 2.8 x 1010. The actual 
 energy resolution achieved was already much greater in this experiment,
 since energy shifts amounting to a small fraction of the natural line width 
 were actually observed. Since then, it has become possible, by utilizing other  
 nuclear isotopes, to improve the obtainable energy resolution once more by 
 several orders of magnitude. It is this property of the recoilless nuclear res- 
 onance absorption - namely, that it is possible by this means to measure 
 extraordinarily small energy differences between two systems - which gave 
 the method its significance and opened up a broad field of possible applica- 
 tions.
  Thus, the extraordinary sharpness of the recoilless gamma lines brought 
 direct investigation of the hyperfine structure of nuclear transitions within

