122

THE MANIPULATION OF NEUTRAL PARTICLES

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1997 
by
STEVEN CHU
Stanford University, Departments of Physics and Applied Physics, Stanford, 
CA 94305-4060, USA



The written version of my lecture is a personal account of the development of 
laser cooling and trapping. Rather than give a balanced history of the field, I 
chose to present a personal glimpse of how my colleagues and I created our 
path of research.
 I joined Bell Laboratories in the fall of 1978 after working with Eugene 
Commins as a graduate student and post-doc at Berkeley on a parity non-con- 
servation experiment in atomic physics.' Bell Labs was a researcher's para- 
dise. Our management supplied us with funding, shielded us from bureauc- 
racy, and urged us to do the best science possible. The cramped labs and 
office cubicles forced us to rub shoulders with each other. Animated discus- 
sions frequently interrupted seminars and casual conversations in the cafete- 
ria would sometimes mark the beginning of a new collaboration.
 In my first years at Bell Labs, I wrote an internal memo on the prospects for 
x-ray microscopy and worked on an experiment investigating energy transfer 
in ruby with Hyatt Gibbs and Sam McCall as a means of studying Anderson 
Localization.2' 3 This work led us to consider the possibility of Mott or 
Anderson transitions in other exciton systems such as GaP:N with picosecond 
laser techniques.4 During this work, I accidentally discovered that picosecond 
pulses propagate with the group velocity, even when the velocity exceeds the 
speed of light or becomes negative.5
 While I was learning about excitons and how to build picosecond lasers, I 
began to work with Allan Mills, the world's expert on positrons and positro- 
nium. We began to discuss the possibility of working together while I was still 
at Berkeley, but did not actually begin the experiment until 1979. After three 
long and sometimes frustrating years, a long time by Bell Labs standards, we 
finally succeeded in exciting and measuring the 1S-2S energy interval in po- 
sitronium.6

MOVING TO HOLMDEL AND WARMING UP TO LASER COOLING
My entry into the field of laser cooling and trapping was stimulated by my 
move from Murray Hill, New Jersey, to head the Quantum Electronics 
Research Department at the Holmdel branch in the fall of 1983. During con- 
versations with Art Ashkin, an office neighbor at Holmdel, I began to learn

                Steven Chu         123

about his dream to trap atoms with light. He found an increasingly attentive 
listener and began to feed me copies of his reprints. That fall I was also joined 
by my new post-doc, Leo Hollberg. When I hired him, I had planned to con- 
struct an electron energy-loss spectrometer based on threshold ionization of 
a beam of atoms with a picosecond laser. We hoped to improve the energy 
resolution of existing spectrometers by at least an order of magnitude and 
then use our spectrometer to study molecular adsorbates on surfaces with op- 
tical resolution and electron sensitivity. However, Leo was trained as an atom- 
ic physicist and was also developing an interest in the possibility of manipula- 
ting atoms with light.
 Leo and I spontaneously decided to drive to Massachusetts to attend a 
workshop on the trapping of ions and atoms organized by David Pritchard at 
MIT. I was ignorant of the subject and lacked the primitive intuition that is 
essential to add something new to a field. As an example of my profound lack 
of understanding, I found myself wondering about the dispersive nature of 
the "dipole force". The force is attractive when the frequency of light is tuned 
below the resonance, repulsive when tuned above the resonance, and 
vanishes when tuned directly on the atomic resonance. Looking back on 
these early fumblings, I am embarrassed by how long it took me to recognize 
that the effect can be explained by freshman physics. On the other hand, I 
was not alone in my lack of intuition. When I asked a Bell Labs colleague 
about this effect, he answered, "Only Jim Gordon really understands the 
dipole force!"
 By 1980, the forces that light could exert on matter were well understood.? 
Maxwell's calculation of the momentum flux density of light,8 and the labo- 
ratory observation of light pressure on macroscopic objects by Lebedev9 and 
by Nichols and Hull19 provided the first quantitative understanding of how 
light could exert forces on material objects. Einstein" pointed out the quan- 
tum nature of this force: an atom that absorbs a photon of energy hv will re- 
ceive a momentum impulse hv/c along the direction of the incoming photon 
pi.. If the atom emits a photon with momentum Nut, the atom will recoil in 
the opposite direction. Thus the atom experiences a net momentum change 
ANtou, = pin-Nut due to this incoherent scattering process. In 1930, Frisch12 
observed the deflection of an atomic beam with light from a sodium reso- 
nance lamp where the average change in momentum was due to the scatter- 
ing of one photon.
 Since the scattered photon has no preferred direction, the net effect is due 
to the absorbed photons, resulting in scattering force, Fats = Npi„, where N is 
the number of photons scattered per second. Typical scattering rates for 
atoms excited by a laser tuned to a strong resonance line are on the order of 
107 to 108/sec. As an example, the velocity of a sodium atom changes by 3 
cm/sec per absorbed photon. The scattering force can be 105 times the 
gravitational acceleration on Earth, feeble compared to electromagnetic 
forces on charged particles, but stronger than any other long-range force that 
affect neutral particles.
 There is another type of force based on the lensing (i.e. coherent scatter-

124               Physics 1997

ing) of photons. A lens alters the distribution of momentum of a light field, 
and by Newton's third law, the lens must experience a reaction force equal 
and opposite to the rate of momentum change of the light field. For exam- 
ple, a positive lens will be drawn towards regions of high light intensity as 
shown in Fig. 1.13 In the case of an atom the amount of lensing is calculated 
by adding the amplitude of the incident light field with the dipole field 
generated by the atomic electrons driven by the incident field.
























Figure 1. A photograph of a 10 JAM glass sphere trapped in water with green light from an argon 
laser coming from above. The picture is a fluorescence image taken using a green blocking, red 
transmitting filter. The exiting (refracted) rays show a notable decrease in beam angles relative to 
the incident rays. The increased forward momentum of the light results in an upward force on 
the glass bead needed to balance the downward scattering force. The stria in the forward-scatter- 
ed light is a common Mie-scattering ring pattern. (Courtesy A. Ashkin).

This reaction force is also called the "dipole force". The oscillating electric 
field E of the light induces a dipole moment p on the particle. If the induced 
dipole moment is in phase with E, the interaction energy -p.E is lower in high 
field regions. If the induced dipole moment is out of phase with the driving 
field, the particle's energy is increased in the electric field and the particle 
will feel a force ejecting it out of the field. If we model the atom or particle as 
a damped harmonic oscillator, the sign change of the dipole force is easy to 
understand. An oscillator driven below its natural resonant frequency 
responds in phase with the driving field, while an oscillator driven above its 
natural frequency oscillates out of phase with the driving force. Exactly on 
resonance, the oscillator is 90 degrees out of phase and p-E = 0.
 The dipole force was first discussed by Askar'yan14 in connection with plas- 
mas as well as neutral atoms. The possibility of trapping atoms with this force 
was considered by Letokhov,15 who suggested that atoms might be confined 
along one dimension in the nodes or antinodes of a standing wave of light 
tuned far from an atomic transition. In 1970, Arthur Ashkin had succeeded

                    Steven Chu            125

 in trapping micron-sized particles with a pair of opposing, focused beams of 
 laser light, as shown in Fig. 2. Confinement along the axial direction was due 
 to the scattering force: a displacement towards either of the focal points of 
 the light would result in an imbalance of scattered light that would push the 
 particle back to the center of the trap. Along the radial direction, the out- 
 wardly directed scattering force could be overcome by the attractive dipole 
 force. In the following years, other stable particle trapping geometries were 
 demonstrated by Ashkin,'6 and in 1978, he proposed the first three-dimen- 
 sional traps for atoms." In the same year, with John Bjorkholm and Richard 
 Freeman, he demonstrated the dipole force by focusing an atomic beam 
 using a focused laser bearn.18


      Focused laser beams



















                       Glass sphere
Figure 2. A schematic diagram of the first particle trap used by Ashkin. Confinement in the 
axial direction is due to an imbalance of the scattering forces between the left and right propa- 
gating beams. Confinement in the radial direction results from the induced dipole force which 
must overcome the outwardly directed scattering force.

Despite this progress, experimental work at Bell labs stopped a year later be- 
cause of two major obstacles. First, the trapping forces generated by intense 
focused laser beams are feeble. Atoms at room temperature would have an 
average energy i kir-imv2, orders of magnitude greater than could be con- 
fined by the proposed traps. A cold source of atoms with sufficiently high flux 
did not exist and a trap with large volume was needed to maximize the num- 
ber of atoms that could be trapped. Second, the relatively large-volume opti- 
cal trap made from opposing light beams was found to have serious heating 
problems. An atom could absorb a photon from one beam and be stimulated 
back to the initial state by a photon from the opposing beam. In this process, 
it would receive two photon impulses in the same direction. However, the 
same atom could have been excited and stimulated by the two beams in the 
reverse order, resulting in a net impulse in the other direction. Since the

 126                                                     Physics 1997

 order of absorption and stimulated emission is random, this process would in- 
 crease the random velocity of the atom and they would quickly heat and boil 
 out of the trap. This heating effect was rigorously calculated by Jim Gordon 
with Ashkin for a two-level atom.19

TAKING THE PLUNGE INTO THE COLD
My first idea to solve the trap loading problem was modest at best, but it got 
me to think seriously about trapping atoms. I proposed to make a cold 
source of atoms by depositing sodium atoms into a rare-gas matrix of neon." 
By heating the cryogenic surface supporting this matrix of atoms with a puls- 
ed laser, I thought it should be possible to "puff' the neon and sodium atoms 
into a vapor with a temperature of a few tens of Kelvin. Once a vapor, a 
reasonable fraction of the sodium would become isolated atoms and the puf- 
fed source would contain the full Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution of atoms, 
including the very slowest atoms. In a conventional atomic beam, the slowest 
atoms are knocked out of the way by faster moving atoms overtaking them. In 
a puffed source, the surface could be quickly heated and cooled so that 
there would be no fast atoms coming from behind. An added advantage was 
that the source would turn off quickly and completely so that the detection of 
even a few trapped atoms would be possible.
    Soon after my passage from interested bystander to participant, I realized 
that the route to trapping was through laser cooling with counter-propagating 
beams of light. If the laser beams were tuned below the atomic resonance, 
a moving atom would Doppler-shift the beam opposing its motion closer to 
resonance and shift the beam co-propagating with the motion away from 
resonance. Thus, after averaging over many impulses of momentum from 
both beams, the atom would experience a net force opposing its motion. In 
the limit where the atoms were moving slowly enough so that the difference 
in the absorption due to the Doppler effect was linearly proportional to the 
velocity, this force would result in viscous damping, F = -CM. This elegant idea 
was proposed by Hansch and Schawlow in 1975.21 A related cooling scheme 
was proposed by Wineland and Itano in the same year.22
    An estimate of the equilibrium temperature is obtained by equating the 
cooling rate in the absence of heating with the heating rate in the absence of 
cooling,
                                       dWheating/dt = dWcooling/dt =
The heating rate is due to the random kicks an atom receives by randomly 
scattering photons from counter-propagating beams that surround the 
atoms.23, 19 The momentum grows as a random walk in momentum space so 
the average random momentum p would increase as
                                               dt dt 2M 2M= dp2 - N(Pr)2 
where p is the momentum recoil due to each photon and Nis the number of

                 Steven Chu          127

photon kicks per second. By equating the heating rate to the cooling rate, 
one can calculate an equilibrium temperature as a function of the laser in- 
tensity, the linewidth of the transition, and the detuning of the laser from re- 
sonance. The minimum equilibrium temperature kBT.in = ii172, where F is 
the linewidth of the transition, was predicted to occur at low intensities and a 
detuning Av = t/2 where the Doppler shift asymmetry was a maximum. In 
the limit of low intensity, all of the laser beams would act independently and 
the heating complications that would result from stimulated transitions bet- 
ween opposing laser beams could be ignored.
 Not only would the light cool the atoms, it would also confine them. The 
laser cooling scheme was analogous to the Brownian motion of a dust particle 
immersed in water. The particle experiences a viscous drag force and the con- 
finement time in a region of space could be estimated based on another 
result in elementary physics: the mean square displacement (x2) after a time 
At described by a random walk, (x2) = 2Dt, where the diffusion constant is 
given by the Einstein relation D = kBT/a. For atoms moving with velocities v 
such that k-v<T, the force would act as a viscous damping force F = -ay. By sur- 
rounding the atoms with six beams propagating along the ± x, y and z direc- 
tions, we could construct a sea of photons that would act like an exceptional- 
ly viscous fluid: an "optical molasses".24 If the light intensity was kept low, the 
atoms would quickly cool to temperatures approaching Trnin. Once cooled, 
they would remain confined in a centimeter region of space for times as long 
as a fraction of a second.
 At this point, Leo and I shelved our plans to build the electron spectrome- 
ter and devoted our energies to making the optical molasses work. We rapid- 
ly constructed the puffing source of sodium needed to load the optical 
molasses. To simplify matters, we began with a pellet of sodium heated at 
room temperature. Rather than deal with the complications of a rare gas 
matrix, Leo and I decided to increase the number of cold atoms by slowing 
atoms from the puff source before attempting the optical molasses experi- 
ment. There were several early experiments that slowed atomic beams with 
laser light,25 but sodium atoms had to be slowed to velocities on the order of 
200-300 cm/sec (essentially stopped!) before an atom trap could be loaded. 
Two groups achieved this milestone in late 1984: a group at the National 
Bureau of Standards in Gaithersburg, Maryland, led by Bill Phillips using a 
tapered magnetic field26 and another NBS group in Boulder, Colorado, led 
by Jan Hall.27 We decided to copy the technique of Ertmer, et al.,27 and use an 
electro-optic generator to produce a frequency-shifted sideband. The fre- 
quency-shifted light is directed against the atoms coming off the sodium sur- 
face, and as the atoms slow down, the frequency is changed in order to keep 
the light in resonance with the Doppler shifting atoms.
 Leo was better at electronics than I and assumed the responsibility of the 
radio-frequency part of the project while I set out to build a wideband, trans- 
mission line electro-optic modulator. One of the advantages of working at 
Bell Laboratories was that one could often find a needed expert consultant 
within the Labs. Much of the electro-optic modulator development was

128              Physics 1997


pioneered at the Labs in Holmdel in the 1960s and we were still the leaders of 
the field in 1983. I learned about making electro-optic modulators by reading 
the book written by a colleague, Ivan Kaminow.28 I enlisted Larry Buhl to cut 
and polish the LiTaO3 crystal for the modulator. Rod Alferness taught me 
about microwave impedance matching and provided the SA launchers" 
needed to match Leo's electronics with my parallel-plate transmission line 
modulator. One month after we decided to precool the atoms with a fre- 
quency-swept laser beam, we had a functioning, wideband gigahertz electro- 
optic modulator and driver and could begin to precool the atoms from our 
puffing source.
 In the early spring of 1984, Leo and I started with a completely bare optical 
table, no vacuum chamber, and no modulator. Later that spring, John 
Bjorkholm, who had previously demonstrated the dipole force by focusing an 
atomic beam, joined our experiment. In the early summer, I recruited Alex 
Cable, a fresh graduate from Rutgers. Officially he was hired as my "techni- 
cian": unofficially, he became a super-graduate student. In less than one year, 
we submitted our optical molasses paper.29.3° The two papers reporting the 
stopping of atomic beams 26' 27 were published one month earlier.
 The apparatus we built to demonstrate optical molasses is shown in Figs. 3a 
and 3b. We had an ultra-high-vacuum chamber, but did not want to be ham- 
pered by long bake-out times to achieve good vacuum. Instead, we built a 
cryo-shield painted with Aquadag, a graphite-based substance. When cooled




























Figure 3 a. A photograph of the apparatus used to demonstrate optical molasses and the first op- 
tical trap for atoms. The photograph is a double exposure made by photographing the apparatus 
under normal lighting conditions and then photographing the laser beams by moving a white 
card along the beam path in a darkened room. The 143 Hz pulsed laser used to evaporate the so- 
dium pellet (doubled YAG at 582nra) appears as dots of light.

                    Steven Chu             129




























Figure 3 b. Art Ashkin and the author in front of the apparatus in 1986, shortly after the first op- 
tical trapping experiment was completed.

to liquid-nitrogen temperatures, the shield became a very effective sorption 
pump: we could open the vacuum chamber one day and be running by the 
next day. Fast turnaround time has always been important to me. Mistakes are 
unavoidable, so I wanted an apparatus that would allow mistakes to be cor- 
rected as rapidly as possible.
 The first signals of atoms confined in optical molasses showed confinement 
times of a few tens of milliseconds, but shortly afterwards we improved the 
storage time by over an order of magnitude. Surprisingly, it took us a week 
after achieving molasses to look inside the vacuum can with our eyes instead 
of with a photomultiplier tube. When we finally did, we were rewarded with 
the sight shown in Fig. 4.
 In this early work, the laser beams were aligned to be as closely counter- 
propagating as we could manage. A year later, we stumbled onto a misalign- 
ment configuration that produced another order of magnitude increase in 
the storage time. This so-called "super-molasses" alignment of our beams also 
created a compression of the atoms into a region of space on the order of 2 
mm diameter from an initial spread of 1 cm. We were never able to under- 
stand this phenomena and after a number of attempts, published a brief sum- 
mary of these results in conference proceedings.31
 In our first molasses work, we realized that the traditional method of meas- 
uring the temperature by measuring the Doppler broadening of an atomic 
resonance line would not work for the low temperatures we hoped to achieve. 
Instead we introduced a time-of-flight technique to directly measure the vel-

 130              Physics 1997






















Figure 4. A photograph of sodium atoms confined in optical molasses experiment. The atoms 
were pre-cooled by a counterpropagating laser before entering the region of six crossed laser 
beams.


ocity distribution of the atoms. After allowing the atoms in the molasses to 
come to equilibrium, we turned off the light for a variable amount of time. 
The fast atoms escaped ballistically during this time while the slower atoms 
were recaptured by the molasses. Our first measurements showed a tempera- 
ture of 185pK, slightly lower than the minimum temperature allowed by the 
theory of Doppler cooling. We then made the cardinal mistake of experi- 
mental physics: instead of listening to Nature, we were overly influenced by 
theoretical expectations. By including a fudge factor to account for the way 
atoms filled the molasses region, we were able to bring our measurement in- 
to accord with our expectations.


ON TO OPTICAL TRAPPING
Once we demonstrated optical molasses, we began to explore ways to achieve 
our original goal of optically trapping atoms. As a point of reference, Bill 
Phillips and his collaborators had reported the magnetic trapping of sodium 
atoms32 two weeks before our optical molasses paper came out. Although the 
1/e storage of the molasses confinement in our first experiment was a 
respectable T-0.36 sec, optical molasses does not provide a restoring force 
that would push the atoms to the center of the trap.
  Despite the fact that we were in possession of a great source of cold atoms, 
the path to trapping was not yet clear to us for a number of reasons: (i) 
Optical traps based strictly on the scattering force seemed to be ruled out 
because of a no-trapping theorem referred to as the "Optical Earnshaw 
Theorem". This theorem was published in response to earlier proposals to 
make atom traps based on the scattering force.33, 34 ( ii) We believed a trap

               Steven Chu        131

based on an opposing-beam geometry was not viable because of the severe 
stimulated heating effects. (iii) Finally, we ruled out a single focused laser 
beam because of the tiny trapping volume. We were wrong on all counts.
 Immediately after the molasses experiment, we tried to implement a large- 
volume ac light trap suggested by Ashkin.35 Our attempt failed, and after a 
few months, we began to cast around for other alternatives. One possibility 
was another type of ac trap we proposed at a conference talk in December of 
1984,36 but we wanted something simpler. Sometime in the winter of 1986, 
during one of our brainstorming sessions on what to do next, John Bjork- 
holm tried to resurrect the single focused beam trap first proposed in 
Ashkin's 1978 paper.17 I promptly rejected the idea because of the small 
trapping volume. A -1-watt laser focused to produce a -5-mK-deep trap would 
have a trapping volume of -1027cm3. Since the density of atoms in our optical  
molasses was 106 atoms/cm3, we would capture fewer than one atom in a trap 
surrounded by 106 atoms in molasses. A day or two after convincing the group 
that a trap based on a focused laser beam would not work, I realized that 
many more atoms would be captured by the trap than my original estimate. 
An atom close to the trap might not be immediately captured, but it would 
have • repeated opportunities to fall into the trap during its random walk in  
optical molasses.
 The trap worked. We could actually see the random walk loading with our 
own eyes. A tiny dot of light grew in brightness as more atoms fell into the 
trap. During the first days of trapping success, I ran up and down the halls,  
pulling people into our lab to share in the excitement. My director, Chuck 
Shank, showed polite enthusiasm, but I was not sure he actually picked out 
the signal from the reflections in the vacuum can windows and the surround- 
ing fluorescence. Art Ashkin came down with the flu shortly after our initial  
success. He confessed to me later that he began to have doubts: as he lay in 
bed with a fever; he wasn't sure whether the fever caused him to imagine we 
had a working trap.
 We tried to image the tiny speck of light onto an apertured photomultiplier 
tube, but the slightest misalignment would include too much light from the 
surrounding molasses. It was a frustrating experience not to be able to pro- 
duce a repeatable signal on a photomultiplier tube if we could actually see 
the atoms with our eyes. Then it dawned on me: if we could see the signal 
with our eyes, we could record it with a sensitive video camera and then ana-  
lyze the video tape! A local RCA representative, tickled by the experiment, 
loaned us a silicon-intensified video camera. Our trapping paper included a 
photo of our trapped atoms, the first color picture published in Physical 
Review Letters.37
 As we began the atom trapping, Art decided to trap micron-sized particles 
of glass in a single focused beam as a "proof of principle" for the atom trap. 
Instead of an atom in optical molasses, he substituted a silica (glass) sphere 
embedded in water. A micron-sized sphere is far more polarizable than an 
atom and Ashkin felt that it could be trapped at room temperature if the in- 
tensity gradient in the axial direction that would draw the glass bead

132            Physics 1997

into the focus of the light could overcome the scattering force pushing the 
particle out of the trap. This more macroscopic version of the optical tweez- 
ers trap was demonstrated quickly and gave us more confidence that the atom 
trap might work.38 At that time, none of us realized how this simple "toy ex- 
periment" was going to flower.
 Shortly after we demonstrated the optical trap, I hired Mara Prentiss as a 
new permanent staff member in my department. She began to work on the 
super-molasses riddle with us when I got a phone call from Dave Pritchard at 
MIT. He told me he and his student, Eric Raab, had been working on a scat- 
tering-force trap that would circumvent the Optical Earnshaw Theorem.33 
This theorem states that a scattering-force trap is impossible provided the 
scattering force Fscatt is proportional to the laser intensity I. The proof was 
straight forward: V.Fseatt = 0 since any region in empty space must have the 
net intensity flux inward equal to the flux outward. Thus there cannot be a re- 
gion in space where all force lines Fscatt point inward to a stable trapping 
point. Pritchard, Carl Wieman, and their colleagues had noted that the as- 
sumption FseattocI need not be true.39 They went on to suggest possible com- 
binations of external magnetic or electric fields that could be used to create 
a stable optical trap.
 Raab had had difficulties in getting a scattering-force trap to work at MIT 
and, as a last attempt before giving up, they asked if we were interested in col- 
laborating with them on this work. The basic idea is illustrated in Fig. 5 for 
the case of an atom with F = 1 in the ground state and F = 2 in the excited 
state, where F is the total angular momentum quantum number. A weak 
spherical quadrupole trap magnetic field would split the Zeeman sublevels of 
a multilevel atom illuminated by counterpropagating circularly polarized 
laser beams. Due to the slight Zeeman-shift, an atom to the right of the trap 
center optically pump predominantly into the mF = -1 state. Once in this 
state, the large difference in the scattering rates for light and a+ light 
causes the atom to experience a net scattering force towards the trap center. 
Atoms to the left of center would scatter more photons from the G+ beam. 
Since the laser beams remain tuned below all of the Zeeman split resonance 
lines, optical molasses cooling would still be occurring. The generalization to 
three dimensions is straightforward.
 All we needed to do, was insert a pair of modest magnetic-field coils into 
our apparatus to test this idea. I wound some refrigeration tubing for the 
magnetic-field coils, but had to tear myself away to honor a previous commit- 
ment to help set up a muonium spectroscopy experiment with Allan Mills, 
Ken Nagamine and collaborators.° A few days later, the molasses was running 
again, and I received a call at the muon facility in Japan from Alex, his voice 
trembling with excitement. The trap worked spectacularly well and the atom 
cloud was blindingly bright compared to our dipole trap. Instead of the meas- 
ly 1000 atoms we had in our first trap, they were getting 107 to 108 atoms.'
 The basic idea for the trap was due to Jean Dalibard, a protege of Claude 
Cohen-Tannoudji. His idea was stimulated by a talk given by Dave Pritchard 
on how the Earnshaw theorem could be circumvented. I called Jean in Paris

                     Steven Chu             133


         _3   -2  -1   0   +1 +2 mF=+3

          \a- ik
               40 

           60
                   12

             \it
              -2
                           +1 mF=+2


















Figure 5. The magneto-optic trap for atoms with an F = 2 ground state and a F = 3 excited state. 
The slight energy level shifts of the Zeeman sub-levels cause symmetry to be broken and the 
atoms to optically pump predominantly into either the in, = +2 or mi. = —2 state for B<0 or B>0. 
Once in the optically pumped states, the atoms are pushed towards the B = 0 region due to the 
large difference in relative strengths of the transition rates. The relative transition rates for a+ 
and cr- light for the m,= —2 and —1 states are shown.


to convince him that his name should go on the paper we were writing. Jean 
is both brilliant and modest, and felt it would be inappropriate to be a co-au- 
thor since he did not do any of the work.42
  The magneto-optic trap (commonly referred to as the MOT) immediately 
seized the attention of the 'growing community of coolers and trappers. Carl 
Wieman's group showed that atoms could be directly loaded from a tenuous 
vapor without the intermediate step of slowing an atomic beam.43 By increas- 
ing the size of the laser beams used in the trap, Kurt Gibble and I showed that 
as many as —4X 1010 atoms could be trapped.44 Wolfgang Ketterle, Pritchard, 
et a/.45 showed that the density of atoms in the MOT could be increased sig- 
nificantly by causing atoms to scatter less light in the central portion of the 
trap by blocking the repumping beam in that region of space. Stimulated by 
their shadowing idea, my collaborators and I at Stanford showed that by simp- 
ly turning off the repumping light at the end stage of molasses dramatically 
increases the density of low-temperature atoms in the MOT."

134              Physics 1997

























Figure 5 b. A photograph of atoms confined in a magneto-optic trap. The line of fluorescence 
below the ball of trapped atoms is due to the atomic beam used to load the trap.


  The invention and development of the MOT exemplifies how the field of 
laser cooling and trapping grew out of the combined ideas and cooperation 
of an international set of scientists. For this reason, I find it especially fitting 
that the magneto-optic trap is the starting point of most experiments using 
laser-cooled atoms.


OPTICAL MOLASSES REVISITED
In the winter of 1987, I decided to leave the "ivory tower" of Bell Labs and ac- 
cept an offer to become a professor at Stanford. When I left Bell Labs, we had 
just demonstrated the magneto-optic trap and it was clear the trap would pro- 
vide an ideal starting point for a number of experiments. I arrived at Stanford 
in the fall of 1987, not knowing how long it would take to build a new re- 
search team.47 Bill Phillips and Claude Cohen-Tannoudji were assembling 
powerful teams of scientists that could not be duplicated at Stanford. Dave 
Pritchard had been cultivating a powerful group at MIT Other "home run 
hitters" in atomic physics such as Carl Wieman and Main Aspect had just en- 
tered the field. Meanwhile, I had to start over again, writing proposals and 
meeting with prospective graduate students. If I had thought carefully about 
starting a new lab in the face of this competition, I might not have moved.
  As with many aspects of my career, I may not have made the smart move, 
but I made a lucky move. From 1988 to 1993, I entered into the most pro- 
ductive time in my scientific career to date. My first three graduate students 
were Mark Kasevich, Dave Weiss, and Mike Fee. I also had two post-dots, 
Yaakov Shevy and Erling Mils who joined my group my first year at Stanford.

                Steven Chu         135

By January of 1988, Dave and Yaakov had a magneto-optic trap going in the 
original chamber we used to demonstrate optical molasses and the dipole 
trap. The plan was to improve the optical trapping techniques and then use 
the new laser cooling and trapping technology to explore new physics that 
could be accessed with cold atoms.
 Another chamber was being assembled by Mark and Erling with the intent 
of studying the "quantum reflection" of atoms from cold surfaces. While I was 
at Bell Labs, Allan Mills and Phil Platzman began to get me interested in 
studying quantum reflection with ultracold atoms. The problem can be sim- 
ply posed as follows: consider an atom with a long de Broglie wavelength A in- 
cident on an idealized, short-range, attractive potential. In general there is a 
transmitted wave and reflected wave, but in the limit where 7L is much greater 
than the length scale of the potential, one gets the counterintuitive result that 
the probability of reflection goes to unity. A real surface potential has a 
power-law attraction of the form 1 /zn and has no length scale. An atom near 
a surface will experience an attractive van der Waals force with a 1 /z3 poten- 
tial and, further away, the attractive potential would become 1/z4 due to 
"retarded potential" effects first discussed by Casimir. There are also subtle- 
ties to the problem when inelastic scattering channels are included. This 
problem had attracted the attention of a considerable number of theorists 
and experimentalists.
 My plan of research was soon tossed out the window by a discovery that sent 
shock waves through the laser cooling community. By 1987, other groups 
began to produce optical molasses in their labs and measured atom tempera- 
tures near the expected limit,48' 49 but in the spring of 1988, Bill Phillips and 
co-workers reported that sodium atoms in optical molasses could be cooled to 
temperatures far below the limit predicted by theory.5° The NIST group re- 
ported the temperature of sodium atoms cooled in optical molasses to be 
43±20 pK and that the temperature did not follow the frequency dependence 
predicted by theory. The result was so surprising, they performed three dif- 
ferent time-of-flight methods to confirm their result. Within a few months, 
three separate groups led by Wieman, Cohen-Tannoudji, and myself verified 
that sodium and cesium atoms in optical molasses could be cooled well below 
the Doppler limit.
 As with many big "surprises", there were earlier hints that something was 
amiss. My group had been discussing the "super-molasses" problem at con- 
ferences since 1986. At a laser spectroscopy conference in Are, Sweden in 
1987, the NIST group reported molasses lifetimes with a very different fre- 
quency dependence from the one predicted by the simple formula (x2) = 
2DT/a2 that we published in our first molasses paper.51 This group also found 
that the trap was more stable to beam imbalance than had been expected. In 
our collective euphoria over cooling and trapping atoms, the research com- 
munity had not performed the basic tests to measure the properties of optical 
molasses, and I was the most guilty.
 At the end of June, 1988, Claude and I attended a conference on spin-po- 
larized quantum systems in Torino, Italy and gave a summary of the new sur-

136            Physics 1997

prises in laser cooling known at that time.52 After our talks, Claude and I had 
lunch and compared the findings in our labs. The theory that predicted the 
minimum temperature for two-level atoms was beyond reproach. We felt the 
lower temperatures must be due to the fact that the atoms we were playing 
with were real atoms with Zeeman sub-levels and hyperfine splittings. Our 
hunch was that the cooling mechanism probably had something to do with 
the Zeeman sub-level structure and not the hyperfine structure, since cesium 
 (Avhs = 9.19 GHz) and sodium (Avhs = 1.77 GHz) were both cooled to tem- 
peratures corresponding to an rms velocity on the order 4 to 5 times the re- 
coil velocity, vrecoil = tik/M and k = 21t/A,. By then we also knew that the mag- 
netic field had to be reduced to below 0.05 Gauss to achieve the best cooling.
 After the conference, Claude returned to Paris while I was scheduled to 
give several more talks in Europe. My next stop was Munich, where I told Ted 
Hansch that I thought it had to be an optical pumping effect. My knowledge 
of optical pumping was rudimentary, so I spent half a day in the local physics 
library reading about the subject. I was getting increasingly discouraged when 
I came across an article that referred to "Cohen-Tannoudji states". It was be- 
ginning to dawn on me that Claude and Jean were better positioned to figu- 
re out this puzzle.
 After Munich, I went to Pisa where I gave a talk about our positronium and 
muonium spectroscopy work.53' 54' 55 There, I finally realized how molasses 
was cooling the atoms. The idea was stimulated by a intuitive remark made by 
one of the speakers during his talk, "...the atomic polarization responds in 
the direction of the driving light field..." The comment reminded me of a 
ball-and-stick model of an atom as an electron (cloud) tethered by a weakly 
damped harmonic force to a heavy nucleus. I realized the cooling was due to 
a combination of optical pumping, light shifts, and the fact that the polariza- 
tion in optical molasses changed at different points in space. A linearly pola- 
rized laser field drives the atomic cloud up and down, while a circularly pola- 
rized field drives the cloud in a circle. In optical molasses, the x, y, and 
z-directed beams all have mutually perpendicular linear polarizations and the 
polarization of the light field varies from place to place. As a simple example, 
consider a one-dimensional case where two opposing light beams have mutu- 
ally perpendicular linear polarizations as shown in Fig. 6. The electron cloud 
wants to rotate with an elliptical helicity that is dependent on the atom's 
position in space.
 Another effect to consider is the ac Stark (light) shift. In the presence of 
light, the energy levels of an atom are shifted, and the amount of the shift is 
proportional to the coupling strength of the light. Suppose an atom with 
angular momentum F = 2 is in 0+ light tuned below resonance. It will optical- 
ly pump into the mF = +2 state and its internal energy in the field will be low- 
ered as shown in Fig. 6 c. If it then moves into a region in space where the 
light is a-, the transition probability is very weak and consequently the ac 
Stark shift is small. For sodium the mF = +2 energy is lowered 15 times more 
in a+ light than in a- light. Hence, the atom gains internal energy by moving 
into the region. This increase in internal energy must come at the expen-

