                                 427

"SYNTHETIC METALS": A NOVEL ROLE FOR 
ORGANIC POLYMERS

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000 
by
ALAN G. MACDIARMID
Department of Chemistry, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsyl- 
vania 19104-6323, USA.



INTRODUCTION
An organic polymer that possesses the electrical, electronic, magnetic, and 
optical properties of a metal while retaining the mechanical properties, pro-  
cessibility, etc. commonly associated with a conventional polymer, is termed 
an "intrinsically conducting polymer" (ICP) more commonly known as a "syn- 
thetic metal". Its properties are intrinsic to a "doped" form of the polymer.  
This class of polymer is completely different from "conducting polymers" 
which are merely a physical mixture of a nonconductive polymer with a con- 
ducting material such as a metal or carbon powder distributed throughout 
the material.


THE CONCEPT OF DOPING
Conjugated organic polymers are either electrical insulators or semiconduc- 
tors. Those that can have their conductivity increased by several orders of 
magnitude from the semiconductor regime are generally referred to as 'elec- 
tronic polymers' and have become of very great scientific and technological 
importance since 1990 because of their use in light emitting diodes'. Trans- 
(CH),, and the emeraldine base form of polyaniline are used in Figure 1 to il- 
lustrate the increases in electrical conductivity of many orders of magnitude  
which can be obtained by doping. The conductivity attainable by an elec- 
tronic polymer has very recently been increased an infinite number of times 
by the discovery of superconductivity in regioregular poly(3-hexylthio- 
phene) 2. Although this phenomenon was present only in a very thin layer of 
the polymer in a Field Effect (FET) configuration at a very low temperature 
(-2 K) it represents an historical quantum leap - superconductivity in an or-  
ganic polymer!
 Prior to the discovery of the novel protonic acid doping of polyaniline, dur- 
ing which the number of electrons associated with the polymer chain remain 
unchanged,3 the doping of all conducting polymers had previously been ac- 
complished by redox doping. This involves the partial addition (reduction)

428	
Chemistry 2000
Conductivity increases with increased doping
U)
2
SEMICONDUCTORS
INCREASING DOPING LEVELS
Ag, Cu  
Fe  
Mg
In, Sn 
Ge 
Si 
AgElr 
Glass
0 Diamond
Nylon
to
Quartz
Doped trans-(CH). 
[105 Stm]
Doped polyaniline 
[103 Skrn]
trans-(CH)x 
[10-5 S/cm]
Polyaniline 
[1040 S/cm]
Figure 1. Conductivity of Electronic Polymers
or removal (oxidation) of electrons to or from the pi system of the polymer  
backbone".
The concept of doping is the unique, central, underlying, and unifying  
theme which distinguishes conducting polymers from all other types of poly- 
mers?. During the doping process, an organic polymer, either an insulator or  
semiconductor having a small conductivity, typically in the range 10-10 to 10-5  
S/cm, is converted to a polymer which is in the 'metallic' conducting regime  
(-1 to 104 S/cm). The controlled addition of known, usually small 10 per  
cent) non-stoichiometric quantities of chemical species results in dramatic  
changes in the electronic, electrical, magnetic, optical, and structural prop- 
erties of the polymer. Doping is reversible to produce the original polymer  
with little or no degradation of the polymer backbone. Both doping and un- 
doping processes, involving dopant counterions which stabilize the doped  
state, may be carried out chemically or electrochemically6. Transitory doping  
by methods which introduce no dopant ions are also known8.
By controllably adjusting the doping level, a conductivity anywhere be- 
tween that of the non-doped (insulating or semiconducting) and that of the  
fully doped (highly conducting) form of the polymer can be easily obtained.  
Conducting blends of a (doped) conducting polymer with a conventional  
polymer (insulator), whose conductivity can be adjusted by varying the rela- 
tive proportions of each polymer, can be made9. This permits the optimiza- 
tion of the best properties of each type of polymer.

                     Alan G. MacDiarmid              429





 Since the initial discovery in 1977, that polyacetylene (CH)x, now com- 


monly known as the prototype conducting polymer, could be p- or n-doped, 


either chemically or electrochemically to the metallic state7,1", the develop- 


ment of the field of conducting polymers has continued to accelerate at an 


unexpectedly rapid rate and a variety of other conducting polymers and their 


derivatives have been discovered5'6. This rapid growth rate has been stimulat- 


ed by the field's fundamental synthetic novelty and importance to a cross-dis- 


ciplinary section of investigators - chemists, electrochemists, biochemists, ex- 


perimental and theoretical physicists, and electronic and electrical engineers 


and to important technological emerging applications of these materials.


 In the "doped" state, the backbone of a conducting polymer consists of a 


delocalized pi system. In the undoped state, the polymer may have a conju- 


gated backbone such as in trans-(CH)x which is retained in a modified form 


after doping, or it may have a non-conjugated backbone, as in polyaniline 


(leucoemeraldine base form), which becomes truly conjugated only after p- 


doping, or a non-conjugated structure as in the emeraldine base form of 


polyaniline which becomes conjugated only after protonic acid doping.






REDOX DOPING



All conducting polymers (and most of their derivatives), e.g. poly-(para-phe- 



nylene), +04. poly(phenylenevinylene), _Fara polypyrrole, -E-Q+ 





polythiophene, 4Q+ polyfuran, -01-- poly(heteroaromatic vinylenes) 





ki-,9-0„ (where Y=NH, NR, S and 0); polyaniline, -F0-,,dr ; etc., undergo



either p- and/or n-redox doping by chemical and/or electrochemical 


processes during which the number of electrons associated with the polymer 


backbone changes5'6. Selected examples of the different types of doping are 


presented below.


 Chemical and electrochemical p-doping P-doping, i.e. partial oxidation of the IT 


backbone of an organic polymer, was first discovered by treating trans-(CH). 


with an oxidizing agent such as iodine7, viz.,



          trans-[CH] + 1.5xy 12 --> [CH+Y(I3);]x (y 0.07)



This process was accompanied by an increase in conductivity from -10-5 S/cm 


to -103 S/cm. If the polymer is stretch-oriented five- to six-fold before doping, 


conductivities parallel to the direction of stretching up to -105 S/cm can be 


obtained 5'6.


 Approximately 85% of the positive charge is delocalized over 15 CH units 


(depicted below, for simplicity over only five units) to give a positive soliton, viz.,

                 H   H   H   H   C H H   H
                 I       1   I       I 
                     cI  c,c, 



              MI I li
              H    14  H   H   14  H   H


                           13

430            Chemistry 2000

 P-doping can also be accomplished by electrochemical anodic oxidation by 
immersing a trans-(CH), film in, e.g. a solution of LiC1O4 dissolved in propy- 
lene carbonate and attaching it to the positive terminal of a DC power source, 
the negative terminal being attached to an electrode also immersed in the so- 
lution“), viz.,
   trans-[CH]x+ (xy)(C104)- —> I(CH-F-Y(C104))1 x+ (xy) e- (y 5_ 0.1)
Chemical and electrochemical n-doping. Ndoping, i.e. partial reduction of the 
backbone pi system of an organic polymer, was also discovered using trans- 
(CH)x by treating it with a reducing agent such as liquid sodium amalgam or 
preferably sodium naphthalide7, viz.,
  trans-[CH]X+ (xy)Na+ (Nphth)- ---> [Nay' (CH)-Y]x + Nphth (y _5_ 0.1)
The antibonding TC* system is partially populated by this process which is ac- 
companied by an increase in conductivity of —103 S/cm.
 N-doping can also be carried out by electrochemical cathodic reduction)' 
by immersing a trans-(CH)x film in, e.g. a solution of LiC1O4, dissolved in 
tetrahydrofuran and attaching it to the negative terminal of a DC power 
source, the positive terminal being attached to an electrode also immersed in 
the solution, viz.,
     trans-[CH]x+ (xy)Li+ + ( xy) e- —> [Liy+ ( CH) -Y] x (y 5 0.1)
In all chemical and electrochemical p- and n-doping processes discovered for 
(CH)„ and for the analogous processes in other conducting polymers, 
counter 'clopant' ions are introduced which stabilize the charge on the poly- 
mer backbone. In each case, spectroscopic signatures, e.g. those of solitons, 
polarons, bipolarons, etc., are obtained characteristic of the given charged 
polymer. However, the doping phenomena concept extends considerably be- 
yond that given above to 'doping' processes where no counter dopant ion is 
involved, i.e. to doping processes in which transitory 'doped' species are pro- 
duced, which have similar spectroscopic signatures to polymers containing 
dopant ions. Such type of doping can provide information not obtainable by 
chemical or electrochemical doping. Examples of such types of redox doping 
which can be termed 'photo-doping' and 'charge-injection doping' are given 
below.

DOPING INVOLVING NO DOPANT IONS
Photo-doping. When trans-(CH)x for example, is exposed to radiation of ener- 
gy greater than its band gap, electrons are promoted across the gap and the 
polymer undergoes 'photo-doping'. Under appropriate experimental condi- 
tions, spectroscopic signatures characteristic of, for example, solitons can be 
observed12, viz.,

                                                 Alan G. MacDiarmid                                                         431

                                                         H          H                     H          H

                        trans-ICH)x             \C/V                            \ C
                                                    H         H           H          H         H

    The positive and negative solitons are here illustrated diagrammatically for 
simplicity as residing only on one CH unit; they are actually delocalized over 
-15 CH units. They disappear rapidly due to recombination of electrons and 
holes when irradiation is discontinued. If a potential is applied during irradi- 
ation, then the electrons and holes separate and photoconductivity is ob- 
served.
    Charge-injection doping. Charge-injection doping is most conveniently car- 
ried out using a metal/insulator/semiconductor (MIS) configuration involv- 
ing a metal and a conducting polymer separated by a thin layer of a high di- 
electric strength insulator. It was this approach, which resulted in the 
observance of superconductivity in a polythiophene derivative, as described 
previously. Application of an appropriate potential across the structure can 
give rise, for example, to a surface charge layer, the 'accumulation' layer 
which has been extensively investigated for conducting polymers"3. The re- 
sulting charges in the polymer, e.g. (CH). or poly(3-hexylthiophene), are 
present without any associated dopant ion. The spectroscopic properties of 
the charged species so formed can therefore be examined in the absence of 
dopant ion. Using this approach, spectroscopic studies of (CH). show the sig- 
natures characteristic of solitons and the mid-gap absorption band observed 
in the chemically and electrochemically doped polymer. However, coulombic 
interaction between charge on the chain and dopant ion is a very strong in- 
teraction and one that can totally alter the energetics of the system.

NON-REDOX DOPING
This type of doping differs from redox doping described above in that the 
number of electrons associated with the polymer backbone does not change 
during the doping process.
                                          N-          N+c _o\ / N                           HCI
                                                               ---0--rJ 1 -0-144               NH
                                                                        cr                    Cr
The energy levels are rearranged during doping. The emeraldine base form 
of polyaniline was the first example of the doping of an organic polymer to a 
highly conducting regime by a process of this type to produce an environ- 
mentally stable polysemiquinone radical cation. This was accomplished by 
treating emeraldine base with aqueous protonic acids and is accompanied by 
a nine to ten order of magnitude increase in conductivity (up to -3 S/cm) to 
produce the protonated emeraldine base14-16. Protonic acid doping has sub- 
sequently been extended to systems such as poly(heteroaromatic vinylenes)17.

432                   Chemistry 2000





THE POLYANILINES



The polyanilines refer to a very important class of electronic/conducting poly- 

mers. They can be considered as being derived from a polymer, the base form



of which has the generalized composition: N     NN 




and which consists of alternating reduced,    and oxidized,



-0-0--       repeat units3,14'16. The average oxidation state can be


varied continuously from y = 1 to give the completely reduced polymer,

     H          H
     N    N     N       to y = 0.5 to give the 'half-oxidized' polymer,



      H    H
      N    N               to 0 to give the completely oxidized
                           ■



polymer,                    _N+ . The terms leucoemeraldine',





`emeraldine', and 'pernigraniline' refer to the different oxidation states of 


the polymer where y = 1, 0.5, and 0, respectively, either in the base form, e.g. 

emeraldine base, or in the protonated salt form, e.g. emeraldine hydrochlo- 


ridC3'14'15. In principle, the imine nitrogen atoms can be protonated in whole 

or in part to give the corresponding salts, the degree of protonation of the 

polymeric base depending on its oxidation state and on the pH of the aque- 

ous acid. Complete protonation of the imine nitrogen atoms in emeraldine 

base by aqueous HC1, for example, results in the formation of a delocalized 

polysemiquinone radical cation3'15'18 and is accompanied by an increase in 

conductivity of -1010.

  The partly protonated emeraldine hydrochloride salt can be synthesized 

easily either by the chemical or electrochemical oxidative polymerization of 


aniline3,14'15. It can be deprotonated by aqueous ammonium hydroxide to 

give emeraldine base powder (a semiconductor).






ALLOWED OXIDATION STATES



As can be seen from the generalized formula of polyaniline base,



      N    N           N Y   the polymer could, in principle, exist


in a continuum of oxidation states ranging from the completely reduced ma- 

terial in the leucoemeraldine oxidation state, y = 1 to the completely oxidized 

material in the pernigraniline oxidation state, y = 0. However, we have 


shown16 that at least in N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone (NMP) solution in the 

range y = 0 to y = 0.5 (emeraldine oxidation state) only two chromophores 

are present, characteristic of y = 1 and y = 0.5 species and that all intermediate 

oxidation states consist, at the molecular level, only of mixtures of the chro- 

mophores characteristic of these two states.

  Since most of the properties of polyaniline of interest are concerned with 


the solid state, we have carried out a series of studies in the solid state which

                  Alan G. MacDiarmid         433


show that the same phenomenon is true in the y = 1 to y = 0. 5 oxidation state 
range and in the y = 0. 5 to y = 0 oxidation state range. Within each of these 
ranges all intermediate oxidation states consist, at the molecular level, only of 
mixtures of the chromophores characteristic of the two states defining the be- 
ginning and end of each range19,2°.


DOPING

Polyaniline holds a special position amongst conducting polymers in that its 
most highly conducting doped form can be reached by two completely dif- 
ferent processes — protonic acid doping and oxidative doping. Protonic acid 
doping of emeraldine base units with, for example 1M aqueous HC1 results in 
complete protonation of the imine nitrogen atoms to give the fully protonat- 
ed emeraldine hydrochloride salt14'15:
 As shown in Figure 2, protonation is accompanied by a 9 to 10 order of 
magnitude increase in conductivity reaching a maximum in —1 M aqueous 
HC1.

       103


       101


       1O-1













                      S
      10-11
         10 6.0 5.0 4.0 3,0 2.0- 1.0 0:0 0

              Equilibtrturn pH of Aqueous HO
Figure 2. Conductivity of emeraldine base as a function of pH of HC1 dopant solution as it un- 
dergoes protonic acid doping (• and ■ represent two independent series of experiments) 14'15.


 The same doped polymer can be obtained by chemical oxidation (p-dop- 
ing) of leucoemeraldine base'. This actually involves the oxidation of the u/n 
system rather than just the t system of the polymer as is usually the case in p- 
type doping. Its reaction with a solution of chlorine in carbon tetrachloride 
proceeds to give emeraldine hydrochloride:

434                                                                                                       Chemistry 2000




                                                                                                                             114 --(1)-41H
                                                                                                                                                       cc                                                 Cc

NANOELECTRONICS
The basic purpose of this research is to blend the now well-established field of 
elecronic/conducting polymers with the new, emerging field of nanoscience, 
by electrostatic fabrication ("electrospinning") to produce "nanoelectronics" 
— electronic junctions and devices significantly smaller than the diameter of a 
human hair (50,000 nm). It is commonly accepted that a nanomaterial is de- 
fined as one consisting of a substance or structure which exhibits at least one 
dimension of less than 100 nm (0.1 pm)21.
        Our objectives were: (i) to develop a method by which nanofibers (diame- 
ter < 100 nm) of organic polymers could be controllably and reproducibly 
fabricated such that in one given preparation, all fibers would have a diame- 
ter < 100 nm and (ii) to reproducibly and controllably fabricate, for the first 
time, nanofibers of electronic polymers (in their semiconducting and metal- 
lic regimes) and/or their blends in conventional organic polymers for the pur- 
pose of ascertaining their applicability in the fabrication of nanoelectronic 
devices.
        We have made substantial progress in achieving these objectives by using a 
relatively little known, simple, convenient and inexpensive "electrospinning" 
method22-27. We have previously reported" fabrication of the first conducting 
polymer fibers (diameter —950 nm to 2,100 nm) of polyaniline doped with d,1 
camphorsulfonic acid (PAn.HCSA) as a blend in polyethylene oxide (PEO). 
We were surprised to find that an electronic polymer, such as polyaniline, 
which might have been expected to be more susceptible to degradation than 
most conventional organic polymers, survived, without observable chemical 
or physical change, following the 25,000 V electrospinning fabrication 
process in air at room temperature.
        Electrospinning. The electrospinning technique involves a simple, rapid, in- 
expensive, electrostatic, non-mechanical method in which a polymer solution 
in a variety of different possible common solvents, including water, is placed 
in a hypodermic syringe or in a glass pipette, at a fixed distance (5-30 cm) 
from a metal cathode24. The positive (anode) terminal of a variable high volt- 
age transformer is attached to the metal tip of the hypodermic syringe or to a 
wire inserted into the polymer solution in the glass pipette, the negative ter- 
minal being attached to the metal cathode. The tip of the syringe can be 
placed vertically over the cathode or at any other convenient angle to it. 
When the voltage applied between the anode and cathode reaches a critical 
value, —14,000 V at a —20 cm separation, the charge overcomes the surface 
tension of the deformed drop of the polymer solution on the tip of the sy- 
ringe and a jet is produced. Since the polymer molecules all bear the same

              Alan G. MacDiarmid     435


(positive) charge, they repel each other while traveling in air during a few 
milliseconds from the anode to cathode and become separated25. At the same 
time, evaporation of the solvent molecules occurs rapidly. Evaporation of sol- 
vent is also enhanced because the similarly-charged (positive) solvent mole- 
cules repel each other. Under appropriate conditions, dry, meters-long fibers 
accumulate on the surface of the cathode resulting in a non-woven mesh of 
nano- to micron diameter fibers depending on experimental parameters 
(Figure 3).

























Figure 3. 50 wt% Nanofiber blend of PAn.HCSA fabricated from 2 wt% PAn.HCSA and 2 wt% 
PEO from chloroform solution at 25,000 V (anode/cathode separation, 25 cm). Scale bar: 
100,000 nm.
 Nanofiber Fabrication. Since the submicron fibers (500-1,600 nm) obtained 
in our initial work23 were not classifiable as true "nanofibers," our immediate 
objective was to break the "nanotechnology barrier" and to consistently and 
reproducibly fabricate true nanofibers (diameter <100 nm) of an organic 
polymer. This was accomplished (see Figure. 4) using an 8 wt% solution of 
polystyrene (Mw 212,400) in tetrahydrofuran at a potential of 20,000 V be- 
tween the anode and cathode which were separated by 30 cm. The fibers were 
collected as a mat on an aluminum target and were found to have diameter 
characteristics: average, 43.1 nm; maximum, 55.0 nm; minimum, 26.9 nm. 
Other studies involving polystyrene gave fibers whose diameters were consi- 
stently < 100 nm; average, 30.5 nm; maximum, 44.8 nm; minimum, 16.0 nm. 
It might also be noted that the above 16 nm fiber is only -30 polystyrene mo- 
lecules wide. It is also of interest to note that a 16 nm fiber such as the one 
mentioned above lies well within the - 4-30 nm diameter range of multi- 
walled carbon nanotubes26.
 Electronic Polymer Fibers. By using a previously observed method for produc- 
ing polyaniline fibers27 we have prepared highly-conducting sulfuric acid-

436              Chemistry 2000
























Figure 4. Electrospun fibers of polystyrene (see text). Scale bar: 1000 nm. The extended length 
of the fibers is clearly visible.

doped polyaniline fibers (diameters: average, 139 nm; maximum, 275 nm; 
minimum, 96nm) by placing a — 20 wt% solution of polyaniline in 98% sulfu- 
ric acid in a glass pipette with the tip — 3 cm above the surface of a copper 
cathode immersed in pure water at 5,000 V potential difference. The fibers 
collect in or on the surface of the water. The conductivity of a single fiber was 
— 0.1 S/cm, as expected since partial fiber de-doping occurred in the water 
cathode. The diameter and length of the fibers appear (Figure 5) to be sen-
























Figure 5. 100% polyaniline fiber with an average diameter of 139 nm.

                 Alan. G. MacDiarmid       437


sitive to the nature of the polyaniline used. No great difficulty is foreseen in 
producing fibers < 100 nm diameter.
  It is relatively easy to prepare conducting blends of PAn.HCSA in a variety 
of different conventional polymers such as polyethylene oxide, polystyrene, 
polyacrylonitrile, etc. For example, - 20 wt% blends of PAn.HCSA in poly- 
styrene (Mw 114,200) are obtained by electrospinning a chloroform solution; 
fiber diameter characteristics: average, 85.8 nm; maximum, 100.0 nm; mini- 
mum 72.0 nm. These fibers are sufficiently electrically conductive that their 
SEMs may be recorded without the necessity of applying a gold coating.
  Separate, individual nanofibers can be collected and examined if so de- 
sired. An appropriate substrate - glass slide, silicon wafer or loop of copper 
wire, etc. - is held between the anode and cathode at a position close to the 
cathode for a few seconds to collect individual fibers (see Figure 6).

























Figure 6. Polystyrene fibers collected on a bent copper wire (magnification 33x) and subse- 
quently coated with a thin layer of polypyrrole by in situ deposition from aqueous solution. Scale 
bar: 1 mm.


  Current/voltage (I/V) curves are given in Figure 7 for a single 419 nm 
diameter fiber (Fiber 1) and for a -600nm diameter fiber (Fiber 2) of a blend 
of 50 wt% PAn.HCSA and polyethylene oxide collected on a silicon wafer 
coated with a thin layer of SiO2. Two gold electrodes separated by 60.3 inn are 
deposited on the fiber after its deposition on the substrate.
  Nanofibers as Substrates. The large surface to volume ratio offered by 
nanofibers makes them excellent, potentially useful substrates for the fabri- 
cation of coaxial nanofibers consisting of superimposed layers of different 
materials. Catalysts and electronically active materials can be deposited on 
them by chemical, electrochemical, solvent, chemical vapor, or other means, 
for use in nanoelectronic junctions and devices.

438              Chemistry 2000






















       -10     -5      0       5       10
                    Voltage (V)
Figure 7. Current/voltage curves of 50 wt% PAn.HCSA/PEO blend nanofiber.


 We have found, for example, that polyacrylonitrile nanofibers can be easi- 
ly and evenly coated with a 20-25 nm layer of conducting polypyrrole (Figure 
8) by immersion in an aqueous solution of polymerizing polypyrrole28. 
Analogously, we have found that electroless deposition of metals can also be 
performed. Polyacrylonitrile fibers, for example, can be evenly coated with 
gold by electroless deposition29.
 Carbon Nanofibers. As previously reported" polyacrylonitrile fibers may be



























Figure 8. SEM of conducting polypyrrole coated polyacrylonitrile nanofibers. Scale bar: 1000 nm

              Alan G. MacDiarmid   439

thermally converted to carbon nanofibers with some shrinkage. We have sim- 
ilarly converted polyacrylonitrile nanofibers to carbon nanofibers.
 In summary, electronic polymers have been used for the past 20 years to 
produce rectifying diodes by Schottky and p/n junctions, transistors, light- 
emitting devices, photovoltaic cells, rechargeable batteries, etcl. Now, the 
ability to fabricate nanofibers of electronic polymers which are only a few 
molecules thick suggests the emergence of a field of nanoelectronics whereby 
the electronic properties of such nanofibers can be exploited for technologi- 
cal purposes.

LINE PATTERNING OF CONDUCTING POLYMERS3°
One of the exciting challenges of the first part of this century will be the de- 
velopment of low-cost disposable plastic/paper electronic devices31-33. Con- 
ventional inorganic conductors, such as metals, and semiconductors, such as 
silicon, commonly require multiple etching and lithographic steps in fabri- 
cating them for use in electronic devices. The number of processing steps 
and chemical etching steps involved limit the minimum price and therefore 
their applicability in disposable electronics. On the other hand, conducting 
polymers combine many advantages of plastics, e.g. flexibility and processing 
from solution, with the additional advantage of conductivity either in the 
metallic or semiconducting regimes; however, the lack of simple methods to 
obtain inexpensive conductive polymer shapes/patterns limit many applica- 
tions. We here describe a novel, simple and cheap method to prepare pat- 
terns of conducting polymers by a process which we term, "Line Patterning".
 Line Patterning uses the difference in selected physical and/or chemical 
properties between a substrate and insulating lines which have been printed 
on it by a conventional copying or printing process towards a fluid (or vapor) 
to which they are both simultaneously exposed. The substrate and printed 
lines react differently or at different rates with the fluid (or vapor) to which 
they have been exposed. This results in a non-uniform deposition on the sub- 
strate as compared to the printed lines. If the fluid contains a conducting 
polymer, which remains as a film after evaporation of the solvent, a pattern of 
conducting polymer results. A pattern is first designed on a computer and is 
then printed on, for example, an overhead transparency using a standard, 
non-modified office laser printer.
 The printed (insulating) lines can be easily removed, if necessary, in a few 
seconds by ultrasonic treatment in toluene, dissolving the printed lines and 
leaving a clean pattern of deposited material on the substrate whose shape 
was originally defined by the now non-existent printed lines. Line Patterning 
has the following advantages: no photolithography is involved; no printing of 
conducting polymer is involved; it uses only, e.g., a standard office laser print- 
er, which is not modified in any way; commercially available flexible, trans- 
parent plastic or paper substrates can be used; solutions of commercially 
available conducting or non-conducting polymers can be used from which 
the polymers may be deposited on sustrates; it is inexpensive; rapid develop-

440                        Chemistry 2000

ment of customized patterns (within hours) from a computer designed pat- 
tern to product is routine.
  We have exploited, for example, the observation that a commercial disper- 
sion of poly-3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene (PEDOT, "Baytron P", Bayer Corp.) 
wets commercial plastic overhead transparency, but not the lines printed on it 
by a standard office laser printer. A coating of PEDOT can be applied by a 
roller and after evaporation of the solvent; the printed lines can be easily and 
cleanly removed by sonication, leaving only the conducting polymer on the 
transparency.
  Two electrodes were prepared in this way, each containing 25 lines/inch. A 
drop of a standard commercial Polymer Dispersed Liquid Crystal Display 
 (PDLC)34 mixture containing an optical adhesive and 15 i_tm spacer spheres 
was placed on the center of each electrode. The second electrode was placed 
on top at an angle of 90° to the first. This resulted in a (25 x 25), i.e. 625 pix- 
els/sq. inch matrix. [Figure 9] Exposure to U/V light for a few minutes re- 
sulted in polymerization of the mixture to bind the two electrodes together 
and to produce a free-standing working PDLC liquid crystal display device. 
When an electrode pattern of 100 lines/inch was used a working 10,000 pix- 
el/sq. inch display was produced.



                        Remove toner linesOP'



Figure 9. 625 pixel PDLC Liquid Crystal Display.

  We have devised a novel way of separating conducting polymer circuits 
from each other by making use of the height (-4-5 1.tm) of the printed toner 
lines, using a standard office printer, above the substrate e.g. on an overhead 
transparency. This is illustrated [Figure 10 and 11] by a "push button" switch 
to open and close a simple electrical circuit. A combination of two patterned 
transparencies where the two adjacent conductive areas are electrically sepa- 
rated from each other by two -4-5 .tm non-conductive printed toner lines is 
obtained by placing the printed lines on top of each other as shown in 
Figures 11 and 12. Depression of the areas labeled "PRESS" causes the upper 
transparency to bend. This electrically connects the conducting PEDOT sur- 
faces. When released, the transparency film returns back to its original posi- 
tion, thus breaking the electrical circuit.
  The two-dimensional conducting polymer circuits may be readily convert- 
ed to three-dimensional circuits by two different methods as shown in Figure 
12 simply by (i) stapling two two-dimensional circuits together using a com- 
mon office desk stapler. The metal staple joins together electrically the con-

                           Alan G. MacDiarmid                     441




               PRESS                              PRESS







transparency



                                                             12:11
                                                              uniform
         Press: transparency bends Printed line "spacer"      PEDOT film
         and brings PEDOT          prevents contact of PEDOT
         surfaces into contact     surfaces




                          represents (2 x 4.5 pm = — 9 pm "spacer" 
                          between the two conducting PEDOT surfaces.

Figure 10. A Simple Electronic Circuit ("push button" switch).













































Figure 11. "Push button" switch.














                                         PEDOT      hol e











      Connection with staple             Connection via coated hole

Figure 12. Three-Dimensional Connections.

