                                        453

THE DISCOVERY OF POLYACETYLENE FILM: 
THE DAWNING OF AN ERA OF CONDUCTING 
POLYMERS

Nobel Lecture, December 8,2000
by
HIDEKI SHIRAKAWA
Emeritus Professor, University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8577, Japan.


This lecture is not directly related to our discovery and development of con- 
ducting polymers to which the Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2000 was awarded. 
However, I would like to present my previous work that I had carried out just 
before we reached the discovery of chemical doping. I do hope my talk will be 
of use for you, the audience, to deepen your understandings by learning what 
had happened before and how we did reach the idea of the chemical doping.

I. PROLOGUE
It has been recognized for many years that a very long linear conjugated 
polyene might have various interesting properties, especially optical, electri- 
cal and magnetic properties. The definition of the polyene is that an even 
number of methyne (=CH—) groups is covalently bonded to form a linear 
carbon chain bearing one rc-electron on each carbon atom. Therefore, 
the chemical structure of the polyene is best represented by a formula 
H(CH=CH)nH, where n denotes the number of repeating units. Recently 
polyacetylene has become a more popular name instead of polyene because 
polyacetylene synthesized by the polymerization of acetylene has been used 
extensively as specimens for various studies.
 Pople and Walmsley described in their article in 1962 [1] that "Although it is 
not possible to synthesize very long polyenes (polyacetylene) at present, general interest in 
conjugated polymers with related, but rather more complex, structures makes a full study 
of the electronic states of this simple polymer worthwhile." Although the first poly- 
merization of acetylene was reported in no later than 1958 by Natta and his 
co-workers [2] who prepared polyacetylene that is structurally identical to the 
very long conjugated polyene, the work was not accepted widely in the field. 
Before that time the interests in this compound were limited to theoretical 
approaches to explain to chemists a red-shift of the absorption maximum 
(bathochromic effect) and an increase in the absorption coefficient (hyper- 
chromic effect) with increasing the number of repeating units in the conju- 
gation, and to elucidate for physicists bond alternation in connection with an 
electron-phonon interaction. An accumulation of experimental observations 
on relatively short polyenes [3-8] coupled with theoretical considerations,

454              Chemistry 2000


such as the free-electron model and simple Heckel molecular orbital treat- 
ments, strongly suggested that a difference between the lengths of double 
and single bonds decreases with increasing the conjugation and that all the 
bonds tend to be equal their length in an infinitely long polyene. In other 
words, one would expect that the infinitely long one-dimensional arrange- 
ment of it-electrons forms a half-filled band, or that the highest occupied 
(HO) and the lowest unoccupied (LU) 7c-electron bands merge with each 
other, leading to metallic behavior [9, 10]. In the 1950s, however, it became 
theoretically clear that the polyene with bond alternation is energetically 
more stable than that with bonds of equal length [1, 11-13]. Since two geo- 
metrical isomers, trans and cis, are possible for each double bond, two iso- 
meric forms, all-trans and all-cis, are expected as the two extremes of poly- 
acetylene isomers as shown in Scheme 1. Experimentally the carbon-carbon 
bond lengths in polyacetylene were directly measured by Yannoni and Clarke 
[14] with use of the nutation NMR spectroscopy, 1.36 and 1.44 A for the 
double and single bonds, respectively, in the trans form and 1.37 A for the 
double bond in the cis form.


    H H H H H H HHHHH , H
    I                                j


        1I                  1!I
                    (1)


  H HH HH HH            HH HH HH H 
   \C=C( \C=C( \C =C \CC C=C \C      \C =CI
      \C=C(       C    \C-( \C=C(  \C
   \H 111 \H  \H d     Hi `H H/ \H   \11
                    (2)

Scheme 1. All-trans (1) and all-cis (2) polyacetylene.



 Even after the first synthesis by Natta and co-workers [2], polyacetylene re- 
mained for some time a material of interest to only a few organic [15, 16] and 
polymer chemists [17-19] because the product was obtained as insoluble and 
infusible powders.



II. TRANS OR CIS?

Among few chemists, S. Ikeda and his co-workers had been studying a mecha- 
nism of acetylene polymerization in connection with olefin polymerization by 
various Ziegler-Natta catalysts. They found that the polymerization yields not 
only highly polymerized polyacetylene but also benzene, that is, a cyclic 
trimer of acetylene, and that the ratio of these two products depends upon 
the species of Ziegler-Natta catalysts used. They also found the formation of 
alkylbenzenes as a minor by-product of the acetylene polymerization with a

                Hideki Shirakawa     455

catalyst system composed of titanium tetrachloride and trialkylaluminum. In 
a series of experiments using carbon-14 and deuterium, they noted that a la- 
beled ethyl group is introduced in the ethylbenzene when triethylaluminum 
labeled with carbon-14 or deuterium is used as the co-catalyst [20]. In an- 
other experiments on the oxidation of polyacetylene by alkaline potassium 
permanganate, they observed the formation of propionic and acetic acids 
that are derived from the alkyl groups in the trialkylaluminum used as the co- 
catalyst [20]. From these results, they concluded that polyacetylene and ben- 
zene could be formed from the same active site of the catalyst system. Thus, 
the reaction proceeds by cis-opening of the triple bond in acetylene followed 
by a cis insertion into titanium-alkyl bond of the catalyst. This mechanism fits 
the orbital interaction consideration by Fukui and Inagaki [21], for the role 
of the catalyst according to which the initially formed configuration of the 
double bond is cis as a result of favored orbital interaction between the in- 
serting acetylene and the active site of the catalyst. Whether cyclic trimeriza- 
tion occurs to give benzene or polymerization proceeds to give polyacetylene 
is determined by the conformation of the growing chain that takes either 
cisoid or transoid structure in the vicinity of the active site of the catalyst [22]. 
As no cis form had been known until then, an important question remained: 
why is the mechanism capable of yielding only [9] trans configuration of the 
double bonds in polyacetylene? [2, 19].

III. DISCOVERY OF FILM SYNTHESIS
The conventional method of polymerization in the laboratory is such that the 
catalyst solution is stirred thoroughly by any means to carry out the reaction 
under a homogeneous condition. The acetylene polymerization has not been 
an exception. It was customary for polymer chemists who synthesized poly- 
acetylene to bubble acetylene gas into a catalyst solution with stirring. 
Unfortunately, the product was obtained as an intractable black powder from 
which it is very difficult to make into samples of a shape suitable for mea- 
surement of spectra and physical properties because of its insolubility and in- 
fusibility.
  Soon after I joined Ikeda's group, we succeeded in synthesizing polyacety- 
lene directly in the form of a thin film [23] by a fortuitous error in 1967. 
After a series of experiments to reproduce the error, we noticed that we had 
used a concentration of the Ziegler-Natta catalyst nearly a thousand times 
greater than that usually used. It is worth noting that the insolubility of poly- 
acetylene contributes to the formation of film. In addition, it was found that 
the film is composed of entangled micro-fibers called fibrils by a transmission 
electron microscope observation of an extremely thin film and by scanning 
electron microscope observation on a surface of a thick film as shown in 
Figure 1. The fibril diameter is in the range of 20-100 nm depending upon 
the polymerization conditions. These inherent properties of polyacetylene 
are absolutely necessary for the film formation even under the higher con- 
centration of the catalyst. One more important factor that should be added is

      456             Chemistry 2000
















      Figure la. Transmission electron micrograph of an extremely thin film of polyacetylene.
.
      that the catalyst used at that time, Ti(0-n-C4H9)4-(C2H5)3A1, was quite unique 
      from the viewpoint of its good solubility in organic solvents such as hexane or 
      toluene to give a homogeneous solution and its high activity to give exclu- 
      sively high molecular weight and crystalline polymers. On the contrary, most























      Figure lb. Scanning electron micrograph of the surface of a thick polyacetylene film.

               Hideki Shirakawa    457

of Ziegler-Natta catalysts form precipitates to give inhomogeneous solutions 
when a titanium compound is mixed with alkylaluminum.
 The use of the films enabled us to obtain clear infrared spectra as shown in 
Figure 2 [24] and analysis of these spectra indicated that the configuration of 
the double bonds strongly depends on the temperature of polymerization. 
The trans contents of polyacetylene prepared by the Ziegler-Natta catalysts de- 
creases with decreasing the polymerization temperature as shown in Table I. 
A thermal study [25] indicated that the irreversible isomerization of the cis 
form occurs at temperatures higher than 145 °C to give the trans one. Thus 
the cis form is thermodynamically less stable than the trans one. The observed 
cis-rich polyacetylene synthesized at lower temperatures suggested the cis- 
opening of the triple bond of the acetylene monomer consistent with the cis- 
opening mechanism proposed by Ikeda [22]. In case of the polymerization 
being carried out at higher temperatures, spontaneous isomerization of the 
growing cis double bonds occurs to give trans ones. The cis-opening mecha- 
nism has been supported by the mutation NMR study [14] and by the in- 
frared study of copolymers of acetylene and acetylene-d2 [24]. In conclusion, 
the open problem why only trans polyacetylene had been known was solved by 
the use of films.

Table I. The trans contents of polyacetylene prepared at different temperatures
Temperature (°C)   Trans content (%)
   150               100.0
   100               92.5
    50               67.6
    18               40.7
    0                21.4
   —18                4.6
   —78                1.9
Catalyst: Ti(0-n-C4F19)4-(C2H5)3A1, Ti/A1 = 4, [Ti] = 10 mmo1/1.



IV ELECTRICAL PROPERTIES OF AS-PREPARED 
POLYACETYLENE FILMS
The electrical resistivity of as-prepared films with various cis/trans contents 
was measured by the conventional two-probe method under vacuum in a tem- 
perature range of —120 to 20 °C [26]. The resistivity and energy gap of trans- 
rich polyacetylene were 1.0 x 104 c2cm and 0.56 eV, respectively, whereas the 
values of a cis-rich (80 %) one were 2.4 x 108 c/cm and 0.93 eV, respectively. 
Hatano and co-workers [17] reported that the resistivity and energy gap mea- 
sured on compressed pellets of powder polyacetylene synthesized by the same 
catalyst system are in the range of 1.4 x 104 and 4.2 x 105 Ocm, and 0.46 eV, 
respectively, in good agreement with those for trans-rich polyacetylene film. 
In conclusion, it became apparent that the intrinsic electrical properties do 
not change very much between powder and film.

 458                                                   Chemistry 2000






                            ao

                            60 

                            40 

                            20 F-                                     1
                              0 I r

                            100

                       o    80 --
                       c
                            60

                            ao

                            20
                       as
                              0
                           100  r      _    r-                                   -7-      f   T            I-  1
                            80 

                            60 

                            40 -

                            20
                              0'                L            L        3           I   I                L   1   i
                              4000 3000       2000     1800 1600        1400 1200       1000 800         600 400
                                                          Wavenumber (cm-1)



Figure 2. Infrared spectra of polyacetylene synthesized at (1) —78 °C, (2) 20 °C, and (3) 150 °C. 

After reference 24, Figure 4.








V. HALOGENATION OF THE POLYACETYLENE FILMS



Since no improvement in electrical conductivity was observed in a form of 

film, we tried to use the polyacetylene films as a source of graphite films as the 


carbon content of the polymer is as high as 92.3 %. Thermograms of dif- 

ferential thermal analysis of cis-rich polymer revealed the existence of two 

exothermic peaks at 145 and 325 °C and one endothermic peak at 420 °C, 


which were assigned to cis-trans isomerization, hydrogen migration accompa- 

nied with crosslinking reaction, and thermal decomposition, respectively 


[25], as shown in Scheme 2. Thermogravimetric analysis showed that weight





                                                                   H        HH            HH            HH            H

                                                                     'C=C          C=C           C=C           C=C

                                                                                          \C=C \C=Ci                  C=C
                                                                                                       /
                                                                          H        H H           H H           H H \ H
                          - 78 °C


                                                                                                 Thermal Isomerization
H—CEC—H                     T1(0-n-Bu)4 - Et3A1                                                          (145 °C)




                           150 °C                                       H H H H                         HH               HH


                                                                      .C• ,CC„CC„C                                -.0
                                                                    C'              C'              C' C'
                                                                     I      I       I        I      I        I        I       I
                                                                    H H H H                         H H              HH




                                                                                           A -300 - 330 °C




      C1 - C8 Hydrocarbons 60% Thermal Decomposition                               Crosslinked Brown Polymer
      Brown Oily Paste             40%                > 420 °C              (No longer conjugated double bonds)


Scheme 2. Thermal characteristics of polyacetylene.

                               Hideki Shirakawa                         459




loss reached 63 % at 420 °C. Therefore, pyrolysis of as-prepared polyacetylene 

films is not suitable for the preparation of graphite films.

  Electrophilic addition of halogens such as chlorine and bromine to a car- 

bon-carbon double bond is a well-known reaction and proceeds with good 

yield and few side reactions. Elimination of hydrogen halide from adjacent 

carbon atoms in a halogenated hydrocarbon is also a well-known reaction to 

introduce a carbon-carbon double or triple bond. Since polyacetylene reacts 

with chlorine and bromine under mild conditions, we thought carbonization 

might be possible by combining the both reactions. Thus, a polyacetylene 

film was reacted with chlorine at room temperature to give a chlorinated 

polyacetylene film, which was subsequently treated with a basic reagent to 

eliminate hydrogen chloride to give a carbon film in satisfactory yield. How- 

ever, we found that the carbon film was hardly graphitized even when heated 

at 2000 °C for several hours.

  Fully chlorinated polyacetylene has a chemical structure of -(CHC1-CHC1)n-, 

corresponding to a polymer of 1,2-dichloroethylene. It is known, however, 

1,2-disubstituted ethylenes hardly ever polymerize. Therefore, the chlorina- 

tion of polyacetylene is the sole method to synthesize poly(1,2-dichloroethy- 

lene). To investigate the chlorination process of the polyacetylene film, in situ 

measurements were planned to obtain the infrared spectra during the chlo- 

rination of the polyacetylene film.

  It is well known that chlorination of the simplest conjugated polyene, 1,3- 

butadiene, gives two isomeric products, the 1,2-addition product (3,4-di- 

chloro-l-butene) and the 1,4-addition product (1,4-dichloro-2-butene). Like- 

wise, 1,3,5-hexatriene gives three isomers, 1,2-, 1,4- and 1,6-addition products. 

The reason why the reaction gives various products is explained by the exi- 

stence of different resonance structures in the intermediate as shown in 

Scheme 3. The third isomer is thermodynamically the most stable because 

the molecule has an inner conjugated diene structure with the largest energy 

of resonance stabilization.

  The motivation of the study was to confirm that the 1,2n-addition of chlo- 

rine might occur as the initial step of the reaction as shown in Scheme 4a and 

4b. Since the longer inner polyene structure has the larger energy of reso- 

nance stabilization, it is anticipated that products of 1,2n-addition with larger 

n predominate, rather than a 1,2-addition product at the initial step of the re- 

action or in the partially chlorinated polyacetylene. If such structures could 

be detected by infrared spectroscopy, one might expect that the positive








                        CICH2-CH-CH =CH-CH=CE12-        CICH2-CHCI-CH =CH-CH=CH2

                   C12           il
CH2=CH-CH =CH-CH=CII2   CrI42-CH=CH -CH--CH=CH2CI       CiCH2-CH=CH -CHCI-CH=CH2




                        CICH2-CH=CH -CH=CH-CH2          CICH2-CI-1=CH -CH=CH-CH2CI


Scheme 3. Possible resonance structures in the intermediate during the process of the chlorina- 

tion of 1,3,5-hexatriene and three chlorinated products.

460                                                                          Chemistry 2000

                                                                                                                              .....,    "...,...
                                  CI                                                    1 +Ch
                                             ",......  `,...,    "....,     "..,      "....„... ,..,      "........ "N.,      `...,     `...,,

                                  Cl                                                  1[
                                                                 "--...     '''....   "......   ""-....             "■...     ''....    N-...

                                  CI                                                  8
                                        ...-""     ...."         ....,...   ......,   ....,     ,s,...    "...„,    ".., 

                                  Cl                                                  1l
                                                                            ',.....   ......    ,,,,,.              '-...     ".....    "....,

                                  Cl                                                  1l
                                        .,../      „...,     ....../   ,.."           ,..,      ....„,    "...,     ••••,„,   "".„...   `....,


                                  CI                                                  1[
                                                                       ....."    ......."       "...„...  "..,      `...„,,   "......

                                  CI
                                        ...""      ,...""    ....."    ....."    ......."  ....-*"        ,,,,..    ,.......  `.....,   .....„

                                  CI                                                  IL
                                        ....-'     ..?"      ...,"     ,...-"              ...""     ..-.'"

                                  CI
                                        ......"    ...."     ...,"     ...."     ..--."              ---"       ..--"         N., "...,




Scheme 4a. Possible resonance structures of the intermediate in the chlorination of polyacety- 
lene.


change on the intermediate carbocation is able to migrate far away from the 
reaction site through the conjugated polyene structure.
      Contrary to this expectation, the infrared spectrophotometer recorded no 
spectrum but only a 100 % absorption line in the full range of 4000 to 400 
cm-1 immediately after addition of a trace amount of chlorine to the film. The 
polyacetylene film changed into an opaque material because of some very 
strong absorptions. Upon continued reaction with additional chlorine, the 
spectrum became clearer to give that corresponding to a chlorinated poly- 
acetylene.


VI. EPILOGUE

Later, we know that the very strong absorptions, is the so-called "doping in- 
duced infrared band" composed of three bands at 1397, 1288, and 888 cm-1 
[27-29], which have extremely strong absorption coefficients compared with

                    Hideki Shirakawa           461

          Cl

          ClCI

          Cl  CI

          Cl     Cl

          Cl        CI

                      CI
          CI 

                         Cl
          Cl 

          CI                CI

          CI                  CI
                        •    •        •

Scheme 4b. Expected chemical structures of partially chlorinated polyacetylene.


those of the as-prepared polymer. The observed isotope shifts of these bands 
in the spectra of poly(acetylene-13C2) and poly(acetylene-d2) demonstrated 
that these bands are of vibration origin [27] in the vicinity of the carbocation 
or positively charged carbon in the conjugated polyene. At present, the car- 
bocation formed in long conjugated polyenes is widely known as a positively 
charged soliton [30] that acts as a charge carrier for the electrical conduction. 
At that time, to my regret, I did not recognize that this carbocation could be a 
charge carrier and thus polyacetylene could be the first conducting polymer. 
To open an era of conducting polymers, we had to wait until we intentionally 
carried out the doping experiment with bromine at University of Pennsylva- 
nia, on Tuesday 23rd, 1976 and the later also successively with iodine [31, 32].

ACKNOWLEDGMENT
At the end of my lecture I want to express my heartfelt thanks to the late 
Professor Sakuji Ikeda who gave me a chance to work on the acetylene poly- 
merization, to Professor Masahiro Hatano who contributed to the semicon- 
ducting polymers and encouraged me on my work, to the late Professor Shu

462              Chemistry 2000

Kambara who organized our polymer research group and supported us in 
our work even after his retirement, and to Dr. Hyung Chick Pyun with whom 
I encountered the discovery of polyacetylene film by the fortuitous error. Dr. 
Takeo Ito was the first graduate student for me and who made a great contri- 
bution at the initial stage of this work. My special thanks are to Professors 
Shiro Maeda, Takehiko Shimanouchi, and Mitsuo Tasumi for helpful discus- 
sion on the vibration analyses study. I am indebted to Mr. Shigeru Ando for 
measurements of solid-state properties and to Professor Yoshio Sakai for elec- 
trical conductivity measurements. Throughout this period our research had 
been partly supported by Grant-in-Aids for Scientific Research from Ministry 
of Education, Culture and Science of Japan.


REFERENCES
 [1] J. A. Pople and S. H. Walmsley, Mol. Phys., 5, 15 (1962).
 [2] G. Natta, G. Mazzanti, and P. Corradini, Atti Acad. Naz. Lincei, Cl. Sci. Fis. Mat. Nat., 
   Rend., (8), 25: 3 (1958).
 [3] R. Kuhn, Angew. Chem., 34, 703 (1937).
 [4] J. H. C. Nayler and M. C. Whiting,/ Chem. Soc., 3037 (1965).
 [5] F. Bohlmann and H. Manhardt, Chem. Ber., 89, 1307 (1956).
 [6] F. Sondheimer, D. A. Ben-Efraim and R. Wolovsky, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 83, 1675 (1961).
 [7] Y. Takeuchi, A. Yasuhara, S. Akiyama, and M. Nakagawa, Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn., 46, 2822 
   (1973).
 [8] K. Knoll and R. R. Schrock, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 111, 7989 (1989).
 [9] N. S. Bayliss, J. Chem. Phys., 16, 287 (1948), Quart. Rev., 6, 319 (1952).
[10] H. Kuhn, Hely. Chim. Acta, 31, 1441 (1948).
[11] Y. Ooshika, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn., 12, 1238 , 1246 (1957).
[12] H. C. Longuet-Higgins and L. Salem, Proc. Roy. Soc., A, 252, 172 (1959).
[13] M. Tsuji, S. Fuzinaga, and T. Hashino, Rev. Mod. Phys., 32, 425 (1960).
[14] C. S. Yannoni and T. C. Clarke, Phys. Rev. Lett., 51, 1191 (1983).
[15] L. B. Luttinger, J. Org. Chem., 27, 1591 (1962).
[16] W. E. Daniels, J. Org. Chem., 29, 2936 (1964).
[17] M. Hatano, S. Kambara, and S. Okamoto, J. Polym. Sci., 51, S26 (1961).
[18] W. H. Watson, Jr., W. C. McMordie, Jr., and L. G. Lands,/ Polym. Sci., 55, 137 (1961).
[19] D. J. Berets and D. S. Smith, Trans. Faraday Soc., 64, 823 (1968).
[20] S. Ikeda and A. Tamaki, I Polym. Sci., Polym. Lett., 4, 605 (1966).
[21] K. Fukui and S. Inagaki,/ Am. Chem. Soc., 96, 4445 (1975).
[22] S. Ikeda, Kogyo Kagaku Zasshi, 70, 1880 (1967).
[23] T. Ito, H. Shirakawa, and S. Ikeda, J. Polym. Sci., Polym. Chem. Ed., 12, 11 (1974).
[24] H. Shirakawa and S. Ikeda, Polym. J., 2, 231 (1971).
[25] T. Ito, H. Shirakawa, and S. Ikeda, J. Polym. Sci., Polym. Chem. Ed., 13, 1943 (1975).
[26] H. Shirakawa, T. Ito, and S. Ikeda, Makromol. Chem., 179, 1565 (1978).
[27] I. Harada, Y. Furukawa, M. Tasumi, H. Shirakawa, and S. Ikeda, J. Chem. Phys., 73, 
   4746 (1980).
[28] J. F. Rabolt, T. C. Clarke, and G. B. Street,/ Chem. Phys., 71, 4614 (1979).
[29] C. R. Fincherjr., M. Ozaki, A. J. Heeger, and A. G. MacDiarmid, Phys. Rev. B 19, 4140 
   (1979).
[30] W. P. Su, J. R. Schrieffer, and A. J. Heeger, Phys. Rev. Lett., 42, 1698 (1979).
[31] H. Shirakawa, E. J. Louis, A. G. MacDiarmid, C. K. Chiang, and A. J. Heeger, J. Chem. 
   Soc., Chem. Commun., 578 (1977).
[32] C. K. Chiang, C. R. Pincher, Jr., Y. W. Park, A. J. Heeger, H. Shirakawa, E. J. Louis, S. 
   C. Gau, and A. G. MacDiarmid, Phys. Rev. Lett., 39, 1098 (1977).

