246

QUANTUM CHEMICAL MODELS

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1998 
by
JOHN A. POPLE
Department of Chemistry, Northwestern University, 2145 Sheridan Road, 
Evanston, Illinois 60208, USA


INTRODUCTION
The fundamental underpinnings of theoretical chemistry were uncovered in 
a relatively short period at the beginning of the present century. Rutherford's 
discovery of the nucleus in 1910 completed the identification of the con- 
stituent subparticles of atoms and molecules and was followed shortly there- 
after by the Bohr treatment of electronic orbits in atoms, the "old quantum 
theory". The relation between the positive nuclear charge, atomic number 
and position of an atom in the periodic table was uncovered by 1913. It prov- 
ed difficult to extend Bohr's orbits to a polyatomic situation and the next ad- 
vance had to await the development of the wave theory of matter and the as- 
sociated quantum mechanics in the early 1920s. By 1926, Heisenberg had 
developed matrix mechanics and Schrodinger had proposed the basic non- 
relativistic wave equation governing the motion of nuclei and electrons in 
molecules. The latter,
                TN' = EY'           (1)
is a differential eigenvalue equation for the energy E and wavefunction (If of 
a particular state. His the Hamiltonian operator and T depends on cartesian 
and spin coordinates of the component particles. The only further restric- 
tions are the permutational symmetry requirements for V' (antisymmetry for 
fermions such as electrons and symmetry for bosons). A relativistic generali- 
zation of this equation was proposed a short time later by Dirac.
 The Schrodinger equation is easily solved for the hydrogen atom and 
found to give results identical to the earlier treatment of Bohr. With inclusion 
of relativistic corrections via the Dirac equation, almost perfect agreement 
was found with experimental spectroscopic data. However, exact solution for 
any other system was not found possible, leading to a famous remark by Dirac 
in 1929:
 "The fundamental laws necessary for the mathematical treatment of a large 
part of physics and the whole of chemistry are thus completely known, and 
the difficulty lies only in the fact that application of these laws leads to equa- 
tions that are too complex to be solved"
 This was a cry both of triumph and of despair. It marked the end of the 
process of fundamental discovery in chemistry but left a collossal mathe-

               John A. Pople       247

matical task of implementation. In retrospect, the implied finality of the 
claim seems excessively bold. In 1929, there had only been one preliminary 
approximate quantum mechanical calculation on the hydrogen molecule by 
Heitler and London, leading to a value of the bond energy of only about 70% 
of the experimental value. Nevertheless, the physicists were highly confident 
and most moved on to study the internal structure of the nucleus during the 
1930s. In fact, their boldness was apparently justified, for no significant 
failure of the full Schrodinger-Dirac treatment has ever been demonstrated.
 This was the challenge presented to the early quantum chemists by 1930. 
Given the hopelessness of exact solution, how would it be possible to develop 
approximate mathematical procedures that could (a) assist the qualitative in- 
terpretation of chemical phenomena; and (b) provide predictive capability. 
Attempts to approach this problem by a model approach is the topic ad- 
dressed here.

FEATURES OF THEORETICAL MODELS
A theoretical model for any complex process is an approximate but well-defined 
mathematical procedure of simulation. When applied to chemistry, the task is 
to use input information about the number and character of component par- 
ticles (nuclei and electrons) to derive information and understanding of 
resultant molecular behavior. Five stages may be distinguished in the devel- 
opment and use of such a model:

Target
A target accuracy must be selected. A model is not likely to be of much value 
unless it is able to provide clear distinction between possible different modes 
of molecular behavior. As the model becomes quantitative, the target should 
be that data is reproduced and predicted within experimental accuracy. For 
energies, such as heats of formation or ionization potentials, a global ac- 
curacy of 1 kcal/mole would be appropriate.

Formulation
The approximate mathematical procedure must be precisely formulated. 
This should be general and continuous as far as possible. Thus, particular pro- 
cedures for particular molecules or particular symmetries should be avoided. 
If this can be done, the procedure becomes a full theoretical model chemistry, 
which can be explored in detail as far as available resources permit.

Implementation
The formulated method has to be implemented in a form, which permits its 
application in reasonable times and at reasonable cost. In recent times, this 
stage involves the development of efficient and easily used computer pro- 
grams. It is closely comparable to the stage of building equipment in an ex- 
perimental investigation.

248                 Chemistry 1 998

Verification
The next step is to test the model against known chemical facts to determine 
whether the target has been achieved. If quantitative accuracy is being 
sought, this can be done by various statistical criteria such as the root-mean- 
square difference between the results of the theoretical model and experi- 
mental data. In selecting such a data-set, it is important to make it as broad as 
possible, while limiting it to experimental facts known to be of high quality. If 
the results of such a comparison do meet the target requirements, the model 
may be said to be validated.

Prediction
Finally, if the model has been properly validated according to some such 
criterion, it may be applied to chemical problems to which the answer is un- 
known or in dispute. If the experimental data-set is sufficiently broad, there is 
a reasonable expectation that the results will be accurate to something like 
the target accuracy. This stage, of course, is the one of most interest to the 
larger chemical community.
  One further aspect of theoretical models is the introduction of empirical 
parameterization. Models which utilize only the fundamental constants of 
physics are generally termed ab initio; if some parameters are introduced 
which are determined by fitting to some experimental data, the methods are 
semi-empirical . Clearly, there is a wide range of possible empiricism, as will be 
noted in subsequent parts of this article.

HARTREE-FOCK MODELS
During the 1930s, most work was of a qualitative nature, treating the electrons 
as moving in independent molecular orbitals. However, the foundations of the 
the orbital theory of many-electron systems was laid by Hartree, Fock and 
Slater. If the 2n electrons in a closed-shell molecule are assigned to a set of n 
molecular orbitals tv, (i = 1,...n), the corresponding many-electron wavefunc- 
tion can be written

             = (0!)-1/2det[(0la)(1113)(b2a)...1 (2)

Here the are taken to be orthonormal and a and 13 are spin functions. This 
single-configuration wavefunction is usually described as a Slater determinant.
  If the molecular orbitals tv, are varied to minimize the energy, calculated as 
the expectation value of the full Hamiltonian H,
                   E =< 411111W >               (3)
then the energy E is fully defined and, according to the variational principle, 
is an upper bound for the exact Schrodinger energy from the full wave equa- 
tion (1). This procedure leads to a set of coupled differential equations for 
the yiZ, as first derived by Fock. The method is known as Hartree-Fock theory, 
early applications having been made (to atoms) by Hartree.

                           John A. Pople                    249

  Following the break due to World-War II, work on quantum chemistry re- 
sumed in a number of countries. In Cambridge, Lennard-Jones and his group 
(of which I became a member in 1948) reexamined the Hartree-Fock equa- 
tions with a view to transforming the orbitals vi into localized or equivalent 
orbitals, representing bonding and lone electron pairs, concepts widely used 
in the qualitative description of molecular structure. However, the coupled 3- 
dimensional differential equations appeared intractable and little progress 
was made towards their solution.
  A major advance occurred in 1951 with the publication from Chicago of 
the Roothaan equations [1]. (Actually, these had been circulated in a report 
some time earlier.) Roothaan considered molecular orbitals that were restrict- 
ed to be linear combinations of a set of prescribed 3-dimensional 1-electron 
functions xm(,u = 1,2,..N, N>n).Thus
                               N
                              E                              (4)
                              A=1
Variation of the total energy (3) was then carried out with respect to the co- 
efficients pci This leads to a set of algebraic equations which can be written in 
matrix form (using real functions and atomic units throughout),
                            FC = SCE                         (5)
where
           Fti, =     + E PA,RpviA0-) — (01va)/21            (6)
                        Ao-
                       I I th, = f xi.,Hxydr                 (7)

                        Spv = f xi,x,d-r                     (8)

                           E12 = Ei6ij                       (9)
                                 n
                        Piii, = 2 E c„,c,,,                 (10)

       (wviAa) = I f xp(1)x,(1)(1/r12)xA(2)x,(2)dr1dy2      (11)

In these and subsequent equations, we follow a useful practice of using 
roman suffixes for molecular orbitals tv and greek for the expansion func- 
tions z. H is the core Hamiltonian, describing motion of a single electron 
moving in the bare field of the nuclei. The eigenvalues s are the one-electron 
Fock energies, the lowest n corresponding to the occupied molecular orbitals 
1,2,...n.
  These nonlinear equations provide a complete mathematical model if the 
prescribed functions xy are uniquely specified by the nuclear positions. They

250            Chemistry 1998

are often referred to as self consistent field (SCF) equations. In the earliest ver- 
sions of molecular orbital theory, the xi, were chosen to be the atomic orbitals 
of the component atoms, in which case the theory was described as 
LCAOSCF for 'linear combination of atomic orbitals'. More generally, the set 
{20 is referred to as the basis set. Normal practice is to choose basis functions 
which are centered at the nuclei and depend only on the atomic number 
(positive charge) of that nucleus.
 The Roothaan-type of equations can be extended to electron configura- 
tions in which some orbitals are doubly occupied and some singly. Another 
extension is one in which electrons of a-spin and 13-spin are assigned to dif- 
ferent molecular orbitals te and tp0. This is usually referred to as a spin-un- 
restricted configuration. There will be two sets of coefficients cpai and The 
corresponding generalization of the Roothaan equations was published by 
the author and Nesbet in 1954 [2]. These are usually denoted as Unrestricted 
Hartree-Fock or UHF, and the option of double and single occupation as 
Restricted Open Hartree-Fock or ROHF.
 The introduction of basis set expansions played a major role in the devel- 
opment of quantum chemistry. It changed the mathematical task from the 
numerical solution of coupled differential equations (following the atomic 
work of Hartree) to the double challenge of evaluation of the 3- or 6-dimen- 
sional integrals (7),(8) and (11), followed by solution of the algebraic SCF 
equations (5). If analytic integration were possible, the model could become 
precise in the sense that good arithmetic correctness would be possible, even 
though the underlying approximations (use of a single configuration deter- 
minant and a finite basis) might still be unsatisfactory.
 During the 1950s, integral evaluation was regarded as the main barrier to 
progress. The best choice of basis functions for LCAOSCF theory appeared to 
be Slater-type atomic orbitals (STO), which have exponential radial parts by 
analogy to the hydrogen atom. The one- and two-electron integrals (7),(8) 
and (11) can then be evaluated analytically in the two-center case. However, 
great difficulties were encountered for the three- and four-center cases. It was 
common to describe this impasse as "the nightmare of the integrals".
 There were two responses to the integral difficulties. One was to make ap- 
proximations for the more difficult integrals and to introduce parameters for 
others, with values obtained by empirical fits to experimental data. This prac- 
tice became known as semi-empirical. The alternative of proceeding without ap- 
proximation or empirical parameterization was, at the time, necessarily 
limited to very small molecules and became known as the ab initio approach. 
The most widely used semi-empirical methods were based on the zero-dif- 
ferential-overlap approximation, in which products of different atomic oritals 
zmx, are neglected in most integrals. This approximation, when applied to 
the 7r-electrons of conjugated organic molecules, became known as the 
Pariser-Parr-Pople (PPP) theory [3-5]. It was later generalized to the treat- 
ment of all valence electrons in the CNDO and INDO theories [6] (1964-6) 
and then pursued at a more empirical level by the group of MJ.S.Dewar. The 
CNDO/INDO methods were genuine chemical models in the sense that they

                John A. Pople      251

could be used to study many molecules, vary structure to determine equi- 
librium geometries and generate potential surfaces. However, they were limit- 
ed by uncertainty over the consequences of the massive integral approxima- 
tions and the large number of empirical parameters.
 Within the ab initio community, a truly major development was the intro- 
duction of gaussian-type basis functions. In 1950, S.F. Boys [7], working in 
Cambridge, had demonstrated that all integrals in SCF theory could be 
evaluated analytically if the radial parts had the form P(x,y,x)exp(-12), where 
P(x,y,z) is any polynomial in the cartesian coordinates x,y,z. Initially, this ap- 
peared to be of limited value, since single gaussian functions were poor ap- 
proximations to atomic orbitals, but it was clear that prospects would improve 
if larger numbers of basis functions could be handled. For several years, 
there was competition between proponents of Slater-type and gaussian-type 
basis sets.
 The 1950s also saw the introduction of computers into quantum chemistry. 
By the time of the 1959 meeting, there were already several groups develop- 
ing ab initio programs, using both Slater and gaussian bases. Early 
codes for 2-center integrals with Slater basis functions were developed in 
Chicago and used by Ransil in the first full LCAOSCF treatment of diatomic 
hydrides. At the same meeting, Boys presented several prescient papers 
describing simple SCF calculations using gaussians. During the early 1960s, 
other general purpose programs were developed, notably the gaussian pack- 
ages POLYATOM and IBMOL, leading to a number of individual computa- 
tions of molecular orbitals at the LCAO or minimal basis level.
 My own research group began ab initio work in 1968 with the development 
of the GAUSSIAN program. At that time, the relative cost of ab initio 
LCAOSCF and CNDO computations on small organic molecules was over 
1000. The original intention was to use full ab initio results to test various in- 
tegral approximations that were less severe than the use of zero differential 
overlap. However, in the course of developing the program, Warren Hehre 
and I were able to generate a new integral algorithm that improved efficien- 
cy for highly contracted gaussian basis sets by more than two orders of mag- 
nitude [8]. This was based on a method of axis rotation inside inner loops, 
thereby limiting the number of arithmetic operations in the innermost sec- 
tions of the program. Using a procedure of least-squares fitting Slater-type 
basis functions by a fixed contraction of K gaussians, we were able to repro- 
duce the results of earlier full Slater results on a series of small molecules. 
The choice K=3 proved adequate and led to the STO-3G basis and the gene- 
ral theoretical model HF/STO-3G. This was published in 1969 [9] and the 
code was made generally available as GAUSSIAN70 shortly thereafter.
 Investigation of the minimal HF/STO-3G model quickly showed major 
failures. Comparison of some isomeric species (e.g. propene and cyclopro- 
pane) showed too much stability for single bonds, relative to multiple bonds. 
This can be traced to the failure of the minimal basis to describe anisotropic 
atoms. In acetylene, for example, the carbon 2p6 atomic orbitals should be 
much tighter than 2p7r; this effect cannot be properly simulated by the

252            Chemistry 1998

isotropic structure implied by a minimal basis with identical 2p functions in 
all three directions. This difficulty can be overcome by using two basis func- 
tions per valence atomic orbital instead of one. Such a basis is 6-31G, which 
has a single contracted 6-gaussian basis function for the inner shell, a set of 
inner 3-contracted and a set of outer uncontracted gaussians for the valence 
shell of each atom. This is an example of a split-valence basis. Another similar 
commonly used type of basis set is double-zeta, in which there are two basis 
functions per atomic orbital for all atomic shells.
 There are several notable failures for split-valence bases. In the first place, 
such bases tend to favor structures of high symmetry. For example, the am- 
monia molecule NH3 is predicted to have a trigonal structure which is too 
close to planarity. This deficiency can reasonably be attributed to the fact 
that, in a planar structure, the lone pair of electrons are assigned to a nitro- 
gen orbital that is pure p-type, which cannot mix with higher angular mo- 
mentum d-type functions, whereas, in a non- planar structure, the lone-pair 
orbital is a sp mixture, for which further stabilization by d-mixing is possible. 
A second deficiency in Hartree-Fock studies at the split-valence level is an ex- 
aggeration of polarity, as measured by electric dipole moments. This can also 
be attributed to restriction of lone-pair orbitals to pure p-type. The 3pir lone- 
pair orbitals in HCl, for example, will probably be polarized towards hydro- 
gen if mixing with dr basis is allowed, thereby reducing the predicted dipole 
moment.
 Considerable improvement is found in Hartree-Fock models if a single set 
of uncontracted d-functions are added on each heavy (non-hydrogen) atom. 
Such a basis is 6-31G*, or 6-31G(d) [10,11]. If a single set of uncontracted 
p-functions is added on each hydrogen, the basis is denoted by 6-31G** or 6- 
31G(d,p) . These additional basis functions are termed polarization functions. 
The full model with the 6-31G* basis is then described as HF/6-31G*. Other 
important basis set extensions are the introduction of higher polarization 
functions (as in 6-31G(2df,p) which contains two sets of d-functions and a set 
of f-functions on heavy atoms and a single set of p-functions on hydrogen) 
and the use of diffuse functions, which are particularly important for anions 
and electronic states. The latter are denoted by a `+' as in 6-31+G(d).
 The Hartree-Fock model HF/6-31G* has proved quite effective in the 
description of molecular conformations. Its overall performance in this and 
other regards has been documented elsewhere [12]. It is notably successful in 
giving differences of different isomeric forms of organic molecules, where no 
major changes of bond lengths are involved. Rotational potentials about 
single bonds were successfully explored using this level of theory [13]. A par- 
ticular example is the anomeric effect in carbohydrate chemistry, which was 
not properly understood until the interaction of rotational potentials about 
geminal C-0 single bonds was investigated using HF/6-31G* theory [14].

                  John A. Pople        253

 CORRELATED MODELS
 The major fault implicit in all Hartree-Fock models is neglect of electron cor- 
 relation between the motions of electrons of antiparallel spin (af3 correla- 
 tion). In the very early days of quantum chemistry, it was recognized that 
 neglect of correlation led to severe underestimation of bond dissociation 
 energies. This may be understood qualitatively by considering the process of 
 complete homolytic dissociation of a bond in which one electron ends up on 
 one center and one on the other. If the motion of the two electrons is uncor- 
 related, there will be a finite possibility of both electrons ending up on the 
 same center.
  Neglect of af3 electron correlation is implicit in the use of a single-deter- 
 minant wavefunction; improved wavefunctions necessarily involve the use of 
 many determinants. Most practical correlation procedures start with the 
 Hartree-Fock determinant and form linear combinations with other deter- 
 minants. It is particularly convenient to form additional determinants from 
 the unoccupied or virtual molecular orbitals, which are the higher eigen- 
 functions of the Fock operator. If a finite basis is used, with 2n electrons and 
 N cartesian basis functions, there will be N-n virtual orbitals, which may be oc- 
 cupied by a or /3 electrons.
  At this point, it is convenient to change the notation somewhat and use 
 spinorbital basis functions which are products of the cartesian basis functions 
 and the a or /3 spin functions. Nis now the size of this spinorbital basis (twice 
 the number of cartesian basis functions) and n is the total number of elec- 
 trons. This notation enables us to use a common notation for both spin-re- 
 stricted and spin-unrestricted cases. If labels i,j,k,... are used for occupied 
 spinorbitals and labels a,b,c,... for virtual, then single-determinant functions 
 using Fock orbitals may be classified as unsubstituted (i.e. Hartree-Fock)
 singly substituted r, doubly substituted tlia,; and so forth. A general multi- 
 determinant wavefunction can then be written

         = ao   E aNita + E aza3bv:: + (12)
                 is     ijab
 The a-coefficients can be determined by variation to minimize the calculated 
 energy. This is the method of configuration interaction (CI). If only singles are 
 mixed in, no energy lowering follows, since the occupied orbitals are already 
 optimized. The simplest effective form of CI allows for doubles only in (12). 
This is usually denoted by CID. If singles are also included, the method is 
 CISD. These configuration interaction techniques were first implemented as 
 iterative schemes around 1970 and are still often used in practical computa- 
 tions. If all possible substitutions are included in the expansion (a large but 
 finite set if a finite basis set is used), the method is described as full configu- 
 ration or FCI. The FCI procedure, although desirable in principle, is usually 
 too costly to apply except for very small systems.
  Although CID and CISD are well-defined models, given a standard basis 
set, they suffer some serious disadvantages. These have to do with size-con-

254               Chemistry 1998

sistency. If a method such as CID is applied to a pair of completely separated 
systems, the resulting energy is not the sum of the energies obtained by ap- 
plying the same theory to the systems separately. If CID is applied to two 
separated helium atoms, for example, the wavefunction does not allow for 
simultaneous excitation of pairs in each atom, this being strictly a quadruple 
excitation. This failure of CID and CISD models is likely to lead to poor 
descriptions of large molecules and interacting systems.
 A second general method of incorporating electron correlation is to treat 
its effects by perturbation theory. Suppose we define a perturbed Hamilto- 
nian as
              H(A) = F0 + A{H - F0}       (13)

where F0 is the Fock Hamiltonian (for which the single determinants in (12) 
are exact eigenfunctions), then To is the appropriate wavefunction if A = 0 
and the exact(FCI) T is obtained if A = 1. The perturbation procedure used is 
to expand the computed energy in powers of A,

         E(\) = E0 + AE1 + \2E2+ \3E3+... (14)

cut the series off at some level and then put A = 1. This perturbation method 
was first introduced by Moeller and Plesset [15] and is often denoted by MPn 
if terminated at order n. The MP1 energy (E0 + E1) is identical to the Hartree- 
Fock value. MP2 is the simplest practical perturbative procedure for electron 
correlation and incorporates only effects of double substitutions. At third or- 
der, MP3 also involves only double substitutions. At the fourth order level, 
MP4 includes a description of the (indirect) effects of singles, the leading 
contributions of triples and some treatment of certain quadruple substitu- 
tions.
 Moeller-Plesset theory is size-consistent if the computations are carried out 
completely at any given order. Difficulties are that the terms become alge- 
braically complicated at higher orders and also are increasingly costly to ap- 
ply. In fact, Hartree-Fock theory (with no integral approximations) scales as 
N4, MP2 as N5, MP3 as N6 and MP4 as N7. The triple contributions in the 
MP4 energy are the most expensive and generally limit the applicability of 
Moeller-Plesset theory to this level. The MP2,MP3 and MP4 models were 
implemented by several groups in the 1970s and incorporated into the 
GAUSSIAN program [16,17].
 A third general approach to correlation theory is the use of coupled cluster 
methods, originally introduced into quantum chemistry by Cizek [18]. If the 
configuration interaction CID wavefunction is written in the form
                   = (1 + T2),P0          (15)

where T2 is an operator specifiying all double substitutions, with undetermin- 
ed coefficients, then the corresponding coupled- cluster function (CCD) is

                 John A. Pople       255

                 = exp(T2)T0         (16)
The CCD coefficients are determined, not by the variational method, but by 
requiring zero projection of (H— L) onto To and all Tab. This method was 
first implemented in 1978 [19-21] . Single substitutions are incorporated by 
using the operator exp(T1+ T2) instead of exp( T1). This then defines a CCSD 
model [22,23].
 Unlike CISD, the CCSD method is size-consistent. The cost is of order N6, 
as for CISD. Being non-variational, the resulting total energy is no longer an 
upper bound for the exact result, but it is generally thought that the achieve- 
ment of size-consistency is a matter of greater importance. Another, slightly 
simpler, method is quadratic configuration denoted QCISD. This is also size- 
consistent and can be regarded as an approximation intermediate between 
CISD and CCSD.
 The QCISD and CCSD methods take no account of the effects of triple sub- 
stitutions, known to be important by studies at the MP4 level. A useful way to 
take account of triples is to carry out an iterative QCISD or CCSD computa- 
tion and the do a single computation of the effects of triples, using the single 
and double amplitudes already found. These are the QCISD (T) and 
CCSD (T) methods [24,25]. A third related method is the Brueckner-doubles 
method, BD (T) [26], which alters the underlying occupied orbitals so that 
ther is no singles mixing. All three of these methods are superior to MP4 in 
that, when the energy is expanded in a Moeller-Plesset series, complete agree- 
ment with a FCI expansion is obtained up to fourth order and many other 
terms at higher order are also included [27]. In fact, the QCISD, CCSD and 
BD methods have the further advantage of being completely correct for com- 
posite two-electron systems such as a set of isolated helium atoms.
 The cost of QCISD (T) or CCSD(T) scales as iterative N6, followed by a 
single computation at N7. They represent the most sophisticated correlation 
methods that are simple enough to be incorporated into general theoretical 
models at the present time.

GENERAL ENERGY MODELS
In recent years, progress has been made in developing models which repro- 
duce chemical energies to an accuracy approaching that achieved in good ex- 
perimental work. The description of model features in the two previous sec- 
tions indicates that two main features are involved, basis set and level of 
correlation. The options available are usefully summarized in a two-dimen- 
sional model chart as shown in Figure 1. The various correlation methods are 
displayed horizontally in order of increasing sophistication from left to right. 
Basis sets are displayed vertically, becoming more flexible from top to bottom. 
At the far right, full configuration interaction (FCI) represents complete 
solution within the finite space defined by the basis. At the bottom of the table, we 
have (in principle but not in practice), the results of applying a complete 
basis set. At the bottom right, application of a complete basis set with full con-

256            Chemistry 1998

figuration interaction corresponds to full solution of the non-relativistic 
Schrodinger equation.

   Basis   HF  MP2  MP3  MP4  QCI FCI
   STO-3G
   6-31G
   6-31G(d)
  6-31+0(d)
  6-311+G(d)
 6-311+G(2df)
    co                            S-eqn
Figure 1. General Model Table. (QCI refers to QCISD(T)).
Each empty box in this chart represents a well-defined size-consistent theo- 
retical model as specified in Section 2. Clearly, we may test each level to find 
how far we have to proceed from top-left to bottom-right for acceptable 
agreement between theory and experiment. Eventually, adequate per- 
formance will be achieved, if the underlying assumptions of quantum me- 
chanics are correct.
 In practice, full models usually have to make some compromises to achieve 
a wide range of applicability. If the prediction of energies is most important, 
a common practice is to carry out a geometry optimization (to an equili- 
brium structure, for example) at some lower level of theory and then make a 
final, more expensive, computation at a higher level. A useful notation for 
this type of composite model is "model-1//model-2", meaning single-point 
calculations using model-1 at geometrical structures determined by model-2.
 To illustrate these ideas, we give a partial description of the G3 model for 
molecular energies, recently published [28]. This is a refinement of previous 
energy models G1 and G2 which have been under development for more 
than a decade [29,30]. The main computational steps are summarized in 
Figure 2.

         Basis  HF  MP2 MP4  QCI
        6-31G(d)freqopt-12    3
        6-31+G(d)    4   5
       6-31G(2df,p)  6   7
        G3large      8        ?
Figure 2. G3 Model Table. (QCI refers to QCISD(T)).

                                  John A. Pople                              257

In addition to the standard type of basis sets already described, a large basis 
(G3large), which permits a flexible description of the whole space with inner 
shells, is added. This basis is so large that only MP2 computations are 
reasonably possible. Geometrical structures in the G3 model are determined 
at the MP2/6-31G(d) level [31] . This is followed by a sequence of single-point 
calculations which aim to estimate the results of a potential QCl/G3 large 
energy, by assuming that effects of some of the improvement steps can be 
treated additively. The actual formula used is:
         ? = 2 + (3 — 2) -F ( 5 — 2) + (7 — 2) + (8 — 1) — (4 - 1) — (6 — 1) (17)
Earlier studies [32] had indicated that this kind of addititivy was reasonably 
accurate. (It should be noted that all correlation computations except the full 
MP2/G3 large are carried out in the "frozen core" approximation, only in- 
teractions between valence electrons being treated).
  An important contribution to total molecular energies is the zero-point vi- 
brational energy. This is estimated in G3 theory by using harmonic frequen- 
cies calculated at the HF/6-31G(d) level and then empirically scaled by a fac- 
tor 0.8929 (HF theory being known to systemically overestimate the 
magnitudes of frequencies [33]). In addition, a small correction is added for 
the spin-orbit splitting in isolated atoms, obtained from experimental 
data [34].
  The computations as described up to this level give a reasonable account of 
significant energy differences, such as dissociation energies and ionization 
potentials. However, there is a significant systematic error, all binding ener- 
gies being slightly too low. This can be reasonably interpreted as being due 
mostly to the limitation in the basis sets being used. An accurate description 
of the wavefunction cusp at the point where electrons of opposite spin come 
to the same point in space requires basis sets involving high angular momen- 
tum. Another reason is that, in molecules, the symmetry is lower than in 
atoms and again neglect of the effects of higher angular momentum basis 
functions will favor atomic energies relative to molecular.
  These difficulties can be partly overcome by adding a small empirical cor- 
rection, depending on the number of electrons and distinguishing between 
atoms and molecules. The theory therefore becomes semi-empirical or, per- 
haps "slightly empirical" since the parameters are small and their origin is 
partly understood. This higher-level correction (HLC) is — Anv — B(na no) 
for molecules and — Cn13 — D(na — n,3) for atoms (including atomic ions). na 
and ??,9 are the numbers of a and )6 electrons, respectively, with na nfl. This 
completes the specification of a total G3 energy for any atom or molecule.
  The parameters A,B, C,D are determined as part of the validation process. 
This is carried out using a large set of 299 experimental energy differences, 
involving molecules up to the size of benzene (42 electrons). These data in- 
clude 148 heats of formation, derived from heats of atomization, 85 ioniza- 
tion potentials, 58 electron affinities and 8 proton affinities. All of these ex- 
perimental results are believed known to an accuracy of 1 kcal/mole or 
better. Values of A,B, C,D are obtained by minimization of the mean absolute

258            Chemistry 1998

deviation between theory and experiment. These are (in millihartrees) 6.386, 
2.977,6.219 and 1.185. The resulting mean deviation is 1.02 kcal/mole, close 
to the target accuracy. The corresponding root-mean-square deviation, which 
lays more emphasis on the poorer levels of agreement, is 1.45 kcal/mole. 
However, nearly 88 % of the G3 deviations fall in the range, —2.0 to +2.0 
kcal/mole.These results are significantly better than the prior G1 and G2 
models, which use a smaller database of experimental facts.
 The poorest results are worthy of note. Largest absolute deviations are 4.9 
kcal/mole (C2F4) for heats of formation, 7.0 kcal/mole (B2F4) for ionization 
potentials, 4.2 kcal/mole (NH) for electron affinities and 1.8 kcal/mole (P113 
and SH2) for proton affinities.

CONCLUSIONS
The current status of ab initio quantum chemical models is that some success 
has been achieved in approaching experimental accuracy in predictive power. 
The target of 1 kcal/mole is not far away for small molecules containing up to 
about fifty electrons. However, the G3 model has a number of remaining de- 
ficiencies that merit further attack.
1. The use of an empirical correction, which depends only on the number of 
 electrons, is undesirable. One consequence is that the model becomes dis- 
 continuous in some manner. For example, if a bond is broken, the elec- 
 tron count of paired versus unpaired electrons has to change at some 
 point, thereby providing a discontinuity in the potential surface. The same 
 criticism can be applied to the use of different parameters for atoms and 
 molecules. Some form of extrapolation is probably necessary, but it would 
 be much better if this could be carried out in a continuous and differenti- 
 able manner.
2. The G3 model is based on MP2/6-31G(d) geometries, which are known to 
 show considerable errors [311. Some of the failures of the final energies 
 can be attributed to this; clearly a method which would reproduce known 
 bond lengths and angles more accurately would be preferable.
3. No account is taken of relativity in the G3 model. The total energy of a 
 molecule is known to depend significantly on relativistic corrections, par- 
 ticularly for inner-shell electrons. However, considerable cancellation of 
 errors occurs in processes such as bond dissociation. Nevertheless, some 
 inclusion of relativistic contributions to chemical processes is clearly desir- 
 able.
4. The applicability of the G3 model to large systems is presently limited by 
 the very expensive treatment of the triples terms, where computational 
 cost scales as the seventh power of the size of the system. The magnitude of 
 these terms is small, but not insignificant. A simpler treatment of three- 
 electron effects would be desirable.
 Finally, some brief comment should be made about theoretical models 
based on density functional theory (DFT). Such methods do not handle the 
two-electron interactions explicitly but rather allow for them using properties

                  John A. Pople         259

of the one- electron density. This leads to lower cost and therefore a wider 
range of applicability. Recent forms of DFT have also introduced a consider- 
able amount of empirical parameterization, sometimes using the same set of 
experimental data. At the present time, the principal limitation of DFT 
models is that there is no clear route for convergence of methods to the cor- 
rect answer, comparable to the ab initio chart shown in Figure 1. Interaction 
between these two groups of theoretical chemists is a hopeful direction for 
future progress.



REFERENCES
1. C. C J. Roothaan, Rev. Mod. Phys. 23, 61 (1951).
2. J. A. Pople and R. K. Nesbet, J. Chem.Phys. 22, 571 (1954).
3. R. G. Parr, J. Chem. Phys. 20, 1499 (1952).
4. R. Pariser and R. G. Parr, J. Chem. Phys. 21, 466,767 (1953).
5. J. A. Pople, Trans. Faraday Soc. 49, 1375 (1953).
6. J. A. Pople, D. P. Santry and G. A. Segal, J. Chem. Phys. 43, 5129,5136 (1965).
7. S. F. Boys, Proc. Roy. Soc. A200, 542 (1950).
8. J. A. Pople and W. J. Hehre, J. Comput. Phys. 27, 161 (1978).
9. W. J. Hehre, R. F. Stewart and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys. 51, 2657 (1969).
10. P.C.Hariharan and J.A.Pople, Theor. Chim. Acta, 28, 213 (1971).
11. M. M. Francl, W. J. Pietro, W. J. Hehre, J. S. Binkley, M. S. Gordon, D. J. DeFrees and 
  J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys 77, 3654 (1982).
12. W. J. Hehre, L. Radom, P. v. R. Schleyer and J. A. Pople, "Ab Initio Molecular Orbital 
  Theory", John Wiley, (New York 1986).
13. L. Radom, W. J. Hehre and J. A. Pople, J. Amer. Chem.Soc. 54, 724 (1971).
14. G. A. Jeffrey, J. A. Pople and L. Radom, Carbohydrate Res. 25, 117 (1972).
15. C. Moeller and M. S. Plesset, Phys. Rev. 46, 618 (1934).
16. R. Krishnan and J. A. Pople, Int. J. Quantum Chem. 14, 91 (1978).
17. R. Krishnan, M. J. Frisch and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys. 72, 4244 (1980).
18. J. Cizek, J. Chem. Phys. 45, 4256 (1966).
19. J. A. Pople, R. Krishnan, H. B. Schlegel and J. S. Binkley, Int. J. Quantum Chem. 14, 
  545 (1978).
20. R. J. Bartlett and G. D. Purvis, Int. J. Quantum Chem. 14, 561 (1978).
21. P. R. Taylor, G. B. Bacskay, N. S. Hush and A. C. Hurley, Chem.Phys.Lett 41, 444 
  (1976).
22. G. D. Purvis and R. J. Bartlett, J. Chem. Phys. 76, 1910 (1982).
23. G. E. Scuseria, A. C. Schneiner, T. J. Lee, J. E. Rice and H. F. Schaefer, J. Chem.Phys. 
  86, 2881 (1987).
24. J. A. Pople, M. Head-Gordon and K. Raghavachari, J. Chem. Phys. 87,5968 (1987).
25. K. Raghavachari, G. W .Trucks, M.Head-Gordon and J. A. Pople, Chem. Phys. Lett. 
  157, 479 (1989).
26. N. C. Handy, J. A. Pople, M. Head-Gordoni, K. Raghavachari and G. W. Trucks, 
  Chem.Phys.Lett. 164, 185 (1989).
27. K. Raghavachari, J. A. Pople, E. S. Replogle and M. Head-Gordon, J. Chem. Phys. 94, 
  5579 (1990).
28. L. A. Curtiss, K. Raghavachari, P. C. Redfern, V. Rassolov and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. 
  Phys. 109, 7764 (1998).
29. L. A. Curtiss, C. Jones, G. W. Trucks, K. Raghavachari and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys. 
  93, 2537 (1990).
30. L. A. Curtiss, K. Raghavachari, G. W. Trucks and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys. 94, 7221 
  (1991).

260               Chemistry 1998

31. D. J. DeFrees, B. A. Levi, S. K. Pollack, W. J. Hehre, J. S. Binkley and J. A. Pople, J. 
   Amer. Chem. Soc. 101, 4843 (1979).
32. L. A. Curtiss, J. E. Carpenter, K. Raghavachari and J. A. Pople, J. Chem. Phys. 96, 9030 
   (1992).
33. J. A. Pople, H. B. Schlegel, K. Raghavachari, D. J. Defrees, J. S. Binkley, M. J. Frisch, R. 
   A. Whiteside, R. F. Hout and W. J. Hehre, Int J. Quantum Chem. 15, 269 (1981).
34. C. Moore, Natl. Bur. Stand. (U.S.) Circ 467 (1952).

