146           Chemistry 1997

ATP SYNTHESIS BY ROTARY CATALYSIS

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1997 
by
JOHN E. WALKER
The Medical Research Council Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Hills Road, 
Cambridge, CB2 2QH, U. K.


Biological energy comes from the sun. Light energy harvested by photosyn- 
thesis in chloroplasts and phototropic bacteria, becomes stored in carbo- 
hydrates and fats. This stored energy can be released by oxidative metabolism 
in the form of adenosine triphosphate (ATP), and used as fuel for other bio- 
logical processes. ATP is a high energy product of both photosynthesis and 
oxidative metabolism, and in textbooks, it is often referred to as the chemical 
currency of biological energy.
 In the 1960s and early 1970s, the field of oxidative metabolism was dom- 
inated by a debate about the nature of the intermediate between NADH (a 
key product from carbohydrate and fat metabolism) and ATP itself. Many bio- 
energeticists believed in and sought evidence for a high energy covalent 
chemical intermediate. The issue was resolved by Peter Mitchell, the Nobel 
Laureate in Chemistry in 1978. He established that in mitochondria, energy 
is released from NADH via the electron transport chain and used to generate 
a chemical potential gradient for protons across the inner membrane of the 
organelle. He referred to this gradient as the proton motive force (pmf; also 
designated as Al.tH_,) . It was demonstrated that the pmf is harnessed by the 
ATP synthesizing enzyme (ATP synthase) to drive the synthesis of ATP from 
ADP and inorganic phosphate, not only in mitochondria, but also in eubac- 
teria and chloroplasts [1].
 Because of Peter Mitchell's efforts, the pmf became established as a key in- 
termediate in biological energy conversion. In addition to being employed in 
ATP synthesis, it is also used by various membrane bound proteins to drive 
the transport of sugars, amino acids and other substrates and metabolites 
across biological membranes. The pmf powers the rotation of flagellae in 
motile bacteria. In newly born children and in hibernating animals, it is con- 
verted directly into heat by uncoupling the mitochondria in brown adipose 
tissue. Some bacteria that live in saline conditions generate a sodium motive 
force to act as an equivalent intermediate in their energy conversion proces- 
ses [2]. The general notion of creating a proton (or sodium) motive force 
and then using it as a source of energy for other biochemical functions is 
known as chemiosmosis.
 Today, the general outlines of chemiosmosis are well established. It is ac- 
cepted that during electron transport in mitochondria, redox energy derived 
from NADH is used by three proton pumping enzymes called complex I

               John E. Walker     147

(NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase), complex III (ubiquinone:cytochrome c 
oxidoreductase) and complex IV (cytochrome c oxidase). They act consecu- 
tively and produce the pmf by ejecting protons from the matrix (the inside) 
of the organelle (see Figure 1). Until recently, the workings of these 
chemiosmotic proton pumps was obscure, but currently our understanding is 
being transformed by the application of modern methods of molecular bio- 
logy for the analysis of their structures and functions. For example, two inde-  
pendent atomic resolution structures of cytochrome c oxidase isolated from 
bovine mitochondria [3, 4] and from the bacterium, Paracoccus denitrificans 
[5, 6], are guiding mutational and spectroscopic experiments that are provid- 
ing new insights into its mechanism. Partial structures of mitochondria' com- 
plex III from two different species [7] will have a similar impact soon on our 
understanding of that enzmye. Complex I, the third proton pump in mito- 
chondria, is an assembly of at least 43 different polypeptides in mammals, 
with a combined molecular mass in excess of 900,000 [8]. In addition, it has 
a non-covalently bound flavin mononucletide, and at least five iron-sulphur 
clusters that act as redox centres. A consequence of this extreme complexity 
is that the structural analysis of complex I is less advanced than those of com- 
plexes III and IV, although the general outline of the complex has been 
established by electron microscopy [9, 10].

THE ATP SYNTHASE
Since 1978, my colleagues and I have concentrated on analyzing the structure 
of the ATP synthase, another multisubunit complex from mitochondria, 
where it is found in the inner membrane alongside the three proton pump- 
ing enzymes (see Figure 1 ) . Similar complexes are found in chloroplast and 
eubacterial membranes. Throughout our endeavours, we have been motiva- 
ted by the expectation that detailed knowledge of its structure would lead to 
a deeper understanding of how ATP is made. A substantial part of our efforts 
has been directed at establishing the subunit compositions of the ATP syn- 
thesizing enzymes from various sources, and with determining the primary se- 
quences of the subunits [11-31]. These rather extensive analyses helped to 
show that the overall structure of the ATP synthase, and hence the general 
principles governing its operation, are very similar in mitochondria, chloro- 
plasts and eubacteria, although the enzymes from the various sources differ 
in the details of both their sequences and subunit compositions (see Table 1). 
It is also known that the ATPases from various sources differ in the mecha- 
nisms that regulate their catalytic activities [32].
 In 1962, the inside surface of the inner membranes of bovine heart mito- 
chondria was found by electron microscopic examination to be lined with 
mushroom shaped knobs about 100 A in diameter (Figure 2A) [33]. Later 
on, similar structures were found to be associated with the thylakoid mem- 
branes of chloroplasts (Figure 2B) [34], and with the inner membranes of 
eubacteria (Figure 2C). At the time of their discovery, the function of these 
membrane bound knobs was not known, but they were thought to be proba-

148                       Chemistry 1997


        Pi 4- H+    ADP
                          .4-1 subunit (301cD)


                        ATP














                               2H+    4H+
          ATP synthase      cyt aa3 cyt bc1     complex I
  Subunits    31             13       11           43
  kD         600             205      240         1,000
Figure 1. The enzyme complexes of oxidative phophorylation in the inner membranes of mam- 
malian mitochondria. Three proton pumps, complex I, complex III (cytochrome bc1) and com- 
plex IV (cytochrome aa3) convert redox energy in NADH into the proton motive force (pmf) by 
ejecting protons from the matrix of the mitochondrion. The ATP synthase uses the energy of the 
pmf to produce ATP from ADP and phosphate. ADP and phosphate are brought into the mito- 
chondrion by related proetin carriers. External ADP is exchanged for internal ATP, making the 
newly synthesized ATP available for many biological functions. Dotted lines indicate electron 
pathways. Q and C are the mobile electron carriers ubiquinone and cytochrome c, respectively.


Table 1. Equivalent subunits in ATP synthases in bacteria, ehloroplasts, and bovine mito- 
chondria

Type           Bacteria        Chloroplasts        Mitochondria

F1             cx              cc
               [3              [3                  13

               8               6                   OSCP
                                                   8

F0             a               a (or x)            a (or ATPase 6)
               b"              b and b' (or I and II)
               c               c (or III)
Supernumerary                                      F6
                                                   inhibitor 
                                                   A6L
               –               –                   d
               –               –                   e
               –               –                   f
                                                   g
a ATP synthases in E. coli and bacterium PS 3 (both eight-subunit enzymes) have two identical 
copies of subunit b per complex. Purple non-sulphur bacteria and cyanobacteria appear to 
have nine different subunits, the extra subunits (known as b') being a homologue of b. 
Similarly, chloroplast enzymes are made of nine non-identical subunits, and the chloroplast sub- 
units known as I and H are the homologues of b and b'.

                   John E. Walker         149




























































Figure 2. Knobs associated with biological membranes detected by electron microscopy in nega- 
tive stain. (A), Inside-out vesicles from bovine heart mitochondria; (13), thylakoid membranes 
form pea chloroplasts; (C), inside-out vesicles from E. roll. Different magnifications have been 
used in parts (A)—(C), and the knobs are all about IOU A in diameter. Reproduced with permis- 
sion from references [88, 89].

150               Chemistry 1997

bly important in biological energy conversion, and hence they were named 
"the fundamental particles of biology" [35]. In a brilliant series of biochem- 
ical reconstitution experiments conducted in the 1960s, Efraim Racker estab- 
lished that they were the ATP synthesizing enzyme complex (for example see 
references [36-38] , and hence that these early micrographs were the first 
glimpses of its structure.
 We now know that the head of the mushroom is a globular protein com- 
plex (known as the F1 domain), where the catalytic sites of the ATP synthase 
lie. The F1 part is attached to the membrane sector by a slender stalk about 
45 A long. The hydrophobic membrane domain (known as F.) transports 
protons back through the energized membrane into the matrix, somehow re- 
leasing energy in this process and making it available to drive ATP synthesis in 
the catalytic F1 domain. For some years, it has been accepted that three 
protons are transported back through the F. membrane sector for each ATP 
molecule that is formed in F1 [I]. However, recent experiments suggest that 
the chloroplast enzyme transports four protons through the membrane for 
each ATP that is made [39]. Therefore, it appears that either one or, less 
likely, both of these values of the H+:ATP ratio are incorrect, or that the 
mechanisms and structures of the mitochondrial and chloroplast enzymes 
differ significantly in their F. domains. This point will be elaborated later in a 
consideration of the possible structure and mechanism of F0.
 The general model of the mechanism of the ATP synthase that will be dev- 
eloped below is that the F. membrane domain contains a rotating molecular 
motor fuelled by the proton motive force. It is proposed that this motor is me- 
chanically coupled to the stalk region of the enzyme, and that the rotation of 
the stalk affects the catalytic domain and makes the three catalytic sites pass 
through a cycle of conformational states in which first, substrates are bound 
and sequestered, then second, ATP is formed from the sequestered sub- 
strates, and finally the newly synthesized ATP is released from the enzyme. 
This cycle of interconversion of the three catalytic sites is part of a binding 
change mechanism of ATP synthesis developed by Paul Boyer (see Figure 3)






        ADP+Pi      ENERGY

          1          2


Figure 3. An energy dependent binding change mechanism of ATP synthesis. The catalytic sites 
in the 0-subunits interact and interconvert between three forms: 0, open, site with very low affi- 
nity for substrates and catalytically inactive; L, loose site, loosely binding substrates and catalyti- 
cally inactive; T, tight site, tightly binding substrates and catalytically active. The proton induced 
conformational changes convert a T-site with bound ATP into an open site, releasing the bound 
nucleotide. Concomittantly, an L-site with loosely bound ADP and phosphate is converted to a T- 
site where substrates are bound and ATP froms. Fresh substrates bind to an 0-site converting it to 
an L-site, and so on. One third of the catalytic cycle is illustrated. Reproduced with permission 
from reference [40].

                        John E. Walker                 151


[40]. One of its basic tenets is that the energy requiring steps in this cycle of 
ATP synthesis are in the binding of substrates and in the release of products. 
This mechanism also implies that the ATP synthase must be an asymmetrical 
structure, and structural asymmetry is also implicit in the molar ratios of the 
subunits of F1-ATPase. Indeed, it is now clear from the asymmetrical features 
that are inherent in the enzyme's structure that there can be no structurally 
symmetrical states in the catalytic cycle.




THE STRUCTURE OF F1-ATPase

An important practical point about the ATP synthase complex that has influ- 
enced the strategy for analyzing its structure is that, as Racker had shown in 
the 1960s, the globular catalytic domain F1-ATPase can be detached from the 
membrane domain and studied separately in aqueous solution. Subsequently, 
Alan Senior and Harvey Penefsky purified the bovine F1 complex [41, 42] 
and Penefsky demonstrated that it is an assembly of five different kinds of 
polypeptides, which he called a, 13, 7, 8 and E [42]. Eventually, it was accepted 
that they were assembled in the complex in the molar ratios 3a:313:17:18:1E. 
Hence, each F1 particle is an assembly of nine polypeptides, and in the bovine 
heart enzyme, their combined molecular mass is about 371,000 (see Table 2).



Table 2. The subunits of bovine F1-ATPase
Subunit      MWt          Function

a            55,247       Nucleotide binding
P            51,705       Nucleotides, catalysis
7            30,141       Link to F.
8            15,065       Stalk
E             5,632       Stalk

a3133ylolel 371,694


  Both a- and 13-subunits bind nucleotides, and we now know that the cataly- 
tic nucleotide binding sites lie almost entirely within the 13-subunits (see 
Figure 4). The nucleotides bound to a-subunits remain associated during the 
catalytic cycle and do not participate directly in ATP synthesis. What they are 
doing remains mysterious, although both structural and regulatory functions 
have been suggested.
  In 1981, we found that the sequences of the a- and 13-subunits were related 
weakly through most of their length [12, 13], and Matti Saraste and I won- 
dered which regions of the sequences were contributing to the nucleotide 
binding sites. By examination of the known primary and atomic structures of 
adenylate kinase [43], and of the sequence of myosin from Caenorhabditis 
elegans (at the time unpublished information, made available to me by Jonathan 
Karn), we were able to propose that two short degenerate sequence motifs

152               Chemistry 1997



common to adenylate kinase, myosin and the a- and p-subunits, of F1-ATPase 

were involved in helping to form their nucleotide binding pockets [44].

  This proposal has had far greater consequences than we ever imagined at 

the time of its publication in 1982. Over the years, one of the two motifs (see







           ATP binding site of 13Tp







       R189       u-S344               8260




          NH         OH          0
            O NH2        [HO H)  0
                                 0
           NH2          H3N+      O

                               162 C>
                            HO    0      D256 

                                  0
                                         E192
                                  C> 
                                  0







                              CH3











                                 0 

                                F418

                           CF

                        OH

                              A421
                  N 
                  H
           F424
                       T425

Figure 4. The nucleotide binding site in the bTP-subunit of bovine FrATPase. Except for aTP- 
Arg373 and the main chain carbonyl and the side-chain of aTP-Ser344, all of the amino acids are 
in bTP. Residues 159-164 are part of the P-loop sequence. The ordered water molecule is poised 
for nucleophilic attack on the terminal phosphate and is activated by G1u188. As an incipient ne- 
gative charge develops on the terminal phosphate in a penta-coordinate transition state of ATP 
hydrolysis, it will be stabilized by the guanidinium of a-Arg 373. Reproduced with permission 
from reference [50] .

                  John E. Walker        153


Figure 5) has become established as a reliable indicator of the presence of 
purine nucleotide binding sites in proteins of known sequence, but of un- 
known biochemical function. One spectacular demonstration of its predictive 
value has been in the identification of members of the widely dispersed fam- 
ily of ABC (adenosine binding cassette) transport proteins [45], which 
includes the cystic fibrosis protein and multi-drug resistance proteins. 
Another early success was its help in the identification of the oncogene pro- 
tein p21 as a GTPase [46]. The atomic structure of F1-ATPase described be- 
low, has shown that, as in other proteins, the two sequence motifs describe 
amino acids that are involved in forming the phosphate binding region of its 
nucleotide binding sites. For this reason, one of the sequences is often refer- 
red to as the P-loop (phosphate binding loop) sequence [47] (see Figure 5).
 In the determination of the atomic structure of F1-ATPase from bovine 
heart mitochondria, the key problem that had to be solved was how to grow 
crystals of the protein complex that would diffract X-rays to appropriately 
high resolution. Crystals were obtained at the beginning of our efforts, but, as 
often happens, they diffracted X-rays rather poorly. Therefore, over a period



P-LOOP SEQUENCES IN Fi-ATPase





consensus           G X XX X      GK T

a     169-176       G DRQ T       GK T

      159-163       G GAGV        GK T

Figure 5. The phosphate binding loop sequence motif in the a- and 13-subunits of bovine 
F1-ATPase. In some purine binding sites, the final threonine is replaced by a serine residue.



of seven years, factors influencing crystal formation were studied systemati- 
cally, and the diffraction properties of the crystals were improved gradually. 
Eventually, suitable cystals were obtained in 1990. In retrospect, the impor- 
tant factors for obtaining these crystals were to use highly pure preparations 
of enzyme from which trace impurities had been eliminated, to remove en- 
dogenous bound nucleotides and to replace them with a non-hydrolyzable 
chemical analogue of ATP, namely 5'-adenylylimidodiphosphate (AMP-PNP) 
which has the effect of locking the complex in a unique conformation, and to 
grow the crystals in the presence of deuterium oxide instead of water. By ex- 
posing the crystals to X-rays at a synchrotron source, it was demonstrated that 
crystals of bovine F1-ATPase grown under these conditions diffracted to at 
least 2.8 A resolution [48, 49]. Drs. Rene Lutter and Rose Todd were key col- 
laborators during this critical period. At this point, for the first time the struc-

154            Chemistry 1997

tural analysis of F1-ATPase appeared to be a realistic possibility. Our chances 
of success with such a large protein complex were increased significantly by 
collaborating with Dr. Andrew Leslie, who is a professional protein crystallo- 
grapher. Together with him and a post-doctoral visitor, Dr. J. P. Abrahams, we 
were able to arrive at an atomic resolution structure [50] surprisingly rapidly, 
given the size of the complex, and the associated problems of collecting and 
processing the X-ray diffraction data.
 The structural model of bovine F1-ATPase contains 2,983 amino acids. 
Except for short disordered stretches at their N-terminals, the sequences of 
the a- and I3-subunits were traced in their entirety. Three a-helical segments 
of the y-subunit corresponding to residues 1-45, 73-90, and 209-272 were al- 
so built into the model. The segments linking these three segments are also 
disordered, as are the entire 8- and E-subunits (150 and 50 amino acids re- 
spectively). These disordered regions of the y-, 6- and E-subunits, comprising 
in total about 300 amino acids, probably lie beneath the a3133 sub-complex, 
where the y-subunit protrudes from the structure (the y-subunit is blue in 
Figures 6 and 7) . The protrusion is probably a vestige of the 45 A stalk that 
links the F1 and F. domains in the complete ATP synthase complex.
 The structural model shows that the three a-subunits and the three 13-sub- 
units are arranged in alternation around a sixfold axis of pseudo-symmetry 
provided by an a-helical structure in the single 'y-subunit (see Figures 6 and 
7). Despite the large excesses of AMP-PNP and ADP in the mother liquor sur- 
rounding the crystals, five, and not six, nucleotides are bound to each en- 
zyme complex. An AMP-PNP molecule is found in each a-subunit and a 
fourth one in one 13-subunit. An ADP molecule is bound to the second I3-sub- 
unit, and the third 13-subunit has no bound nucleotide at all. A comparison of 
the structures of the three chemically identical 13-subunits in the F1 complex 
provides an explanation. The two catalytic I3-subunits that have AMP-PNP and 
ADP bound to them (known as 13TP and (3Dp, respectively; see Figures 7b and 
7c) have different but rather similar conformations, whereas the structure of 
the third 13-subunit, to which no nucleotide has bound (known as RE; see 
Figure 7d), differs substantially from the other two, particularly in the central 
domain where the nucleotides are bound in 13TP and r3Dp. In 13E' the C-termi- 
nal half of this central domain, together with the bundle of six a-helices that 
form the C-terminal domain, have rotated away from the sixfold axis of 
pseudo-symmetry. This disruption of the central domain removes the capaci- 
ty of the 13E-subunit to bind nucleotides. Therefore, the crystal structure of 
F1-ATPase contains the asymmetry required by the binding change mecha- 
nism, and the three different conformations of the subunits 13E, 13TP and 13Dp 
could be interpreted as representing the "open", "loose" and "tight" states, 
respectively.
 More recent extensive crystallographic analyses of F1-ATPase with bound 
antibiotic inhibitors [51, 52], of enzyme occupied with ADP and ATP (K. 
Braig, M. Montgomery, A. G. W. Leslie and J. E. Walker, unpublished work), 
of enzyme inhibited by ADP and aluminium fluoride (K. Braig, I. Menz, M. 
Montgomery, A. G. W. Leslie and J. E. Walker, unpublished work), and of en-

                  John E. Walker          155












































Figure 6. The three-dimensional structure of bovine FrATPase shown in solid representation. 
The red, yellow and blue parts correspond to a-, 13- and 'y-subunits respecively. From top to bot- 
tom, respectively, the complex is viewed from above (towards the membrane in the intact ATP 
synthase), from the side, and from beneath.




zyme covalently inhibited with 4-chloro-7-nitrobenzofluorazan (G. Orriss, A. 
G. W. Leslie and J. E. Walker, unpublished work), leave little room for any 
doubt that the high resolution structure described above represents a state in 
the active cycle of the enzyme.
 The most exciting aspect of the structure is that it suggests a mechanism 
for interconverting the three catalytic subunits through the cycle of confor- 
mations required by the binding change mechanism. It appears from the 
structure (Figure 7) that the nucleotide binding properties of the three cata- 
lytic [3-subunits are modulated by the central a-helical structure in the i-sub-

156               Chemistry 1997








































Figure 7. The three-dimensional structure of bovine FrATPase shown in ribbon representation. 
The colour code for subunits is the same as used in Figure 6, and nucleotides are black, in a "ball- 
and-stick" representation. The axis of pseudo-symmetry is vertical. AMP-PNP is bound to the 
three a-subunits, and to the a-subunit defined as fl. Subunit 13,, has bound ADP and subunit 
BE has no associated nucleotide. Subunits aTP, aE and aDP occupy the same relative positions 
as the corresponding n-subunits, but are rotated by -60°. The relationships of the various a- and 
P-subunits to each other is summarized in the icon in the top left or right corner of parts 
(A)—(D). In parts (C)—(D), the shaded part of the icon shows which subunits are depicted. 
Subunit au contributes to the nucleotide binding site of [irp, and similarly for app and aE. 
Subunits a and y are numbered from 1-510 and 1-272, respectively. By convention, the fifth ami- 
no acid (serine) in subunit P is residue 1 and the first four amino acids (Ala.Ala.Gln.Ala) are re-  
ferred to as residues —1 to —4. The C-terminal amino acid is residue 478. (A) A view of the entire 
F, particle in which subunits aE and RE point towards the viewer, revealing the anti-parallel 
coiled-coil of the N- and C-terminal helices of the 'subunit through the open interface between 
them. The bar is 20 A long. (B) Subunits au, y and PDP from a similar viewpoint to (A), but ro- 
tated 180° about the axis of pseudo-symmetry. The N- and C-termini of the p- and y-subunit are 
shown. (C) Subunits aE, g and from a similar viewpoint to (A), but rotated by -60°. The aste- 
risk indicates an interaction of the loop containing the DELSEED sequence and the y-subunit. 
(D) Subunits aDP, y, and DE from a similar viewpoint to (A), but rotated by 60°. The arrow indi- 
cates the disruption of the (3-sheet in the nucleotide binding domain. PE_Asp 316, PE_Thr 318 and 
PE_Asp 323 in a loop of the nucleotide binding domain make H-bonds with residues 'y.Arg 254 
and yGln 255 from the C-terminal helix, 6 A below the hydrophobic sleeve. The asterisk indica- 
tes a loop that makes an interaction with the C-terminal part of the y-subunit. Reproduced with 
permission from reference [50].

               John E. Walker      157

unit. This structure is curved, and its coiled-coil region is likely to have ri- 
gidity. In the crystal structure, its curvature appears to be imposing the "open 
state" on the 0E-subunit by pushing against the C-terminal domain of the pro- 
tein, forcing the nucleotide binding domain to split and hinge outwards, 
thereby removing its nucleotide binding capacity. Therefore, by inspection of 
the model, the simplest way of interconverting the three conformations of 
I3-subunits would be to rotate this central a-helical structure. As it is rotated, 
the curvature of the 7-subunit moves away from the 0E conformation, allow- 
ing that subunit to close, progessively entrapping substrates and allowing ATP 
to form spontaneously. At the same time, the next I3-subunit will be progress- 
ively opened by the effect of the curvature of the 7-subunit, allowing the ATP 
that has already formed in its nucleotide binding site to be released.


EVIDENCE FOR A ROTARY MECHANISM IN ATP SYNTHASE
The suggestion that ATP synthesis involves the cyclic modulation of nucleo- 
tide binding properties of the three catalytic 13-subunits by rotation of the 7- 
subunit was attractive because it provided a reasonable structural basis for the 
binding change mechanism. However, the proposal was based upon the in- 
terpretation of a static atomic model, and there was no proof that the enzyme 
operated in this way in reality. Therefore, in the laboratories of Richard Cross,  
Rod Capaldi and Wolfgang Junge, various experiments were carried out to 
test the rotary hypothesis [53-55]. These experiments were all consistent with 
the rotary model, and they provided convincing evidence of the movement of 
the ysubunit through 90-240°, but conclusive proof of repeated net rotations 
through 360° was lacking.
 Early in 1997, clear evidence of continuous rotation of the y-subunit re- 
lative to the surrounding a303 subcomplex was provided by a spectacular ex- 
periment conducted at the Tokyo Institute of Technology by Masasuke 
Yoshida and colleagues [56]. The essence of this experiment (summarized in 
Figure 8) was to bind the a313371 sub-complex to a nickel coated glass surface 
in a unique orientation, by introducing the nickel binding sequence (histidi- 
ne)10 at the N-terminals of the 0-subunits. A cysteine residue, introduced by 
mutagenesis into the exposed tip of the 7-subunit, distal from the nickel sur- 
face, was biotinylated, thereby allowing a fluorescently labelled biotinylated 
actin filament to be attached via an intermediate streptavidin molecule, 
which has four biotin binding sites. The actin filaments were 1-3 tim long, 
and their ATP dependent anticlockwise rotation could be seen in a fluores- 
cence microscope. The rate of rotation was approximately once per second, 
about one fiftieth of the rate anticipated from the turnover number of the 
fully active enzyme. The reduced activity can be attributed to the load of the 
actin filament and to the absence of the 8- and E-subunits.
 In addition to its impact in providing direct visual proof of the rotation of 
the 'J+-subunit, one crucially important aspect of this experiment is that it es-  
tablishes the order of interconversion of the three conformations of 0-sub-

158              Chemistry 1997























        Coverslip coated with Ni-NTA
Figure 8. Experimental observation of the ATP-depenedent rotation of the '.subunit of the 
afiiy, sub-complex. For explanation, see the text. Reproduced with permission from reference 
[56).



units observed in the crystal structure. During ATP hydrolysis, the 13 DP sub- 
unit converts into the PE state, I3E changes to PTp and 13Tp changes to 13Dp. 
During ATP synthesis, it is reasonable to assume that the 7-subunit rotates in 
the opposite direction, and that the order of conformational changes in the 
(3-subunits is the reverse of those occurring during ATP hydrolysis.


GENERATION OF ROTATION BY PROTON TRANSPORT 
THROUGH THE Fo MEMBRANE DOMAIN

Once convincing evidence of rotation of the 7-subunit had been obtained, 
among the next questions for consideration were: how is rotation generated 
by proton transport through Fo, and what is the nature of the connections 
between the F1 and the F. domains? High resolution structure is likely to be 
crucial in providing clear answers to both questions, but as yet there is no 
such structure for either the Fo domain or the central stalk between F1 and 
F0, except for the ordered protrusion of the y-subunit. Structures of the iso- 
lated &subunit [57, 58] and of a fragment of subunit d [59] of the E. coli en- 
zyme have been established. The bacterial &subunit (equivalent to the bovine 
&subunit [60] ) probably interacts with the 7-protrusion, and the bacterial & 
subunit (equivalent of the bovine OSCP subunit [60] ) appears to interact 
with the N-terminal region of the a-subunits (vide infra) , but the precise loca- 
tions and functions of these proteins in ATP synthase are unclear.
 Despite the lack of a detailed structure of the F. domain, evidence about 
the arrangement of the membrane subunits is accumulating. The simplest F0

               John E. Walker      159

domain characterized so far is the one found in eubacterial enzymes exem- 
plified by E. coli. It has three constituent subunits named a, b and c assembled 
in the molar ratios a1b2c9_12 [61, 62]. The uncertainty in the number of c sub- 
units per complex is a consequence of the experimental difficulties associat- 
ed with making appropriate measurements. Secondary structural models for 
all three subunits have been advanced by interpretation of the sequences of 
the bacterial Fo subunits [63]. That of subunit a has been interpreted 
variously as indicating the presence of five, six or seven hydrophobic mem- 
brane spanning subunits in the protein, but recent experimental evidence in- 
dicates that the correct value is five [64] . In its C-terminal and in penultimate 
a-helices are found positively charged amino acids that are essential for a 
functional Fo. Subunit b is anchored in the membrane by a single N-terminal 
a-helix [65]. The remainder of this protein is highly charged and may form a 
homo-dimer by making a parallel a-helical coiled-coil. This polar extramem- 
brane region interacts with subunits in F1 [66]. The model of subunit c has 
two antiparallel transmembrane a-helices linked by an extra-membranous 
loop, and this has been shown by nmr studies to be the structure of the pro- 
tein in a chloroform-methanol solvent mixture [64] . Cysteine residues intro- 
duced by mutation into the loop region and into the tip of the 7-subunit form 
a disulphide link under oxidizing conditions, showing that in the intact en- 
zyme, these regions are either in contact (possibly transiently) or close to 
each other [67]. Similar kinds of experiment provide evidence of interactions 
between subunits e and c [68]. The most important feature of subunit c is the 
side chain carboxyl of an aspartate residue, which is buried in the membrane 
in the C-terminal a-helix. This carboxyl group is conserved throughout all 
known sequences of c-subunits, and it is required for transmembrane proton 
transport. [61, 63] Depending on the exact number of subunits c per com- 
plex, there are 9-12 such buried carboxyls in each ATP synthase complex.
 The mitochondrial ATP synthase complex contains subunits that are equi- 
valent to subunits a and c (see Table 1). Mitochondrial subunit b is also prob- 
ably the equivalent of its bacterial homonym, although it appears to have two 
anti-parallel transmembrane a-helices at its N-terminus, rather than one, and 
there is only one b-subunit per enzyme complex. Presumably the role of the 
second b-subunit in the bacterial complex is performed by other subunits 
that are unique to the mitochondrial complex (for example subunits d and 
F6), but such matters will only become clear when more detailed structural 
evidence becomes available for both bacterial and mitochondrial enzymes. 
Nonetheless, the bacterial and mitochondrial Fo domains have many features 
in common, and it is highly probable that they operate by very similar me- 
chanisms.
 Models have also been advanced about the association of the F0 subunits in 
the membrane domain. One such model suggests that the c-subunits form a 
ring by interactions though their C-terminal a-helices, with the N-terminal a- 
helices outside the ring [69], and annular structures of c-subunits have been 
visualized by atomic force microscopy [70, 71] . Some preliminary experi- 
mental evidence of this arrangement has also been obtained by formation of

160               Chemistry 1997

disulphide cross links after introduction of cysteine residues at appropriate 
sites (N. J. Glavas &J. E. Walker, unpublished work). In addition, the atomic 
force microscopy images indicate that the b-subunits are placed peripheral to 
a ring of c-subunits [71]. Currently, there is no experimental evidence that 
shows whether the a subunit lies outside or within the c-annulus.
  Wolfgang Junge has proposed a model of how proton transport through F() 
might generate a rotary motion [72] (see Figure 9). The essence of this hy- 
pothetical rotary motor is that the essential carboxyls in the c subunits are ar- 
ranged around the external circumference of the c-annulus. Part of the ex- 
ternal surface of the annulus interacts with subunit a, and in this region the 
carboxyls are negatively charged. It is envisaged that subunit a has an inlet 
port on the external surface of the membrane which allows a proton to neu- 
tralize one of the negatively charged carboxylates. The resulting un-ionized 
carboxyl will find its way by thermal vibrations to its preferred environment in 
contact with the phospholipid bilayer. The neutralization of this carboxylate 
at one point of the circumference is accompanied by re-ionization of another 
one further around the circumference of the c-annulus, by release of the pro- 
ton on the opposite side of the membrane via an exit port in subunit a, and 
regeneration of a negative charge in the c-annulus:subunit a interface. These 
protonation-deprotonation events result in a rotary movement of the c-annu- 
lus. The rotation brings the next negatively charged carboxyl to the inlet port









 la subunit                       12c subunits
















                                After W. Junge
              H±
Figure 9. A hypothetical model for generation of rotation by proton transport through the F. do- 
main of ATP synthase. The central cylindrical part is made of c-subunits, the external curved 
structure is the single a subunit. The heavy black line indicates the path of the protons. For 
further explanation, see the text.

