                Walter Kohn        213

ELECTRONIC STRUCTURE OF MATTER - WAVE 
FUNCTIONS AND DENSITY FUNCTIONALS

Nobel Lecture, January 28, 1999 
by
WALTER KOHN
Department of Physics, University of California, Santa Barbara, CA 93106- 
9530, USA


I. INTRODUCTION
The citation for my share of the 1998 Nobel Prize in chemistry refers to the 
"development of the density functional theory". The initial work on Density 
Functional Theory (DFT) was reported in two publications: the first with 
Pierre Hohenberg in 1964111 and the next with Lu J. Sharn[21 in 1965. This 
was almost 40 years after E. Schroedinger[31 published his first epoch-making 
paper marking the beginning of wave-mechanics. The Thomas-Fermi theory, 
the most rudimentary form of DFT, was put forward shortly afterwardsR 51 
and received only modest attention.
 There is an oral tradition that, shortly after Schroedinger's equation for the 
electronic wave-function had been put forward and spectacularly validated 
for simple small systems like He and H2, P.M. Dirac declared that chemistry 
had come to an end — its content was entirely contained in that powerful 
equation. Too bad, he is said to have added, that in almost all cases, this equa- 
tion was far too complex to allow solution.
 In the intervening more than six decades enormous progress has been 
made in finding approximate solutions of Schroedinger's wave equation for 
systems with several electrons, decisively aided by modern electronic com- 
puters. The outstanding contributions of my Nobel Prize co-winner John 
Pople are in this area. The main objective of the present account is to ex- 
plicate DFT, which is an alternative approach to the theory of electronic 
structure, in which the electron density distribution n(r), rather than the 
many electron wavefunction plays a central role. I felt that it would be useful 
to do this in a comparative context; hence the wording "Wavefunctions and 
Density Functionals" in the title.
 In my view DFT makes two kinds of contribution to the science of multi- 
particle quantum systems, including problems of electronic structure of 
molecules and of condensed matter:
 The first is in the area of fundamental understanding. Theoretical chemists 
and physicists, following the path of the Schroedinger equation, have become 
accustomed to think in a truncated Hilbert space of single particle orbitals. The 
spectacular advances achieved in this way attest to the fruitfulness of this per- 
spective. However, when high accuracy is required, so many Slater deter-

214            Chemistry 1998

minants are required (in some calculations up to — 101) that comprehension be- 
comes difficult. DFT provides a complementary perspective. It focuses on 
quantities in the real, 3-dimensional coordinate space, principally on the 
electron density n(r) of the groundstate. Other quantities of great interest 
are: the exchange correlation hole density nxe(r,r1) which describes how the 
presence of an electron at the point r depletes the total density of the other 
electrons at the point r; and the linear response function, x(r,r';c)), which de- 
scribes the change of total density at the point r due to a perturbing potential 
at the point r', with frequency co. These quantities are physical, independent of 
representation, and easily visualisable even for very large systems. Their un- 
derstanding provides transparent and complementary insight into the nature 
of multiparticle systems.
 The second contribution is practical. Traditional multiparticle wavefunc- 
tion methods when applied to systems of many particles encounter what I call 
an exponential wall when the number of atoms, N, exceeds a critical value 
which, for "chemical accuracy", currently is in the neighborhood of No 10 
(to within a factor of about 2) for a system without symmetries. A major im- 
provement along present lines in the analytical and/or computational aspects 
of these methods will lead to only modest increases in No. Consequently, 
problems requiring the simultaneous consideration of very many interacting 
atoms, N/No >> 1, such as large organic molecules, molecules in solution, 
drugs, DNA, etc. overtax these methods. On the other hand, in DFT, comput- 
ing time T rises much more moderately with the number of atoms, currently 
as T Na with a 2-3, with ongoing progress in bringing a down towards a
 1 (so-called linear scaling). The current state of the art of applied DFT can 
handle systems with up to N = 0(102)-0(103) atoms.
 The following figures and legends illustrate what can currently be achiev- 
ed. In these examples the number of atoms is 0(102) and the number of elec- 
trons several times larger.
 In Section 1, I shall talk about traditional wavefunction methods and con- 
trast their great success for few-atom systems with their fundamental limita- 
tions in dealing with very-many-atom systems.
 Section 2 deals with DFT against the backdrop of wavefunction methods. 
The basic theory is summarized: First the original Hohenberg-Kohn (HK) 
variational principle, where n(r) is the variational variable, is described. This 
is followed by the Kohn-Sham (KS) self-consistent single-particle equations 
which involve the well-defined exchange — correlation functional, Exjn(r)]. 
In principle, when used with the exact Exc, these single particle equations in- 
corporate all many-body effects.'
 Next the physics of Exc[n(r)] is discussed in terms of the concept of the ex- 
change correlation hole nx,(r,r'). I have found the concept of "nearsighted- 
ness" useful which, in the present context, says that the exchange correlation 
hole nx,(r,r) for an electron at the point r is largely determined by p —
whereµ is the chemical potential and velf (i) is the effective single particle

' It is however known that for some density distributions Exc[n(r)] cannot be defined

                    Walter Kohn             215



































Figure I. Methanol inside a cage of the zeolite sodalite. Zeolites are crystalline arrays of cages 
built of silicon (blue), aluminum (yellow), and oxygen (red) atoms. For each Al atom one must 
have a positive counter-ion (in this case 14+ (white)). A methanol molecule is inside the cage (car- 
bon is green) where it can react with the proton. DFT calculations have assigned and clarified the 
IR spectra, have determined the binding sites of methanol, and have calculated the activation 
energy for the reaction. Acid catalysis in zeolites is widely used in the chemical industry. (After E. 
Nusterer, P. Bloechl and Karlheinz Schwarz, Angew. Chem. 35, 175).


potential for r near r. Although nearsightedness becomes a well defined con- 
cept only for metallic systems which are very large, it has been found to be 
useful also for systems as small as a single atom.
 There follows a brief discussion of approximations for Exe which reflect 
nearsightedness, and other general principles.
 Parts III-V discuss applications of DFT to electronic groundstates, as well as 
a host of generalizations to other electronic and non-electronic systems. 
 Finally a few concluding remarks and speculations are offered.


II. SCHROEDINGER WAVEFUNCTIONS — FEW VERSUS MANY 
ELECTRONS

The foundation of the theory of electronic structure of matter is the non- 
relativistic Schroedinger equation for the many-electron wavefunction

216                               Chemistry 1998















































Figure 2. The geometric structure of the clathrate Sr,Gai,Ge„ (Sr red, Ga blue, Ge white) and its 
charge density in a plane bisecting the centers of the cages. DFT calculations have shown that the 
Sr atoms are weakly bound and scatter phonons effectively, thereby, lowering thermal conducti- 
vity. However, contrary to intuitive expectations, the Sr atoms do not donate electrons to the 
frame and are practically neutral. Conductivity is due to electrons traveling through the frame, 
not through the one-dimensional Sr "wires" in the structure; there is thus little scattering of con- 
duction electrons, by Sr vibrations. For these reasons, the compound is a metal with a large 
Seebeck coefficient (unlike ordinary metals). The calculation suggests that other compounds of 
this type may be even better thermoelectrics. (Theory by N.P. Blake and H. Metiu, submitted for 
publication).



           h2                    Ze2         1          e2
       {- 2m ./E 02   •           -       +  2 j     ri — I              = 0, (2.1)

where r. are the positions of the electrons and R1, Z1 the positions and atomic 
numbers of the nuclei; 11, m and e are the conventional fundamental con- 
stants; and E is the energy. This equation reflects the Born-Oppenheimer ap- 
proximation, in which — for purposes of studying electron-dynamics — the 
much heavier nuclei are considered as fixed in space. This paper will deal 
largely with non-degenerate groundstates. The wavefunction 4' depends on 
the positions and spins of the N electrons but in this paper spins will general- 
ly not be explicitly indicated. Thus

                      Waller Kohn             217




























Figure 3. Fully Hydroxylated Aluminum (0001) Surface. (Red-O; blue-interior Al; grey-H-atoms; 
the green lines are H-bonds). Each surface Al-atom in Al20, has been replaced by 3 H-atoms. The 
figure represents a superposition of configurations in a molecular dynamics simulation at regu- 
lar intervals of 1 ps. These calculations help to understand the complex dynamics of water ad- 
sorption on aluminum (KG. Haas el al., Science 282, 265 (1998)).



                   =        rAr )            (2.2)
The Pauli principle requires that

                                             (2.3)
where P.., permutes the space and spin coordinates of electrons j and j'. All 
physical properties of the electrons depend parametrically on the R1 , in par- 
ticular the density n(r) and total energy E which play key roles in this paper:

                n(r) = n(r; R1, ,            (2.4)


                 E =           ,             (2.5) 

where .1\1 is the number of nuclei.

A. Few Electron Systems—the H2 Molecule
The first demonstrations of the power of the Schroedinger equation in chem- 
istry were calculations of the properties of the simplest multielectron mole- 
cule, H2: Its experimental binding energy2 and internuclear separation are

'This is the observed dissociation energy plus the zero point energy of 0.27 eV.

218                            Chemistry 1998

                         xp : D = 4.75eV, R = 0.740 AA.                 (2.6)
The earliest quantum theoretical estimate was made by Heitler and London 
in 1927161, who used the Ansatz
         IIL - A [coH(rl — R1)(pH(r2 — R2) + (pit(rl — R2)(PH(r2 — Ri)] X0 , (2.7)
where cpH(7-1 — R1) is the orbital wavefunction of electron 1 in its atomic 
groundstate around a proton located at R1, etc; denotes the spin singlet 
function; and A is the normalization. The components of this wavefunction 
describe two hydrogen atoms, at R1 and R2, with spins pointing in opposite di- 
rections. The combination satisfies the reflection symmetry of the molecule 
and the Pauli principle. The expectation value of the Hamiltonian as a func- 
tion of R=1R1— R2 I was calculated. Its minimum was found to occur at R= 
0.87A, and the calculated dissociation energy was 3.14eV, in semiquantitative 
agreement with experiment. However the errors were far too great for the 
typical chemical requirements of 16 R 0.01 A and Is D 0.1 eV.
   An alternative Ansatz, analogous to that adopted by Bloch for crystal elec- 
trons, was made by Mullikan in 1928E71:
                    * BM = (Pmol(r1)(00mol(r2) • X0 7                   (2.8) 
where
             ciomot(ri) = (49H(ri — R1) + 401/(ri - R2))                (2.9)
and A' is the appropriate normalization constant. In this function both elec- 
trons occupy the same molecular orbital cp.oi(r). The spin function xo is again 
the antisymmetric singlet function. The results obtained with this function 
were R= 0.76 A, and D = 2.65eV, again in semiquantitative agreement with ex- 
periment.
   The Mullikan Ansatz can be regarded as the simplest version of a more 
general, so-called Hartree-Fock Ansatz, the Slater determinant

              UHF = —2112Det I (pm(ri)a(1)(pm(r2)0(2)                  (2.10)

where cp.(r) is a general molecular orbital and a and J3 denote up and down 
spin functions. For given R-a IR,— R2 I , minimization with respect to (p.(r) of 
the expectation value of H leads to the non-local Hartree Fock equationsE81 
for the molecular orbital cp.( r), whose solution gives the following results: 
R= 0.74 A, D = 3.63eV.
   The most complete early study of H2 was undertaken by James and 
Coolidge in 1933[91. They made the very general variational Ansatz

                            111 JC = W(ri, r2)Xo ,                     (2.11)
where T(r1,r2) is a general, normalized function of r1 and r2, symmetric under 
interchange of 7-1 and r2 and respecting the spatial symmetries of the mole- 
cule. The trial function was written as depending on a number of parame-

                                                                  Walter Kohn                                                                   219


ters, p1,p2...pm, so that for given IR1 — R2 I , the expectation value of the 
Schroedinger Hamiltonian in 111, an upper bound to the true groundstate 
energy, became a function of the parameters pi, E = m). The calcula- 
tions were made with M up to 13. Minimization of E(A,...,pm) with respect to 
the p. resulted in R = 0.740 A and D = 4.70 eV, in very good agreement with 
experiment. More recent variational calculations of the same general charac- 
ter give theoretical results whose errors are estimated to be much smaller 
than experimental uncertainties, and other theoretical corrections.
    Before leaving the variational calculation for 112, we want to make a very 
rough "guesstimate" of the number of parameters M needed for a satisfactory 
result.
    The number of continuous variables of T(r10-2) is 6 — 1 = 5, the reduction 
by 1 reflecting axial symmetry. Let us call the number of parameter per vari- 
able needed for the desired accuracy p. Since a fractional accuracy of 0(10-2) 
is needed for the energy, implying a fractional accuracy of 0(10-1) in 4', we 
guess that 3 << p « 10. Hence M = p5 = 35 - 105, 102 — 105.
    By using symmetries and chemical and mathematical insights, this number 
can be significantly reduced. Such relatively modest numbers are very manag- 
able on today's (and even yesterday's) computers.
    It is thus not surprising that for sufficiently small molecules, wavefunction 
methods give excellent results.


B. Many Electrons — Encountering an Exponential Wall
In the same spirit as our last "guesstimates" for H2, let us now consider a ge- 
neral molecule consisting of N atoms with a total of N interacting electrons, 
where N >> 10 say. We ignore symmetries and spin, which will not affect our 
general conclusions. Reasoning as before, we see that the number M of para- 
meter required is
                                                 m p3N 3 < p < 10.                                                                         (2.12)

The energy needs to be minimized in the space of these M parameters. Call 
M the maximum value feasible with the best available computer software and 
hardware; and N the corresponding maximum number of electrons. Then, 
from Eq. (2.12) we find

                                                             s = 1 logA-213 logp                                                           (2.13)

Let us optimistically take M 109 and p = 3. This gives the shocking result

                                                      -          1 9
                                                    N-3 0.48 = 6(!) .                                                                      (2.14)


In practice, by being "clever", one can do better than this, perhaps by one 
half order of magnitude, up to say'R t; 20. But the exponential in Eq. (2.12) 
represents a "wall" severely limiting N.
    Let us turn this question around and ask what is the needed M for N= 100. 
By Eq. (2.12) and taking p = 3 we find

 220                 Chemistry 1998

                   Al Re, 3300 Re, io"°(!)      (2.15)
I cannot foresee an advance in computer science which can minimize a quan- 
tity in a space of 10150 dimensions. Of course, estimates like Eq. (2.15) are 
very rough and only their logarithm should be taken seriously. But the "ex- 
ponential wall" is real and reflects the interconnectedness of kV (rp...,rN) in the 
3Ndimensional configuration space defined by the requirement that all r be 
inside the 3D region containing the molecule.
  We conclude that traditional wavefunction methods, which provide the "re- 
quired" chemical accuracy are generally limited to molecules with a small 
total number of chemically active electrons, N< 0(10).


C. Some Meta-physical-chemical Considerations
The following remarks are related to a very old paper by one of my teachers, 
J.H. Van Vleck,1111 in which he discusses a problem with many-body wavefunc- 
tions, later referred to as the Van Vleck catastrophy.
  I begin with a provocative statement. In general the many-electron wavefunction 
  ( ,...,rN) for a system of N electrons is not a legitimate scientific concept, when N 
No, where No 103.
  I will use two criteria for defining "legitimacy": a) That can be calculated 
with sufficient accuracy and b) can be recorded with sufficient accuracy.

Construction of an accurate approximation to W. 
Without leaving the context of wavefunctions, I shall call the approximate 
wavefunction 'I' sufficiently accurate if

                       110 12» 0.5 ,            (2.16)

a rather liberal requirement. (One could equally well choose 0.9 or 0.1).
  Consider now the example of N' non-overlapping identical n-electron mo- 
lecules with exact wave-functions and approximate wave-functions 
 i(rp...,rn). Let us take n = 10 and posit that a very accurate can be calculat- 
ed with

             (1t, 711) 1= 1 - E where c =10-2 , (2.17)
again a liberal estimate.
  Then, for an N'-molecule system with N' 102, and thus N= 103 electrons 
   tF) = (1 — 6)N' e-1 '& 0.37, i.e., almost acceptable by the criterion
(2.16). Note however, that for N = 104, (til, IF) cio 5 x 10-5 so that 
NI, 'If - 3 x 10-9(?) — the exponential wall is again there, in another form. 
For fully interacting systems the situation is much worse and our estimate of 
No z, 103 is probably much too high.
  Can this problem ever be overcome along present lines of thought? I think 
not. Even if there were no computational limits, other physical effects, such as

                Walter Kohn        221

relativistic or radiative corrections which may be minor for systems of small N 
exponentiate when N exceeds N.
 (It is obvious that the estimates made above have only logarithmic validity).

Recording of W ( ri1-2,...,r
Let us now assume that somehow we have obtained an accurate approxima- 
tion to 'P, in the sense of Eq (2.16), and wish to record it so it can be repro- 
duced at a later time. How many bits are needed? Let us take q bits per varia- 
ble. Then the total number of bits is
                 B = r            (2.18)
For q= 3, a very rough fit, and N= 103, B = 101500, a quite unrealistic number. 
(The total number of baryons in the accessible universe is estimated as 108°1).
 Having attempted to discredit the very-many-electron wavefunction 
111(r1,...,rN), for many electrons I must, of course, recall two well-known facts: 
physically/chemically interesting quantities, like total energy E, density n(r), 
pair correlation function g(r,r1), etc. depend on only very few variables and, 
formally, can be thought of as obtained by tracing over all other variables, e.g.

   n(r) = N I kV (r, r2, ..., rN)111(r, r2, ..., rN)dr2...drN ; (2.19)
and that some T's which, by the criterion (1.16) are hopelessly "bad" for 
large N, give respectable and even very accurate results for these contracted 
quantities. Of course not every bad trial-'1` will give good results for these 
quantities, and the question of how one discriminates the useful "bad" kii, 
from the vast majority of useless "bad" kr-i's requires much further thought. 
This issue is related, I believe, to the concept of "nearsightedness" which I 
have recently suggested[ml.
 In concluding this section I remark that DFT, while derived from the N-par- 
ticle Schroedinger equation, is finally expressed entirely in terms of the den- 
sity n(r), in the Hohenberg-Kohn formulation,Ell and in terms of n(r) and 
single-particle wavefunctions 4)(r), in the Kohn-Sham formulation [21. This is 
why it has been most useful for systems of very many electrons where wave- 
function methods encounter and are stopped by the "exponential wall".

III. DENSITY FUNCTIONAL THEORY—BACKGROUND
In the fall of 1963, I was spending a sabbatical semester at the Ecole Normale 
Superieure in the spacious office of Philippe Nozieres. A few weeks after my 
arrival Pierre Hohenberg, also a visitor from the US, joined forces with me. 
Ever since my period at the Carnegie Institute of Technology (1950-1959) I 
had been interested in disordered metallic alloys, partly because of the excel- 
lent metallurgy department and partly because of the interesting experimen- 
tal program of Emerson Pugh, in Physics, on substitutional alloys of Cu with 
the adjacent elements in the periodic table, such as CuxZni_x. These alloys were 
viewed in two rather contradictory ways: As an average periodic crystal with

222                 Chemistry 1998


non-integral atomic number Z = xZ1 + (1—x) Z2(Zi = 29, Z2 = 30). This model 
nicely explained the linear dependence of the electronic specific heat on x. 
On the other hand the low temperature resistance is roughly proportional to 
x(1—x), reflecting the degree of disorder among the two constituents. While 
isolated Cu and Zn atoms are, of course, neutral, in a Cu—Zn alloy there is 
transfer of charge between Cu and Zn unit cells on account of their chemical 
differences. The electrostatic interaction energy of these charges is an im- 
portant part of the total energy. Thus in considering the energetics of this 
system there was a natural emphasis on the electron density distribution n(r).
 Now a very crude theory of electronic energy in terms of the electron den- 
sity distribution, n(r), the Thomas-Fermi (TF) theory, had existed since the 
1920sE41 [53. It was quite useful for describing some qualitative trends, e.g. for 
total energies of atoms, but for questions of chemistry and materials science, 
which involve valence electrons, it was of almost no use; for example it did 
not lead to any chemical binding. However the theory had one feature which 
interested me: It considered interacting electrons moving in an external po- 
tential v(r), and provided a highly over-simplified one-to-one implicit relation 
between v(r) and the density distribution n(r):

                                    1 2m 
       n(r) =     veff (0)3/2 (7 = 3r2(V)32)'   (3.1)



             veff(r) = v(r) + n(r') dr'         (3.2)
                          J I r — r' I

where p is the r-independent chemical potential; Eq. (3.1) is based on the ex- 
pression

                   n = 7(p, — 03/2              (3.3)

for the density of a uniform, non-interacting, degenerate electron gas in a con- 
stant external potential v; and the second term in (3.2) is just the classically 
computed electrostatic potential times (-1), generated by the electron densi- 
ty distribution n(?). Since Eq. (3.1) ignores gradients of veff(r) it was clear that 
the theory would apply best for systems of slowly varying density.
 In subsequent years various refinements (gradient-, exchange-and correla- 
tion corrections) were introduced, but the theory did not become signifi- 
cantly more useful for applications to the electronic structure of matter. It was 
clear that TF theory was a rough representation of the exact solution of the 
many-electron Schroedinger equation, but since TF theory was expressed in 
terms of n(r) and Schroedinger theory in term of W(r1,...,rN), it was not clear 
how to establish a strict connection between them.
 This raised a general question in my mind: Is a complete, exact description of 
groundstate electronic structure in terms of n(r) possible in principle. A key 
question was whether the density n(r) completely characterized the system. It 
was true in TF theory, where n(r), substituted in Eq. (3.1) yields, (veff(r) — 
and, by (3.2), ( v(r) — p). In addition, n(r) also yields the total number of elec-

                            Walter Kohn                     223

trons by integration. Thus the physical system is completely specified by n(r). 
It was also simple to check that the same was true for any 1-particle system, as 
well as for a weakly perturbed, interacting, uniform electron gas
                 v(r) = vo  Avi (7-) (A << 1) ,           (3.4)


                   n(r) = n0 + Ani(r) +    ,              (3.5)
for which v1(r) can be explicitly calculated in term of n1(r) by means of the 
wave-number-dependent susceptibility of the uniform gas. This suggested the 
hypothesis that a knowledge of the groundstate density of n(r) for any electronic 
system, (with or without interactions) uniquely determines the system. This hypothesis 
became the starting point of modern DFT.

IV. THE HOHENBERG-KOHN FORMULATION OF DENSITY 
FUNCTIONAL THEORY
A. The Density n(r) as the Basic Variable
The Basic Lemma of HK. The groundstate density n(r) of a bound system of 
interacting electrons in some external potential v(r) determines this potenti- 
al uniquelytn.

Remarks:
(1) The term "uniquely" means here up to an uninteresting additive con- 
   stant.
(2) In the case of a degenerate groundstate, the lemma refers to any ground- 
   state density n(r).
(3) This lemma is mathematically rigorous.
  The proof is very simple. We present it for a non-degenerate groundstate.
  Let n(r) be the non-degenerate groundstate density of N electrons in the 
potential v1 (r), corresponding to the groundstate T1, and the energy El. 
Then,
     Ei = 0111,         f vi(r)n(r)dr        (T + U)411) , (4.1)

where H1 is the total Hamiltonian corresponding to v1, and T and U are the 
kinetic and interaction energy operators. Now assume that there exists a 
second potential v2(r), not equal to vl (r) + constant, with groundstate 'F2, 
necessarily which gives rise to the same n(r). Then

           E2 =f v2(r)n(r)dr + f (T2, (T U)W2).           (4.2)

Since Ti is assumed to be non-degenerate, the Rayleigh-Ritz minimal prin- 
ciple for 'P1 gives the inequality,

224                          Chemistry 1998


       E1 < 2, HOF 2) = f vi(r)n(r)dr (412, (T +                2)

                           = E2 f (Vi        — v2(r))n(r)dr.         (4.3)

Similarly
        E2 < (W1, 11411) =            (v2 (r) — vi(ri))n(r)dr        (4.4)

where we use 5 since the non-degeneracy of qI2 was not assumed. Adding 
(4.3) and (4.4) leads to the contradiction
                         El +E2 <E1 + E2"                            (4.5)
We conclude by reductivo ad absurdum that the assumption of the existence of 
a second potential v2(r), which is unequal to v1(r) + constant and gives the 
same n(r), must be wrong. The lemma is thus proved for a non-degenerate 
groundstate.
  Since n(r) determines both Nand v(r) (ignoring an irrelevant additive con- 
stant) it gives us the full H and N for the electronic system. Hence n(r) 
determines implicitly all properties derivable from H through the solution of 
the time-independent or time-dependent Schroedinger equation (even in 
the presence of additional perturbations like electromagnetic fields), such as: 
the many-body eigenstates qi(1)(r1,...,rN), ... the 2-particle 
Green's function G(r1t1, r2t2), the frequency dependent electric polarizability 
a(w), and so on. We repeat that all this information is implicit in n(r), the 
groundstate density.

Remarks:
1. The requirement of non-degeneracy can easily be liftedr121.
2. Of course the lemma remains valid for the special case of non-interacting 
  electrons.
3. Lastly we come to the question whether any well-behaved positive function 
  n(r), which integrates to a positive integer N, is a possible groundstate den- 
  sity corresponding to some v(r). Such a density is called v-representable 
  (VR). On the positive side it is easy to verify that, in powers of k, any near- 
  ly uniform, real density of the form n(r) = no + XE n(q)eig.r is VR, and that 
  for a single particle any normalized density n(r) = (r) is also VR. On 
  the other hand Levy[131 and Lieb [14] have shown by an example which in- 
  volves degenerate groundstates, that there do exist well-behaved densities 
  which are not VR. The topology of the regions of v-representability in the 
  abstract space of all n(r) continues to be studied. But this issue has so far 
  not appeared as a limitation in practical applications of DFT.

B. The Hohenberg-Kohn Variational Principle
The most important property of an electronic groundstate is its energy E. By 
wavefunction methods E could be calculated either by direct approximate

                      Walter Kohn              225

solution of the Schroedinger Equation HT = PP or from the Rayleigh Ritz 
minimal principle,

                 E = min,- , 1140 ,           (4.6)

where is a normalized trial function for the given number of electrons, N.
  The formulation of the minimal principle in terms of trial densities, n(r), 
rather than trial wavefunctions was first presented in ref. 1. Here we shall 
follow the more succinct derivation due to Levy113J and Liebr141, called the 
constrained search method.
  Every trial function corresponds to a trial density n(r) obtained by inte- 
grating c-fi* qi over all variables except the first and multiplying by N. One may 
carry out the minimization of (4.6) in two stages. First fix a trial it(r) and 
denote by 'It?, the class of trial functions with this n. We define the constrain- 
ed energy minimum, with n(r) fixed, as

           Ev[ii (0]       Hiff".„)

                    fv(r)ii(r)dr + F[ii(r)],  (4.7)
where

          F[n(r)] minc,(4-1(r), (T U)x11(0) . (4.8)

F[fi (r)] requires no explicit knowledge of v(r). It is a universal functional of 
the density ii(r), (whether the latter is VR or not). In the second step mini- 
mize (4.7) over all

  E = minn(r)Ev[n(r)] = minfi(of f v(r)i-i(r)dr + F[fi(r)]} . (4.9)

For a non-degenerate groundstate, the minimum is attained when n(r) is the 
groundstate density; and, for the case of a degenerate groundstate, when 
n(r) is any one of the groundstate densities. The HK minimum prin- 
ciple (4.9) may be considered as the formal exactification of Thomas-Fermi 
theory.
  The formidable problem of finding the minimum of ('', H CP) with respect 
to the 3N-dimensional trial function qf has been transformed into the seem- 
ingly trivial problem of finding the minimum of E jii(r)] with respect to the 3- 
dimensional trial function n(r).
  Actually the definition (4.8) of F[n(r)] leads us right back to minimization 
with respect to 3N-dimensional trial wavefunctions. Nevertheless, significant 
formal progress has been made: the strict formulation of the problem of ground- 
state densities and energies entirely in terms of the density distribution n(r) 
and of a well-defined, though, not explicitly known, functional of the density, 
F [ii(r)], which represents the sum of kinetic energy and interaction energy 
(T+ n, associated with n (see Eq. (4.8)).

226                                                                                                                                            Chemistry 1998

           One can now easily re-derive the Thomas-Fermi (TF) theory by making the 
approximations

                                                                                                           T =f n(r)i3ok2F(n(r))dr,                                                                                                                                                                                                        (4.10) 


                                                                                                               U                                         1 n(r)n(r') drdr' , r_ril                                                                                                                                                         (4.11)
where kF(n) is the Fermi wave-vector of a uniform electron gas of density n 
and 1-10 kF2(n) is the mean kinetic energy per electron of such a gas. The ex- 
pression for U is the classical (or mean field) approximation. Various pre- 
viously known corrections, of TF theory for exchange, correlation and densi- 
ty gradients can also be easily re-derived.
           The main remaining error is due to the seriously inadequate representa- 
tion of the kinetic energy, T, by Eq. (4.10) or its gradient-corrected forms. 
This deficiency is largely remedied by the self-consistent, so-called Kohn- 
Sham equations, discussed in the following Section 4C.
           A second interesting class of systems n(r) = no + n1(r), where n1(r) << no, 
could also be treated using the no                                                                                                                                                                                        density-density response func-
tion, K( I r—                                                            I).

C. The Self Consistent Kohn-Sham Equations
Soon after the publication of the TF theory, Hartreer81 proposed a set of self- 
consistent single particle equations for the approximate description of the 
electronic structure of atoms[81. The concept was physically very simple. Every 
electron was regarded as moving in an effective single particle potential
                                                                                             vil(r)+Z                                                    r                             f n(r')    Ir—r')                                                                                                                                   (4.12)
where the first term represents the potential due to a nucleus of atomic 
number Z and the second the potential due to the average density distribu- 
tion n(r). (The negative charge of the electron has been allowed for). Thus 
each electron obeys the single particle Schroedinger equation

                                                                                                               v2 +vit(r)} 49i (r) = fi(Pi(r),                                                                                                                                                                                                 (4.13
where j denotes both spatial as well as spin quantum numbers. The mean 
density is given by
                                                                                                                        n(r) = E I (MO 12,                      j=1  N                                                                                                                                                                     (4.14)
where, in the groundstate, the sum runs over the Nlowest eigenvalues, to re- 
spect the Pauli exclusion principle. Equations (4.12)—(4.14) are called the

                                    Walter Kohn                                 227


self-consistent Hartree equations. One may start from a first approximation 
for n(r), (e.g. from TF theory), construct vH(r), solve (4.13) for the (pj; and 
recalculate n(r) from Eq. (4.14), which should be the same as the initial n(r). 
If it is not one iterates appropriately until it is.
  In the winter of 1964, I returned from France to San Diego, where I found 
my new post-doctoral fellow, Lu Sham. I knew that the Hartree equations de- 
scribed atomic groundstates much better than TF theory. The difference be- 
tween them lay in the different treatments of the kinetic energy T (See Eqs. 
(4.10) and (4.13). I set ourselves the task of extracting the Hartree equations 
from the HK variational principle for the energy, Eqs. (4.9), (4.7), (4.8), 
which I knew to be formally exact and which therefore had to have the 
Hartree equations and improvements "in them". In fact it promised a 
Hartree-like formulation, which — like the HK minimal principle — would be 
formally exact.
  The Hartree differential equation (4.13) had the form of the Schroedinger 
equation for non-interacting electrons moving in the external potential veg. 
Could we learn something useful from a DFT for non-interacting electrons 
moving in a given external potential v(r)?. For such a system, the HK vari- 
ational principle takes the form


                    Ev(o[n]       f v(r)fi (r)dr Ts[ft(r)]                   (4.15)

                               > E ,                                         (4.16) 

where (assuming that n(r) is VR for non-interacting electrons) ,

        T jii(r)    kinetic energy of the groundstate of non-interacting (4.17)
                    electrons with density distribution n(r).

The Euler-Lagrange equations, embodying the fact that the expression (4.14) 
is stationary with respect to variations of n(r) which leave the total number of 
electrons unchanged, is

    Ev[ii(r)]        (Sii(r) {v(r) +  on(6 r)Ts[n(r)]        —€}dr      0 , (4.18)

where ii(r) is the exact groundstate density for v(r). Here £ is a Lagrange mul- 
tiplyer to assure particle conservation. Now in this soluble, non-interacting 
case we know that the groundstate energy and density can be obtained by cal- 
culating the eigenfunctions cp.(r) and eigenvalues c of non-interacting, 
single-particle equations

                           1 172 +v(r)       €i)Coi(r) = 0,                  (4.19)

yielding
                           N                   N
                    E = cj          n(r) = > I (Pi(r) 12 .                   (4.20)
                          j=1                 :7=1

