                                  303

A HALF-CENTURY OF NEUROTRANSMITTER 
RESEARCH: IMPACT ON NEUROLOGY AND 
PSYCHIATRY

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000
by
ARVID CARLSSON
Department of Pharmacology, Goteborg University, Goteborg, Sweden.




BEGINNINGS
My encounter with dopamine followed upon an incredible sequence of for- 
tunate events. I had been working on calcium metabolism, using radioactive 
isotopes, which had then just become commercially available. This work had 
resulted in my doctoral thesis in 1951 and a series of subsequent papers, in- 
cluding two doctoral theses by students of mine. It had become somewhat 
visible internationally, resulting for example, in an invitation to a Gordon 
Conference in New England in 1955. The reason why I left this research field 
was that in connection with a competition for an associate professorship in 
pharmacology the expert committee let me know that in their opinion cal- 
cium metabolism did not occupy a central position in pharmacology. I there- 
fore turned to Professor Sune Bergstrom who was at that time head of the 
Department of Physiological Chemistry of the University of Lund, Sweden. 
This department was located in the same building as our Pharmacology 
Department. Professor Bergstrom had already been very helpful in several in- 
stances when I had a professional problem of some kind. Incidentally, 
Dr. Bengt Samuelsson was at that time working with Professor Bergstrom 
in the same department. Thus the three Swedes who were to become Nobel 
Laureates in the period 1980-2000, happened to be working under the same 
roof for a few years.
 I asked Sune Bergstrom if he could help me to get in touch with an out- 
standing American laboratory working in the area of biochemical pharma- 
cology, which I felt had a great future. He wrote to his friend Dr. Bernard 
Witkop, a highly talented chemist working in the National Institutes of 
Health in Bethesda, Md. This letter was forwarded via the late Dr. Sidney 
Udenfriend, to his boss the late Dr. Bernard B. Brodie (Fig. 1), head of the fa- 
mous Laboratory of Chemical Pharmacology of the National Heart Institute. 
That is how I came to work under Dr. Brodie for about five months, starting 
in August 1955. The timing of my arrival there was extremely fortunate. 
Brodie and his colleagues had just a few months before made a breakthrough 
discovery, namely that the administration of reserpine, a recently introduced

304                                  Physiology or Medicine 2000
























Figure 1. Bernard B. Brodie 
(1907-1989)


antipsychotic and antihypertensive drug, caused the virtually complete disap- 
pearance of serotonin from the brain and other tissues (Pletscher el at 1955, 
1956, Fig. 2).


"APPRENTICE TO GENIUS"

Brodie was a remarkably charismatic and intensive person. He was generally 
called Steve Brodie. This referred to a saloon keeper named Steve Brodie, 
who at the beginning of the previous century had .jumped off the Brooklyn 
Bridge in order to win a bet, Bernard Brodie, too, was a sensation seeker who



                                                                    1
                  0.75• 1









                       111.-E:4P4NE DOSAGE MG./ PCG.                             2.0          2.5


Figure 2, Brain level of serotonin four hours. after various intravenous doses of reserpine, From 
Pletscher 1 at.(1956),

                Arvid Carlsson     305

in his youth had started on a career as a boxer but later switched to become 
an organic chemist. He then confined his sensation seeking to non-physical 
adventures. He liked to call himself a gambler. He had gained a tremendous 
reputation as a pioneer in the area of drug metabolism and should perhaps 
rightly be called the father of modern biochemical pharmacology. A large 
number of his apprentices, coming from various parts of the world, later be- 
came prominent figures in pharmacology (see Kanigel, "Apprentice to Ge- 
nius"). In the 1950s, after hearing about the sensational clinical actions of the 
new antipsychotic drugs and the ability of the hallucinogenic LSD to block 
serotonin effects on various peripheral organs he decided to enter the field of 
psychopharmacology. While knowing very little about the brain he had a 
tremendous trump card in being able to determine for the first time sero- 
tonin and similar molecules in the brain, using the prototype of a new instru- 
ment developed in his own lab together with Sidney Udenfriend and Dr. 
Robert Bowman. This instrument, the spectrophotofluorimeter, was to re- 
place previous bioassays and to revolutionize drug research and neurotrans- 
mitter pharmacology for several decades.
 This research soon led to the breakthrough discovery just mentioned, that 
is, the depletion of serotonin stores by reserpine treatment. For the first time 
a bridge seemed to have been built between the biochemistry of the brain 
and some important brain functions, with some obvious neuropsychiatric im- 
plications.
 Brodie and his colleagues, especially Dr. Parkhurst Shore, generously in- 
troduced me into the new analytical methods and the use of the new instru- 
ment. I proposed to Brodie that we investigate the effect of reserpine on the 
catecholamines in view of their chemical similarity to serotonin. But Brodie 
thought this would be waste of time. He was so sure that serotonin was the 
target to focus upon.

A "ROSETTA STONE"?
But I felt that a look at the catecholamines might be worth while. To get start- 
ed quickly I would then need a partner specialized in the catecholamine field. 
Again I was incredibly lucky. Of all the people working in that field at the time 
the most clever partner in such a project was located in my home University, 
the University of Lund: Professor Nils-Ake Hillarp (Fig. 3). I wrote to him 
from Bethesda and proposed a collaboration, and he agreed. Thus a most 
fruitful collaboration started, lasting until his untimely death in 1965. 
Hillarp's personality was different from that of Brodie in many respects, but 
they were similar in terms of brilliance, charisma and intensity. His back- 
ground was histology and histochemistry, but his knowledge extended far in- 
to physiology and biochemistry.
 In the spring of the following year Hillarp and I got the first results. We 
demonstrated the depletion of catecholamines from the adrenal medulla of 
rabbits following treatment with reserpine (Carlsson and Hillarp 1956). This 
was before I had acquired my own miracle instrument, the so-called Aminco-

306         Physiology or Medicine 2000

















                      Figure 3. llillarp. Photo: Georg


Bowman Spetrophotolluorimeter. The only instrument we had for the deter- 
mination of catecholamines was a colorimeter, using the method of von Euler 
and Hamberg (1949). But we did not need any instrument because be ab- 
sence of a colour development in the samples from reserpine-treated rabbits 
could be seen with the naked eye.
 The same results were obtained when we analyzed heart and brain, in the 
latter case using our new instrument. We also found that sympathetic nerves 
no longer responded to nerve stimulation following reserpine treatment, ap- 
parently clue to depletion of transmitter (Carlsson et al. 1957a). Thus deple- 
tion of catecholamines could be the cause of the behavioral inhibition in- 
duced by reserpine. To investigate this we gave DOPA (3,4-dihydroxyphenyl- 
alanine) to reserpine-treated animals and thus discovered the dramatic re- 
versal of the reserpine-induced syndrome by this catecholamine precursor 
(Carlsson ei al. I957b, Fig. 4). The reason we used the precursor was that the 
catecholamines are unable to penetrate from the blood into the brain, be- 
cause of the blood-brain barrier.
 We then analyzed the brains of DOPA-treated animals and much to our dis- 
appointment we were unable to detect any restoration of noradrenaline 
levels. Experiments with monoamine oxidase inhibitors clearly showed that a 
monoamine rather than DOPA itself was responsible for the behavioral 
response, and thus we were forced to look for the intermediate in the con- 
version of DOPA to noradrenaline: dopamine.
 At that time dopamine was considered to be without any interest because of 
its low physiological activity, when tested on various smooth-muscle prepara-  
tions. We had to develop a method for determining dopamine because no 
such method was available at the time (Carlsson and Waldeck 1958). We 
could then show that dopamine occurs normally in the brain in an amount

                 Arvid Carlsson        307


























Figure 4. Rabbits treated with reserpine (5 mg/kg intravenously).before (toe) and after DL- 
DOtA (200 mg/kg intravenously, bouom). From Carlsson (1960). Photo: Tor Magnusson.




somewhat higher than that of noradrenaline, that it is brought to disappear 
by reserpine treatment, and that the antireserpine action of DOPA is closely 
correlated to the restoration of dopamine levels in the brain. We also showed 
that the restoration of serotonin levels by treatment with its precursor 5-hy- 
droxytryptophan did not lead to any reversal of the reserpine syndrome 
(Carlsson et (ii. 1958).
 The classical method in physiology to prove a function of a natural con- 
stituent, is to remove the constituent in question and demonstrate a loss of 
function, and then to reintroduce the constituent, and demonstrate a restora- 
tion of the same function. We thought we had done this in the case of dop- 
amine. We could easily exclude possible alternative explanations, such as a 
role of noradrenaline and serotonin and a direct action of L-DOPA.
 In fact, our enthusiasm made us think that now we had found the Rosetta 
stone that would give us access to the chemical language of the brain.
 Later we found the unique distribution of dopamine in the brain, with an 
accumulation in the basal ganglia, that is structures known to be involved in 
motor functions. This, taken together with the fact that a characteristic side 
effect of reserpine is to mimic very faithfully the syndrome of Parkinsonism 
and to induce a similar syinptomatology in animals, led us to conclude that 
depletion of dopamine will induce the Parkinson syndrome and that treat- 
ment with L-DOPA will alleviate that syndrome by restoring the dopamine 
level. All this I presented at the First International Catecholamine Symposium 
in October, 1958 (Carlsson 1959, Bertler and Rosengren 1959).

308         Physiology or Medicine 2000

A BATTLE IN LONDON
A year and a half later, in March 1960, a Ciba Foundation Symposium on 
Adrenergic Mechanisms was held in London (Vane et al. 1960). I then pre- 
sented the same data and some additional support obtained from studies on 
the action of monoamine oxidase inhibitors. At this meeting practically all of 
the most eminent experts in this area participated. The central figure was Sir 
Henry Dale, a Nobel Laureate aged 85 but still remarkably vital. He dominat- 
ed the scene, and the participants, many of whom were his former students, 
treated him with enormous respect, like school children their headmaster, al- 
though many of them had indeed reached a mature age.
 To better understand how our dopamine story was received at this meeting 
it may be useful to recapitulate briefly the development following Otto 
Loewi's discovery of chemical transmission in the frog heart (Loewi 1921). 
During the following decades evidence accumulated, supporting the exis- 
tence of chemical transmission in various parts of the peripheral nervous 
system. Dale and his collaborators played an important role here. They had, 
however, been fiercely attacked by a number of neurophysiologists, who ar- 
gued in favour of an electrical transmission across the synapses. The most 
eminent proponent of this view was Sir John Eccles. The debates between 
Dale and Eccles had been quite vivid, as witnessed by several attendants of 
these debates between what was called "the sparks" and "the soup". Despite 
the sometimes harsh wordings the debates between Dale and Eccles over the 
years ended in mutual respect and admiration, as clearly indicated in the cor- 
respondence of more than twenty years between the two (see Katz 1996, 
Girolami et al. 1994). Doubts about a chemical transmission were particularly 
strongly expressed concerning the central nervous system. In the mid 1950s, 
however, Eccles had placed one foot in the "soup" camp, based on his own ob- 
servation that a recurrent collateral of the motor neurone, impinging on the 
so-called Renshaw cells, seemed to operate by cholinergic transmission. This 
was, however, a very special case, given the fact that motor neurons are cholin- 
ergic. Apart from this finding, as pointed out by McLennan (1963) in his mo- 
nograph "Synaptic Transmission", there was no evidence in favour of chemi- 
cal transmission in the central nervous system.
 At this meeting in London the debate that followed upon our paper entit- 
led "On the biochemistry and possible functions of dopamine and noradren- 
aline in the brain" and a subsequent special discussion session, revealed a pro- 
found and nearly unanimous skepticism regarding our points of view. Our 
data as such were not questioned. Actually some confirmatory animal experi- 
ments were reported at the meeting, and I referred to a paper by Degkwitz et 
al. (1960), in which an anti-reserpine action of DOPA in humans was report- 
ed. Dale expressed the view that L-DOPA is a poison, which he found re- 
markable for an amino acid. Marthe Vogt concluded that the views expressed 
by Brodie and us regarding a function of serotonin and catecholamines, re- 
spectively, in the brain would not have a long life. W.D.M. Paton referred to 
some unpublished experiments indicating that the catecholamines are locat-

               Arvid Carlsson     309

ed in glia. In his concluding remarks John Gaddum stated that at this meet- 
ing nobody had ventured to speculate on the relation between catechol 
amines and the function of the brain. But this was what I had insisted upon 
throughout the meeting, so the clear message to me was that I was nobody!
 In retrospect I believe almost everybody would agree that our story and its 
implications were straight forward and obvious. How come that these emi- 
nent experts rejected the whole thing? I have no definite answer. Clearly the 
pharmacologists had great difficulty in accepting that dopamine could be an 
agonist in its own right, given its poor physiological effect on smooth-muscle 
preparations. The idea of DOPA being a mysterious poison probably came 
out of some experiments reported at the meeting where large doses of this 
amino acid, given to experimental animals together with a monoamine 
oxidase inhibitor, could cause paralysis, convulsions and death. In addition, I 
believe that the previous "sparks-and-soup" debates still had some impact. In 
these debates some elaborate criteria for a neurotransmitter had been for- 
mulated. Our data were of a different kind and these criteria were not ap- 
plicable.
 In this regard I and my collaborators, like my mentor Steve Brodie, simply 
had the advantage of being ignorant and not so much burdened by dogma.

A PARADIGM SHIFT
But it wouldn't be long until the scene would change dramatically. Hillarp 
also attended the London meeting. On our trip back to Sweden we agreed we 
should increase our efforts to convince the world that chemical transmission 
does indeed exist in the brain. Our idea was that Hillarp join me to work full 
time on research in our new and well-equipped department of pharmacology 
of Goteborg University, where I had been appointed professor and chairman 
the year before. We managed to obtain a grant from the Swedish Medical 
Research Council to set Hillarp free from his teaching duties in Lund. He 
could start full-time research in Goteborg already in the autumn of 1960.
 We felt that the ability of catecholamines to yield fluorescent conversion 
products might be useful for their visualization in the microscope. We first 
tried a modifcation of the trihydroxyindole method (Carlsson et al. 1961). It 
worked beautifully for the adrenal medulla but not in other tissues. Hillarp 
then turned to another reaction that had been used for the quantitative assay 
of indoleamines, using formaldehyde as a reagent. Together with his skillful 
research assistant, the late George Thieme he worked out a model system, in 
which they managed to optimize the reaction conditions. (These experi- 
ments were reported by Falck et al. 1962). Subsequently, together with his for- 
mer student Bengt Falck, Hillarp used air-dried preparations of iris and 
mesenterium, and discovered that the reaction worked beautifully, thus per- 
mitting the visualization of noradrenaline in adrenergic nerves and serotonin 
in mast cells in the fluorescence microscope. This led to an intense collabo- 
ration between our Department of Pharmacology in Goteborg and Hillarp's 
original Department of Histlogy in Lund, and finally, after Hillarp's move to

310           Physiology or Medicine 2000




















Figure 5. Group picture, taken January 1965, showing the group of young researchers recruited 
by I [Warp after his move to the Karolinska Institute in 1962. From Dahlstrom and Carlsson 
(1986). Photo: Lennart Nilsson.


take over the chair of histology at the Karolinska Institute in 1963, with an 
enthusiastic group of young students in his new department (see Fig.5). Thus 
within a few years the neuronal localization of dopamine, noradrenaline and 
serotonin in the central and peripheral nervous system was clearly established 
(Fig. 6). Moreover, the major monoaminergic pathways could be mapped 
(Fig. 7), and the site of action of the major psychotropic drugs clarified (see 
Dahlstrom and Carlsson 1986, Carlsson 1966, Fig. 8).
 As mentioned, a large number of people were engaged in this effort. Sadly, 
many of these people have passed away, in many cases prematurely. Among 
these Georg Thieme (Fig. 9) has already been mentioned. Margit Lindqvist
























Figure 6. Dopaminergic cell bodies in rat substantia nigra. Green fluorescence developed fol- 
lowing treatment with formaldehyde vapour. Courtesy of Annica DahlstrOm.

                            Arvid Carlsson                     311






















                                Figure 7. Monoaminergic pathways in brain. From 
                                Fuse and Anden (1966).




                        CHLORPROMAZIAIE. 
                        0.. RE:SERPI/1(E 
                      1.()          gra/late\


           mitochondrion
                                                   target cell


                              amine
     MAO INHIBITORS
                   0.<(
                        /411PRAMINEnerve ending 

Figure 8. Scheme of monoaminergic synapse, with the sires of action of major classes of psy- 
chotropic drugs indicated. From Carlsson (1966).



(Fig. 10), a very skilful laboratrory assistant, who matured to become a quali- 
fied research worker, played an enormous role already from the outset of my 
scientific career. Nils-Erik Anden (Fig. 11) and Jan Hiiggendal (Fig. 12) were 
originally students of mine who became outstanding pharmacologists and 
largely contributed to characterize both central and peripheral monoamin- 
ergic transmission (for some of their early work, see Anden, Carlsson arid 
Fidggendal 1969). Hans Corrodi (Fig. 13), a very skilful organic chemist, who 
moved to Sweden because of his love for the mountains in northern Sweden,

312                     Physiology or Medicine 2000


















Figure 9. Georg Thicrue (1926-1996)    Figure 10. Margit Lindqvist (1924-1978)


contributed much to clarify the chemistry of the formaldehyde histofluores- 
cence method and to many other projects, especially the development of the 
first selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor SSR1 (see below).
  In February 1965 an international symposium entitled "Mechanisms of 
Release of Biogenic Amines" was held in Stockholm (v. Euler et al. 1966), with 
most of the major figures of that research field participating. In his Intro-



















Figure 11. Nils-E:rik Anden (1937-1990)Figure 12. jan Haggencial (1932-1992)

               Arvid Carlsson     313

















                   Figure 13. Hans Corrodi (1929-1974)


ductory Remarks Professor Uvnas mentioned that "...these amines play an im- 
portant role as chemical mediators in the peripheral and central nervous 
system...". None of the participants of this symposium expressed any doubt on 
this point. It looks as though a paradigm shift had taken place between 1960 
and 1965.
 It goes without saying that the concept of chemical transmission has had a 
profound impact on practically every aspect of brain research. In so far as 
neurology and psychiatry are concerned, a couple of examples are summa- 
rized below.


"AWAKENINGS"
Following our above-mentioned proposal of a role of dopamine in Parkin- 
sonism some important parallel and apparently independent developments 
took place in Austria, Canada and Japan. These will now be briefly comment- 
ed upon, starting out with Austria.
 Later in the same year as the Symposium on Adreenergic Mechanisms, 
there appeared in Klinische Wochenschrift a paper in German, describing a 
marked reduction of dopamine in the brains of deceased patients who had 
suffered from Parkinson's disease and postencephalitic Parkinsonism 
(Ehringer and Hornykiewicz 1960). This was soon followed by a paper by 
Birkmayer and Hornykiewicz (1961), in which a temporary improvement of 
akinesia was reported following a single intravenous dose of L-DOPA to 
Parkinson patients.
 As far as I can gather from an autobiography of Hornykiewicz (1992) as 
well as a personal communication from him, the following had happened. I

314          Physiology or Medicine 2000

wish to mention this in some detail, because it illustrates how the interaction 
of different minds can lead to important progress. In 1958, Hornykiewicz was 
approached by a mentor Professor Lindner or, according to a different ver- 
sion, by his chief Professor Bracke, who tried to persuade him to analyze the 
brain of a Parkinson patient, which the neurologist Walter Birkmayer wanted 
to be analyzed for serotonin. Presumably Birkmayer had been impressed by 
Brodie's already mentioned discovery in 1955 of the depletion of this com- 
pound by reserpine, and in contrast to many neurologists at that time he was 
aware of its possible implications. Shortly afterwards, in 1959, Hornykiewicz 
read about our work on dopamine and its role in the Parkinson syndrome. 
He then decided to include dopamine and noradrenaline in the study. In 
fact, in the subsequent work serotonin had to be left out initially because of 
some technical problems.
  Hornykiewicz and his postdoctoral fellow Ehringer were now facing a chal- 
lenge, because they had no adequate equipment to measure dopamine. But 
they managed to overcome this problem by using the purification of the 
brain extracts by ion exchange chromatography that our research group had 
worked out. The subsequent measurement was performed using the colori- 
metric method of Euler and Hamberg. Although this method by itself is high- 
ly unspecific, specificity could be obtained by using our purification step to- 
gether with our finding that dopamine is by far the dominating catechol- 
amine in the basal ganglia, where it occurred in high concentrations. They 
had to work up several grams of tissue and to concentrate the extracts by 
evacuation to dryness. Following this heroic procedure they were richly re- 
warded, because the samples from the Parkinsonian brains, in contrast to the 
controls, turned out to be colourless, as revealed by the naked eye!
  The corresponding development of Parkinson research in Canada is sum- 
marized in a paper by Barbeau et al. (1962), presented at a meeting in Geneva 
in September the previous year. The main findings of the Canadian workers 
was a reduction of the urinary excretion of dopamine in Parkinson patients 
and an alleviation of the rigidity of such patients following oral treatment 
with L-DOPA.
  In Japan some remarkable progress was made, which has not been ade- 
quately paid attention to in the Western countries (see reviews by Nakajima 
1991, and Foley 2000). In a lecture on the 5th of August, 1959, less than a 
year after my lecture at the International Catecholamine Symposium men- 
tioned above, the basic concept regarding the role of dopamine in the basal 
ganglia in Parkinson's disease was presented by I. Sano (1959). In this lecture 
data on the distribution of dopamine in the human brain were presented for 
the first time. In a lecture in Tokyo on the 6th of February, 1960, Sano re- 
ported on reduced amounts of dopamine in the basal ganglia of a Parkinson 
patient, analyzed post mortem, and in the same year he published a paper de- 
scribing alleviation of rigidity in a Parkinson patient following intravenous ad- 
ministration of DL-DOPA (Sano 1960).
  Thus treatment of Parkinson patients with DOPA was initiated simultan- 
eously in three different countries only a few years after the discovery of the

                Arvid Carlsson      315

anti-reserpine action of this agent and the subsequent formulation of the con- 
cept of a role of dopamine in extrapyramidal functions. While this treatment 
led to results of great scientific interest, it took several years until it could be 
implemented as routine treatment of Parkinson patients. The reason was that 
the treatment regimens used initially were inadequate and led to but mar- 
ginal improvement of questionable therapeutic value (Hornykiewicz 1966). It 
remained for George Cotzias (1967) to develop an adequate dose regimen. 
After that L-DOPA treatment rapidly became the golden standard for the 
treatment of Parkinson's disease.
 When I had seen Cotzias' impressive film demonstrating the effect of esca- 
lating oral doses of L-DOPA at a meeting in Canada I hastened back to 
Goteborg and initiated studies together with Drs. Svanborg, Steg and others, 
which quickly confirmed Cotzias' observations (Anden et al. 1970), like in 
many other places at the same time. This success story was soon afterwards 
told to the general public by Oliver Sacks in "Awakenings" (Sacks 1973), 
which became a bestseller and was also made into a movie.

ROLE OF SEROTONIN IN DEPRESSION: ZIMELIDINE, THE FIRST SSRI
The so-called tricyclic antidepressants, with imipramine as the prototype, 
were serendipitously discovered in the late 1950s, thanks to Kuhn, a psychia- 
trist and a keen clinical observer. In the early 1960s these agents were found 
to block the reuptake of noradrenaline by nerve terminals, thus enhancing 
the adrenergic transmission mechanism. In 1968, we discovered that many 
antidepressants also could block the reuptake of serotonin (Carlsson et al. 
1968), and this prompted us to develop a compound that selectively blocked 
the reuptake of serotonin without acting on noradrenaline. Such agents are 
now known as SSRIs. This first agent was called zimelidine, whose preclinical 
properties we first described by Berntsson et al. (1972). Zimelidine turned out 
to be an active antidepressant agent with a very favourable side effect profile 
(Carlsson et al. 1981), apart from a very rare, but serious side effect, presum- 
ably based on an immunological mechanism, that led to its withdrawal from 
the market. But zimelidine was followed by several other SSRIs, among which 
Prozac is especially well known, not least because of a bestseller titled 
"Listening to Prozac", authored by P.D. Kramer (1993). In this book Prozac is 
stated to be able to treat not only patients with depression and a variety of 
anxiety disorders, as had previously been amply demonstrated for many 
SSRIs, but also to be able to change the personality of people with psycho- 
logical problems. Kramer was especially astonished by the fact that distur- 
bances, which would have taken several months of psychotherapy to control, 
could be alleviated within a few days of treatment with Prozac. This 
favourable action, making people feel and function better, even if they were 
not mentally ill in the conventional sense, is a fascinating but, needless to say, 
controversial issue. Less controversial is probably the 25 % reduction in sui- 
cide rates in Sweden in the 1990s, apparently related to the introduction of 
the SSRIs (Isacsson 2000). In any event the SSRIs represent a major thera-

316                            Physiology or Medicine 2000


peutic advance as well as a milestone in rational drug development (Carlsson 
1999).
   The development of zimelidine was based on our discovery that certain an- 
tihistamines arc serotonin-reuptake blocking agents, albeit non-selective. The 
most powerful agents among these were the pheniramines and diphenhy- 
dramine (Carlsson et aL 1969). We started out from the pheniramines and 
developed zimelidine. The Lilly scientists started out from our diphenhy- 
dramine data and developed Prozac, which was found to act very much like 
zimelidine, though devoid of its serious side effect.


DOPAMINERGIC STABILIZERS — A NOVEL PHARMACOLOGIC 
PRINCIPLE

In 1963, Margit Lindqvist and I presented the first evidence supporting the 
view that the most important group of antipsychotic agents, represented by 
agents such as chlorpromazine and haloperidol, act by blocking receptors for 
dopamine, and to some extent also receptors for noradrenaline (Carlsson 
and Lindqvist 1963, Fig.I 4). This conclusion has later been confirmed and 
extended in numerous laboratories, and techniques have been developed to 
screen for such agents in test tube experiments. One might have expected 
then that this should have led to the development of drugs with stronger effi- 
cacy and less side effects. Unfortunately, this has not happened.
   We have hypothesized that the cause of this Failure is that treatment with 
dopamine receptor antagonists can hardly avoid the serious and unpleasant 
side effects induced by dopamine hypofunction. Even though there is evi- 
dence of elevated dopaminergic activity in schizophrenia, this may be limited 
to psychotic episodes. In fact, we may be dealing with an instability of the





                    1.8   Norodren olio°   Dopamine      Norms tonepte    kiethoxyt yr
                    1.6                                            .10
                    1.4                                      9


                    10 
                   08 
                   06 
                   0.4 
                   02
                    0'                        -
          Number 01 exp. 9 4 7             9 5 7           11 5 7          11 5 7

Figure 14. Accumulation of of the basic catecholamine metabolites normetanephrine and 3- 
methoxytyramine, enhanced by treattnem with major neuroleptic agents following monoamine 
oxidase inhibition. From Carlsson and Lindqvist 1963.

               Arvid Carlsson      317

dopamine release rather than a continuously elevated baseline. Thus, be- 
tween psychotic episodes, the patient would then suffer from a dopaminergic 
hypofunction, especially during treatment with the currently used antipsy- 
chotic agents, showing up as a severe disturbance of the reward system and of 
cognition, and also as motor disturbances. This may make it. impossible to 
attain an adequate dose level (for discussion and references, see Carlsson et 
al. 2001).
 We believe that we can now get around this problem by using a new prin- 
ciple of intervention that we call dopaminergic stabilization. The underlying 
mechanism is complicated but in principle it rests on the existence of mutu- 
ally antagonistic subpopulations of dopamine D2 receptors, as regards the 
final functional outcome. For example, the presynaptically located dopamin- 
ergic autoreceptors are inhibitory on the overall dopaminergic activity. 
Dopaminergic stabilizers are dopamine D2 antagonists or partial D2 agonists 
capable of occupying mutually opposing receptor subpopulations in such 
proportions as to leave the normal baseline dopaminergic activity level essen- 
tially unchanged. This leads to stabilization by dampening fluctuations of 
dopamine release, simply because fewer dopamine receptors are unoccupied 
and thus available for the endogenous neurotransmitter.
 Using the dopaminergic stabilizer (-)-0SU6162 (Fig. 15), developed by our 
research group, partly in collaboration with Upjohn (now merged into 
Pharmacia Corporation), we have demonstrated the stabilization phenome- 
non in experimental animals (Fig. 16) and, in preliminary clinical studies, its 
pharmacotheraputic potential in L-DOPA-induced dyskinesias in Parkinson 
patients, in Huntington's disease (Fig. 17), and in schizophrenia (Tedroff et 
al. 1999, Ekesbo 1999, Gefvert et al. 2000).
 The partial dopamine receptor agonist preclamol ( (-)-3-PPP) has likewise a 
dopaminergic stabilizer profile. This agent was discovered by our research 
group and is in development in collaboration with Dr. Carol Tamminga and 
her colleagues at the Maryland Psychiatric Research Center (Lahti et al. 1988). 
 Our experience with dopaminergic stabilizers suggests that research into





    Structure of (+0SU6162










                       Figure 15. Chemical structure of 
                       (-)-0SU6162.

