392

THE MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF MEMORY STORAGE: 
A DIALOG BETWEEN GENES AND SYNAPSES

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000 
by
ERIC R. KANDEL
Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Columbia University, College of Physicians 
and Surgeons, New York, USA.



INTRODUCTION
One of the most remarkable aspects of an animal's behavior is the ability to 
modify that behavior by learning, an ability that reaches its highest form in 
human beings. For me, learning and memory have proven to be endlessly fas- 
cinating mental processes because they address one of the fundamental fea- 
tures of human activity: our ability to acquire new ideas from experience and 
to retain these ideas in memory. In fact, most of the ideas we have about the 
world and our civilization we have learned so that we are who we are in good 
measure because of what we have learned and what we remember. However, 
not all learning experiences are positive. Many psychological and emotional 
problems also result at least in part from our experiences. In addition, spe- 
cific disorders of learning and memory haunt both the infant and the adult. 
Down syndrome, fragile X mental retardation, age-related loss of memory, 
and the devastation of Alzheimer's disease are only the familiar examples of a 
large number of disorders that affect memory.
 Throughout my career I have been interested in the biology of learning. I 
have been curious to know: What changes occur in the brain when we learn? 
And, once something is learned, how is that information retained in the brain 
as memory? I have tried to address these questions by developing a reduc- 
tionist approach that would allow me to investigate the biological mecha- 
nisms underlying elementary forms of learning and memory at a cell and 
molecular level — as specific molecular activities within specific identified 
nerve cells.
 For a biologist like myself, interested in mental processes, the study of 
learning has the further appeal that, unlike other mental processes such as 
thought, language and consciousness, learning is relatively accessible to a cel- 
lular and molecular analysis. Elementary forms of learning and memory have 
been well characterized by classical psychology since the work of Ivan Pavlov 
and Edgar Thorndike in the first half of the 20th century, and these forms of 
learning are the most clearly delineated and, for the experimenter, most 
easily controlled of any mental process.
 I first became interested in the study of memory in 1950, as a result of my

                Eric R. Kandel     393

readings in psychoanalysis while still an undergraduate at Harvard College. 
Later, during medical training, I found the psychoanalytic approach limiting 
because it tended to treat the brain, the organ that generates behavior, as a 
black box. In the mid 1950s, while still in medical school, I began to appre- 
ciate that during my generation the black box of the brain would be opened 
and that the problems of memory storage, once the exclusive domain of psy- 
chologists and psychoanalysts, could be investigated with the methods of 
modern biology. As a result, my interest in memory shifted from a psycho- 
analytic to a biological approach. As a postdoctoral fellow at the National 
Institutes of Health (NIH) in Bethesda from 1957 to 1960, I focused on learn- 
ing more about the biology of the brain, and became interested in knowing 
how learning produces changes in the neural networks of the brain and how 
a transient short-term memory is converted to an enduring long-term me- 
mory.
 From the beginning, my purpose in translating questions about the psy- 
chology of learning into the empirical language of biology was not to replace 
the logic of psychology or psychoanalysis with the logic of cell and molecular 
biology, but to try to join these two disciplines and to contribute to a new syn- 
thesis that would combine the mentalistic psychology of memory storage with 
the biology of neuronal signaling. As I thought more concretely about the 
neural mechanisms of memory storage, I hoped further that the biological 
analysis of memory might carry with it an extra bonus, that the study of me- 
mory storage might reveal new aspects of neuronal signaling. Indeed, this has 
proven true. Time and again, the molecular study of memory has revealed 
novel aspects of more general biological processes.

DEVISING A RADICAL REDUCTIONIST STRATEGY TO LEARNING AND 
MEMORY
At first thought, someone interested in learning and memory might be 
tempted to tackle the problem in its most complex and interesting form. This 
was the approach that my colleague Alden Spencer and I originally had in 
1958 when, at the start of our scientific careers, we joined forces at the NIH to 
study the cellular properties of the hippocampus, the part of the mammalian 
brain thought to be most directly involved in aspects of complex memory (1). 
We were initially interested in a simple question: Are the electrophysiological 
properties of the pyramidal cells of the hippocampus, which were thought to 
be the key hippocampal cells involved in memory storage, fundamentally dif- 
ferent from other neurons in the brain, such as the well-studied motor neu- 
rons in the spinal cord involved in simple movement? In the course of study- 
ing the pyramidal cells of the hippocampus, it became clear to us that all 
nerve cells have similar signaling properties. Therefore, the intrinsic signal- 
ing properties of neurons would themselves not give us key insights into 
memory storage (17).
 Thus, the unique functions of the hippocampus had to arise not so much 
from the intrinsic properties of pyramidal neurons but from the pattern of

394         Physiology or Medicine 2000

functional interconnections of these cells, and how those interconnections 
are affected by learning. To tackle that problem we needed to know how sen- 
sory information about a learning task reaches the hippocampus, and how in- 
formation processed by the hippocampus influences behavioral output. This 
was a formidable challenge, since the hippocampus has a large number of 
neurons and an immense number of interconnections. It seemed unlikely 
that we would be able to work out in any reasonable period of time how the 
neural networks, in which the hippocampus was embedded, participate in be- 
havior and how those networks are affected by learning.
 Thus, to bring the power of modern biology to bear on the study of learn- 
ing, it seemed necessary to take a very different approach — a radically reduc-  
tionist approach. Instead of studying the most complex cases, we needed to 
study the simplest instances of memory storage, and to study them in the ele- 
mentary reflex behavior of those animals that were most experimentally 
tractable. To do this we needed to find experimental systems in which a sim- 
ple behavioral act that was controlled by a small number of large and acces- 
sible nerve cells could be modified by learning. Only in this way could we cor-  
relate changes in the overt behavior of the animals with molecular events in 
identifiable neurons and examine how sensory processing in the brain is 
modified by learning to give rise to memories.
 Such a reductionist approach was hardly new in 20th century biology. One 
need only think of the use of Drosophila in genetics, of bacteria and bacterio-  
phages in molecular biology, and of the squid giant axon in the study of the 
conduction of nerve impulses. Nevertheless, when it came to the study of be- 
havior, many investigators were reluctant to use a reductionist strategy. In the 
1950s and 1960s many biologists and psychologists believed that behavior was 
the one area of biology in which the use of simple animal models, particular- 
ly invertebrate ones, was least likely to succeed. They argued that only higher  
animals exhibit interesting forms of learning and that these forms require 
neuronal organizations and neuronal mechanisms qualitatively different 
from those found in simple animals. As a result, an approach to learning 
based on simple invertebrates was bound to fail because it would lack rele- 
vance to mammalian and particularly to human behavior.
 It was my belief at the outset, however, that concerns about the use of a 
simple experimental system to study learning were misplaced. The question 
was and is not whether there is something special about the human brain; 
there clearly is. Rather, the question is whether the human brain and human 
behavior have anything at all in common with the nervous system and be- 
havior of simpler animals. If so, these fundamental, common principles of 
neuronal organization might well be studied more profitably in simple ani- 
mals.
 The answer to this second question, about commonality, was clear. By 1960, 
work by students of comparative behavior such as Konrad Lorenz, Niko 
Tinbergen, and Karl von Frisch had shown that humans share many beha- 
vioral patterns and even simple forms of learning with simple animals (re- 
viewed in 2). That the evolution of behavior and learning is conservative

                Eric R. Kandel      395

should not be surprising, since the evolution of other biological functions is 
also conservative. There are, for example, no fundamental functional or bio- 
chemical differences between the nerve cells and synapses of humans and 
those of a snail, a worm or a fly. Since behavior and learning is an expression 
of nerve cell activity, it would be surprising if the learning capability of people 
did not have some elementary features in common with the learning of snails, 
worms, or flies. And, if elementary forms of learning are common to all ani- 
mals with an evolved nervous system, there must be conserved features in the 
mechanisms of learning at the cell and molecular level, that can be studied ef- 
fectively even in simple invertebrate animals.


A SIMPLE INVERTEBRATE SYSTEM THAT LENDS ITSELF TO A 
REDUCTIONIST APPROACH

After an extensive search for a suitable experimental animal, I settled on the 
giant marine snail Aplysia (Figure 1), because it offers three important ex- 
perimental advantages: its nervous system is made up of a small number of 
nerve cells; many of these are very large; and (as became evident to me later) 
many are uniquely identifiable (3,13). Whereas the mammalian brain has a 
million-million central nerve cells, Aplysia has only 20,000. These cells are 
clustered in 10 anatomical units called ganglia, each of which contains about 
2,000 cells (Figure 2). An individual ganglion, such as the abdominal gang- 
lion, mediates not one but a family of behaviors. Thus, the simplest behaviors 
that can be modified by learning may involve less than 100 cells. This nume- 
rical simplification made it possible to identify the specific contribution of in- 
dividual neurons to the behavior in which they participate (13). In addition 
to being few in number, these cells are the largest nerve cells in the animal 
kingdom, reaching up to 1,000 I.Lm in diameter, large enough to be seen with 
the naked eye (Figure 3). Because of their extraordinary size and their di- 
stinctive pigmentation, it is possible to recognize many of the cells as unique 
individuals. One can record from these large cells for many hours without any 
difficulty, and the same cell can be returned to and recorded from over a pe-














               Figure 1. The giant marine snail Aplysia californica belongs 
               to the opisthobranch subclass of the gastropod molluscs. 
               Animals of this species may grow to be 30 cm in length and 
               weigh 1 kilogram.

396            Physiology or Medicine 2000


      Human Brain             Aplysia Brain 
      1012 'Neurons          2 x 10 Neurons


                           BLC,CAI

                           C'efebral

                                        Pedal



                           AbdOrnIrial

Figure 2. The human brain has a million-million neurons while the brain of Aplysia has 20,000 
nerve cells. Aplysia nerve cells are clustered together in five major bilateral pairs of ganglia, each 
ganglion containing about 2,000 nerve cells.


riod of days. The cells can easily be dissected out for biochemical studies, so 
that from a single cell one can obtain sufficient mRNA to make a cDNA 
library. Finally, these identified cells can readily be injected with labeled com- 
pounds, antibodies, or genetic construct procedures which opened up the 
molecular study of signal transduction within individual nerve cells.


REQUIREMENT FOR A CELL-BIOLOGICAL STUDY OF MEMORY 
STORAGE

Given a technically advantageous experimental system, how does a cell biolo- 
gist begin to address the problem of learning? The strategy that my col- 
leagues and I developed involved four sequential steps: (1) We first wanted to 
define a simple behavior that can be modified by learning and that gives rise 
to memory storage. (2) We next wanted to identify the cells that make up the 
neural circuit of that behavior. (3) Within that neural circuit we then wanted 
to locate the critical neurons and interconnections that had been modified by 
learning and that store memory. (4) Finally, we wanted to analyze the changes 
that occur at those sites in response to learning and memory storage, first on








                       Figure 3. A photomicrograph of an abdominal 
                       ganglion of Aplysia shows the distinctive pig- 
                       mentation and positions of its cells. The largest 
                       cells are a millimeter in diameter and can be se- 
                       en with the naked eye. Scale bar = I mm. (See 
                       also Fig. 6A).

                          Eric R Kandel                    397


the cellular and then on the molecular level (13). I follow this outline in the 
discussion below.


DELINEATING A BEHAVIOR IN APLYSIA THAT IS CAPABLE OF BEING 
MODIFIED BY LEARNING

Irving Kupfermann and I first wanted to study the simplest possible behavior 
of Aplysia (4). We examined the animal's behavioral capabilities and deli- 
neated a very simple defensive reflex: the withdrawal of the gill upon stimu- 
lation of the siphon, an action that is like the quick withdrawal of a hand from 
a hot object. In Aplysia, the gill is a respiratory organ that lies exposed in the 
mantle cavity. When the animal is in a normal, relaxed state, the gill is par- 
tially covered by a sheet of skin (the mantle shelf), which ends in a fleshy 
spout, the siphon (Figure 1). When a weak tactile stimulus is applied to the 
siphon, both the siphon and gill are withdrawn into the mantle cavity and for 
protection under the mantle shelf (Figure 4); ref. 5).
             Gillwithdrawel reflex                Sensitization



Mantle shelf







 Siphon   yJ     Gill

           :ivy     Tactile   ;_.            Tactile
                    stimulus '47             stimulus
Figure 4. A dorsal view of Aplysia showing the gill, the animal's respiratory organ. The gill lies in 
the mantle cavity and is normally covered partially by the mantle shelf. A light touch to the 
siphon with a fine probe causes the siphon to contract and the gill to withdraw into the mantle 
cavity under the protection of the mantle shelf_ Here, the mantle shelf is shown to be retracted 
for a better view of the gill. Sensitization of the gill-withdrawal reflex, produced by applying a 
noxious stimulus to another part of the body, such as the tail, leads to an enhancement of the 
withdrawal reflex of both the siphon and the gill.


 Kupfermann, Harold Pinsker, and later Tom Carew, Robert Hawkins and I 
found that this simple reflex could be modified by three different forms of 
learning: habituation, sensitization, and classical conditioning (5,8,9). As we 
examined these three forms of learning, we were struck by the resemblance 
each had to corresponding forms of memory storage in higher vertebrates 
and humans. As with vertebrate learning, memory storage for each type of 
learning in Aplysia has two phases: a transient memory that lasts minutes and 
an enduring memory that lasts days. Conversion of short-term to long-term 
memory storage requires spaced repetition — practice makes perfect even in 
snails (8,9,10).

398                                                        Physiology or Medicine 2000


     We focused initially on one type of learning, sensitization, a form of learned 
fear in which a person or an experimental animal learns to respond strongly 
to an otherwise neutral stimulus (5,8,10). For example, if somone is sudden- 
ly exposed to an aversive stimulus, such as a gunshot going off nearby, that 
person will be sensitized by the unexpected noise. As a result, that person will 
be frightened and will now startle to an otherwise innocuous stimulus like a 
tap on the shoulder. Similarly, on receiving an aversive shock to another part 
of the body such as the tail (or head), an Aplysia recognizes the stimulus as 
aversive and learns to enhance its defensive reflex responses to a variety of 
subsequent stimuli applied to the siphon, even innocuous stimuli (Figure 4; 
12). The animal now remembers the shock, and the duration of this memory 
is a function of the number of repetitions of the noxious experience. A single 
shock gives rise to a memory lasting only minutes; this short-term memory 
does not require the synthesis of new protein. In contrast, four or five spaced 
shocks to the tail give rise to a memory lasting several days; this long-term 
memory does require the synthesis of new protein. Further training gives rise 
to an even more enduring memory lasting weeks, which also requires new 
protein synthesis (Figure 5; 10,12).


                                                                                                                4 trains l day 
                                                                                                                for 4 days













                                                                                                 4 single shocks


                                                                              Ingle
                                                                                I shook
                                              100                                                     ----- Control
                                                 0
                                                                 0          1                               4                                7
                                                                                   Days after training
Figure 5. Spaced repetition converts short-term memory into long-term memory in Aplysia. In the 
resting state, before sensitization training, a weak touch to the siphon causes only a weak and brief 
siphon and gill withdrawal reflex. Following a single noxious, sensitizing, shock to the tail, the 
siphon and gill withdrawal reflex repsonse to that same weak touch is enhanced and produces a 
much larger reflex withdrawel response. The memory following this single noxious stimulus lasts 
about one hour. After four or five single tail shocks, the animal's gill and siphon withdrawal re- 
flex to that same weak touch is enhanced further and now lasts more than a day. If the animal re- 
ceives further training — four brief trains of single shocks a day over the course of four days — the 
siphon and gill reflex withdrawal to the same weak siphon touch is enhanced still further and the 
memory now lasts for several weeks. (Modified from 98.)

               Eric R. Kandel      399

 Thus, just as in the complex learning in mammals (107,108), long-term 
sensitization differs from the short-term process in requiring the synthesis of 
new proteins. This was our first clear evidence for the conservation of bio- 
chemical learning mechanisms between Aplysia and vertebrates, and it rein- 
forced the hope that a detailed analysis of short-term memory and its transi- 
tion to long-term memory in Aplysia would reveal molecular mechanisms of 
general importance.

DEFINING THE NEURAL CIRCUIT IN CELLULAR DETAIL
To analyze the cellular mechanisms of sensitization, we needed to identify the 
neural circuit of the gill withdrawal reflex. Kupfermann and I quickly local- 
ized the central neuronal machinery for the reflex behavior in the animal's 
abdominal ganglion (4,6). Because we soon realized that many cells in Aplysia 
could be identified in every animal of the species (3,4,6,7), we were able to 
give the cells specific names and, most important, return to the same cell time 
and again — in both untrained and trained animals. In this way Kupfermann, 
Castellucci, Carew, Hawkins, John Byrne, and I were able to work out signifi- 
cant components of the neural circuit gill-withdrawal reflex in terms of indi- 
vidual cells and cell clusters. The circuit has 24 mechanoreceptor sensory 
neurons that innervate the siphon skin and make direct monosynaptic con- 
nections with six gill motor cells (7,11,36). The sensory neurons also made in- 
direct connections with the motor cells through small groups of excitatory 
and inhibitory interneurons (18,19). In addition to being identifiable, indi- 
vidual cells also proved to have surprisingly large effects on behavior (Figure 
6C; reviewed in 13,22,36).
 As we examined the neural circuit of this reflex in detail, we were struck by 
its invariance — the cells that make up the circuit and their interconnections 
are always the same. In every animal we examined, each cell connected only 
to certain target cells and not to others (Figure 7). Carew, John Koester, 
Wayne Hening, and I also found this invariance in the neural circuitry of 
other behaviors in Aplysia — inking, control of the circulation, locomotion 
(reviewed in 13,15) — raising a key question in the cell-biological study of 
learning: How can learning occur in a neural circuit that is precisely wired?

HOW DOES LEARNING AFFECT THE INVARIANT ELEMENTS OF THE 
NEURAL CIRCUIT?
In his Croonian Lecture to the Royal Society of 1894, Santiago Ramon y Cajal 
proposed a theory of memory storage: memory is stored in the growth of new 
connections (16). This prescient idea was neglected in good part for half a 
century as students of learning fought over newer competing ideas. First, Karl 
Lashley, Ross Adey, Wolfgang KOhler, and a number of Gestalt psychologists 
proposed that learning leads to changes in electric fields or chemical gradi- 
ents, which they postulated surround neuronal populations and are pro- 
duced by the aggregate activity of cells recruited by the learning process.

400                Physiology or Medicine 2000











         L7 motor neuron

         LE sensory neurons







                                              Gill


















         Gill                        Gill     •

         Motor         Motor         Motor 
         Neuron        Neuron        Neuron

                       Sensory       Sensory 
                       Neuron        Neuron It

Figure 6. The neural circuit of the gill-withdrawal reflex can be delineated in terms of specific 
identified cells.
 A. This dorsal view of the abdominal ganglion shows some of the identifiable cells (compare 
with Fig. 3). The six identified motor cells to the gill are shaded brown; seven sensory neurons 
are shaded blue. In the figure a sensory neuron that synapses on gill motor neuron L7 is being 
stimulated electrically and a microelectrode in the motor neuron records the synaptic potential 
produced by the action potential in the sensory neuron (see middle trace in part C).
 B. The physiological demonstration of the direct connections between the sensory neuron and 
motor neuron. The sensory neuron receives input from the siphon skin; the motor neuron 
makes direct connections onto the gill. The fact that the cells are large and identifiable allows for 
the mapping of connections between specific identified cells. This part shows the experimental 
arrangement for simultaneously recording in a pre- and postsynaptic cell. The sensory neuron 
makes a direct connection onto the motor neuron, as is evident in the middle trace in part C.
 C. Individual cells make significant contributions to the reflex. Stimulating a single motor neu- 
ron (traces on the left) produces a detectable change in the gill, and stimulating a single senso- 
ry neuron produces a large synaptic potential in the motor neuron (traces in the middle). 
Repeated stimulation of a single sensory neuron increases the frequency of firing in the motor 
neuron, leading to a visible reflex contraction of the gill (traces on the right). A single tactile sti- 
mulus to the skin normally activates 6 to 8 of the 24 sensory neurons, causing each to fire 1 to 2 
action potentials. The repetitive firing of 10 action potentials in a single sensory neuron, desig- 
ned to simulate the firing of the total population, in fact simulates reasonably well the reflex be- 
havior.

                   Eric R. Kandel         401


                         Siphon



       Tail









            Modulatory 
           interrveurons

                   I atemeuroris


                           Gill 'IL.

Figure 7. The neural circuit of the gill-withdrawal reflex. The siphon is innervated by 24 sensory 
neurons that connect directly with the six motor neurons. The sensory neurons also connect to 
populations of excitatory and inhibitory interneurons that in turn connect with the motor neu- 
rons. Stimulating the tail activates modulatory interneurons that act on the terminals of the sen- 
sory neurons as well as on those of the excitatory interneurons. There are three classes of modu-  
latory neurons activated by tail stimuli: (1) neurons that release serotonin (5-1-1T), (2) neurons 
that release a peptide called the small cardioactive peptides (SCP), and (5) the L29 cells, which  
release an unidentified modulatory neurotransmitter. The serotonergic modulatory action is the 
most important. Blocking the action of these serotonergic cells blocks the effects of sensitizing  
stimuli.


Second, Alexander Forbes and Lorente de No proposed that memory is 
stored dynamically by a self-reexciting chain of neurons. This idea was later 
championed by Donald Hebb as a mechanism for short-term memory. Finally, 
Holger Hyden proposed that learning led to changes in the base composition 
of DNA or RNA. Even though there was much discussion about the merits of 
each of these ideas, there was no direct evidence to support any of them (re- 
viewed in 17).
 We were now in a position to address these alternative ideas by confronting 
directly the question of how learning cans occur in a circuit with fixed neuro- 
nal elements. Kupfermann, Castellucci, Carew, Hawkins, and I examined the 
neural circuit of the gill-withdrawal reflex while the animal underwent 
neither sensitization or habituation, a form of learning in which the animal 
learns to ignore an innocuous stimulus to siphon when given with monoto- 
nous repetition. (We later also extended these studies to an examination of 
classical conditioning (20).) Our studies provided clear evidence for Cajal's 
idea: learning results from changes in the strength of the synaptic connec- 
tions between precisely interconnected cells (6,7). Thus, while the organism's 
developmental program assures that the connections between cells are in-

402         Physiology or Medicine 2000

variant, it does not specify their precise strength. Rather, the strength and ef- 
fectiveness of these preexisting chemical connections can be altered by expe- 
rience. Seen in the perspective of these three forms of learning, synaptic pla- 
sticity emerged as a fundamental mechanism for information storage by the 
nervous system, a mechanism that is built into the very molecular architec- 
ture of chemical synapses (95).
 We soon appreciated that the synaptic strength of a given chemical synapse 
could be modified in two ways: homosynaptically and heterosynaptically. 
Homosynaptic changes in synaptic strength occur in a synapse because of ac- 
tivity in the presynaptic and postsynaptic neurons of that very synapse. During 
habituation, homosynaptic changes occur in the monosynaptic connections 
between the sensory neurons and the motor neurons of the gill-withdrawal re- 
flex. Heterosynaptic changes occur in a synapse where presynaptic and post- 
synaptic neurons are themselves not active but there is, instead, activity in one 
or more modulatory interneurons that act on the presynaptic neurons, on 
the postsynaptic neurons of the synapse, or on both, to modify the strength of 
their synaptic connections. During sensitization, heterosynaptic changes are 
induced in the monosynaptic connections between the sensory neurons and 
motor neurons of the gill-withdrawal reflex. Hawkins, Abrams, and I later 
found that these two types of regulation are recruited together in classical 
conditioning (20,21). Classical conditioning therefore illustrated that the el- 
ementary forms of homo- and heterosynaptic plasticity form an alphabet of 
basic mechanisms that can produce combinations of plasticity with novel 
properties.
 In all three forms of learning we found particularly large changes in the 
synaptic strength of the direct connections between the sensory and motor 
neurons of the reflex. We therefore focused on this one component of the re- 
flex and found several additional principles that have proven to be quite gen- 
eral. First, we found that the same synaptic connection can be modulated in 
opposite ways by different forms of learning. For example, habituation leads 
to a homosynaptic weakening of synaptic connections between the sensory 
neurons and their target cells, the motor neurons and interneurons, while 
sensitization leads to heterosynaptic strengthening of these same sets of con- 
nections (7,13,33). Second, learning not only leads to changes in synaptic 
strength, it can also affect the excitability of neurons. In the case of sensitiza- 
tion the excitability of the sensory (presynaptic) neurons is increased (25). 
Third, the synaptic changes persist, thereby contributing to memory storage 
(10,33,94). Indeed, the same synaptic connection can store both short- and 
long-term memory (7,23,33,43,94,98). At a given synapse synaptic plasticity 
can either be short- or long-lived depending on the number of spaced repe- 
titions of the learning stimulus, and these parallel not only the behavioral 
changes of short-term memory but also those of long-term memory (7,43,93). 
Finally, long-term memory storage involves not only a change in synaptic 
strength, but also anatomical changes, changes in the number of synaptic 
connections (57,58,59).
 The changes at the synapse between the sensory and the motor neuron are

                Eric K Kandel      403

only a part of the changes in the neural circuit of the gill-withdrawal reflex. 
Important changes occur elsewhere in the circuit, but we have studied them 
less. We have focused on the monosynaptic portion of the circuit in order to 
probe in depth the molecular mechanisms that contribute to learning and 
memory.

INITIAL STEPS TOWARD A MOLECULAR CHARACTERIZATION OF 
SENSITIZATION
What are the molecular mechanisms whereby short-term memory is estab- 
lished, and how is it converted to long-term memory? Initially, we focused 
on short-term sensitization (Figure 8). In collaboration with James H. 
Schwartz, we found that the synaptic changes, like the short-term behavior, 
were expressed even when protein synthesis was inhibited. Since the short- 
term changes persisted for many minutes, it seemed unlikely that they in- 
volved a simple conformational change of one or more proteins. We there- 
fore proposed in 1971, that short-term memory might require a series of 
sequential reactions similar to that mediated by cAMP-mediated signaling 
(26). Our attention was drawn to cAMP because Sutherland, Rall and Krebs 
had found that various neurotransmitters could increase cAMP concentration 
in the brain and in other tissues, and in the liver cAMP activated the cAMP- 
dependent protein kinase (26). In 1972, Schwartz, Howard Cedar, and I 
found that stimulation of the modulatory pathways recruited during he- 
terosynaptic facilitation led to an increase in cAMP in the abdominal gang- 
lion (27). Cedar and Schwartz next applied a number of neurotransmitter 
candidates and found that serotonin and dopamine could increase levels of 
cAMP (29). This made us wonder whether the population of modulatory in- 
terneurons, which produces the heterosynaptic facilitation that gives rise to 
sensitization, contains serotonergic or dopaminergic cells.
 Later, Hawkins, Castellucci, David Glanzman, and I delineated the modu- 
latory system activated by a sensitizing stimulus to the tail (19,34,35), and con- 
firmed that it contains serotonergic interneurons. The system includes two 
other classes of heterosynaptic modulators, but the serotonergic neurons are 
most important for sensitization: blocking their actions alone blocked sensi- 
tization (34).

A DISTINCTION BETWEEN MEDIATING AND MODULATORY 
CIRCUITRY
In 1974, Castellucci and I next attempted to localize the change produced by 
habituation and sensitization to either the presynaptic or the postsynaptic 
component of the synapse. We therefore applied a quantal analysis to the 
synaptic connections between the sensory and motor cells and found that the 
short-term homosynaptic depression that accompanies habituation is presy- 
naptic, involving a reduction in the amount of transmitter released from the 
presynaptic sensory neuron (30). This transmitter, Nicholas Dale later

404             Physiology or Medicine 2000




          A      Control Tail Shock






          Motor 
          neuron



          Sensory                 12 mV
          neuron                 _120 mV 
                                50 ms




          B      Control Serotonin








          Motor
          neuron







          Sensory 
          neuron                 1 2 mV 
                                   20 rriV 
                                50 ms



          C      Control Cyclic AMP




          Motor 

          neuron



          Sensory                  5 mV
          neuron
                                 --I 50 mV 
                                50 ms





          D      Control PKA (catalytic subunit)



          Motor                   15 niV
          neuron





          Sensory 

          neuron
                                   10 mV
                                50 ms


Figure 8. The strength of the synaptic connections between the sensory and the motor neurons 

is increased response to a single tail shock that produces short-term sensitization, in response to 

a single pulse of serotonin, and in response to direct injection of either cAMP or PKA into the 

presynaptic sensory neurons.

 A. The increase in synaptic strength produced by a single sensitizing stimulus can be achieved 

by an electrical stimulus to the tail, to the head, or to the neural pathways from the tail or head.

 B. A similar facilitation can also be reproduced by stimulating an individual modulatory cell 

such as one of the serotonergic cells or by the application of serotonin to the connection be- 

tween the sensory neurons and motor neurons.

 C. Facilitation can also he produced by injecting cyclic AMP into the sensory neurons.

 D. Facilitation can also be produced by simply injecting the catalytic subunit of PKA into the 

sensory neurons. In this experiment the spikes of the sensory neuron have been artificially broad- 

ened by the application of tetraethylammonium (TEA) which blocks some of the cell's K• cur- 

rents. This reveals dramatically the further broadening produced by the catalytic subunit of PKA 

through the reduction of the remaining Kt currents. A similar broadening is produced by tail sti- 

muli, application of serotonin, or injection of cAMP. (From 13,31,32,37.)

                Eric R Kandel      405

showed, is glutamate (51). Conversely, we found that the short-term he- 
terosynaptic facilitation that accompanies sensitization results from an in- 
creased release of this transmitter from the sensory neuron (31). We next 
found that a single brief application of serotonin could simulate short-term 
sensitization (Figures 8A and B) — by directly enhancing the release of trans- 
mitter from the sensory neurons, much as does the sensitization-induced fa- 
cilitation — whereas dopamine could not (32). Moreover, pharmacological in- 
hibitors of serotonergic receptors blocked the effect of sensitizing stimuli, 
providing further evidence for the importance of serotonin as a modulator of 
synaptic strength (32).
 Understanding the role of serotonergic and other modulatory neurons in 
sensitization allowed us to distinguish two different types of neural circuits im- 
portant for behavior and learning: mediating and modulating (Figure 7). A 
mediating circuit controls the gill-withdrawal reflex. It consists of the sensory  
neurons, interneurons, and motor neurons of the reflex, and it can be modi- 
fied homosynaptically by habituation. But other, more complex forms of 
learning, such as sensitization and classical conditioning, involve modulatory 
circuits, somewhat akin to the arousal or attentional circuitries in higher ani- 
mals. In Aplysia such a modulating circuit consists of serotonergic and other 
modulatory interneurons that act upon the mediating circuitry to regulate 
the strength of its connections. For example, modulatory interneurons act on 
the sensory neurons, including on their presynaptic terminals, to enhance 
the amount of glutamate released.

SHORT-TERM MEMORY INVOLVES cAMP AND 
THE ACTIVATION OF PKA
The finding that serotonin acts on specific receptors in the presynaptic ter- 
minals of the sensory neuron to enhance transmitter release, coupled with 
the fact that serotonin is capable of bringing about an increase in cAMP in 
the abdominal ganglion, caused us to ask whether serotonin facilitates the re- 
lease of transmitter from the sensory neurons by acting via cAMP. We first ex- 
plored this idea in 1976, when Brunelli, Castellucci, and I injected cAMP di- 
rectly into the presynaptic cells and found that it produced presynaptic 
facilitation (Figure 8C) (32,33). This provided the most direct and com- 
pelling evidence then available in the nervous system, that cAMP is involved 
in a specific physiological function and it gave us our first insight into the 
molecular mechanisms of short-term memory.
 Marc Klein and I next asked: How does cAMP enhance transmitter release? 
We found that serotonin, or injected cAMP, leads to increased excitability and 
a broadening of the action potential by reducing a specific current, allow- 
ing greater Ce influx into the presynaptic terminal with each action poten- 
tial (24). The greater Ca2+ influx could contribute to the enhanced transmit- 
ter release. Following the lead of Paul Greengard, who had proposed that 
cAMP produces all of its action in the brain through the cAMP-dependent 
protein kinase (PKA), Klein and I suggested that cAMP may lead to phos-

406         Physiology or Medicine 2000

phorylation of this K+ channel by activating PKA (24). In collaborative expe- 
riments with Paul Greengard in 1980, Castellucci, Schwartz, and I tested this 
idea by injecting the active catalytic subunit of PKA and found that the ca- 
talytic subunit by itself produced broadening of the action potential and en- 
hancement of glutamate release (Figure 8D) (37). Conversely, the specific 
peptide inhibitor of PKA (PM) blocked the actions of serotonin. These find- 
ings provided direct evidence for the role of PKA in short-term presynaptic fa-  
cilitation (38).
 In 1981, Steven Siegelbaum arrived at Columbia, having just mastered 
single-channel recording during a visit to Erwin Neher and Bert Sakmann in 
Gottingen. In an elegant series of experiments, Siegelbaum and Joseph 
Camardo identified a novel K' channel, the S-type channel, and showed 
that it could be modulated by cAMP (39). Then Siegelbaum and Michael 
Schuster used an isolated inside-out patch of membrane from the sensory 
neuron to show that PKA could act directly to decrease the number of chan- 
nels open in that patch (40). Later, Byrne showed that serotonin also modu- 
lates a delayed-rectifier K' channel whose contribution to spike broadening 
proved even more important than that of the S-type channel (reviewed in 
41). The combined studies indicated that the S-type channel mediated the in- 
crease in excitability with a minor contribution to broadening, whereas the 
delayed-rectifier IQ- channel contributed little to excitability but had a major 
role in spike broadening. Finally, Hochner, Klein, and I — and independently 
Jack Byrne and his colleagues — showed that, in addition to spike broadening, 
serotonin also enhanced release by an as-yet-unspecified action on the release 
machinery. Thus, serotonin leads to an increase in presynaptic cAMP, which 
activates PKA and leads to synaptic strengthening through a combination of 
mechanisms (reviewed in 41).

LONG-TERM MEMORY INVOLVES THE NUCLEAR TRANSLOCATION 
OF PKA AND MAP KINASE AND THE ACTIVATION OF CREB-1
Even earlier, in 1973, Arnold Kriegstein, an M.D.-Ph.D. student, succeeded in 
culturing Aplysia larvae so that we could raise Aplysia in the laboratory (28),  
providing us with animals of any size or age at any time. This was a major ad- 
vance and opened up the study of synaptic plasticity in dissociated cell cul- 
ture, which required very young animals (42,43).
 In the intact animal, one tail shock produces short-term sensitization, 
which does not depend on protein synthesis; four to five tail shocks produce 
sensitization that lasts several days, and this long-term process requires new 
protein synthesis. Both are reflected in alterations in strength in the connec-  
tions between the sensory and motor neurons (Figure 9). By substituting 
puffs of serotonin for tail shocks, Sam Schacher, Pier Giorgio Montarolo, 
Philip Goelet, and I could model this behavioral protocol in a culture dish 
consisting of a single sensory cell making synaptic connections with a single 
motor cell (43). We were able to induce both short- and long-term facilitation 
in this culture and found, as we had with the intact animal, that the long-term

