 328

 THE NEUROBIOLOGY OF DOPAMINE SIGNALING

 Nobel Lecture, December 8, 2000 
by
PAUL GREENGARD
Vincent Astor Professor, Laboratory of Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience, 
The Rockefeller University, 1230 York Avenue, New York, NY 10021, U.S.A.



It is estimated that there are about one hundred billion nerve cells in the 
brain and that on average each of these nerve cells communicates with one 
thousand other nerve cells. A vigorous debate went on from the 1930s 
through the 1960s as to whether intercellular communication across the 
synapses between nerve cells was electrical or chemical in nature. The elec- 
trical school of thought held that the nerve impulse or action potential was 
propagated along the axon to the nerve ending, changed the electrical field 
across the postsynaptic plasma membrane, and thereby produced a physio- 
logical response. The chemical school believed that when the action potential 
came down the axon to the nerve terminal, it caused the fusion of neuro- 
transmitter-containing vesicles with the presynaptic plasma membrane, re- 
leasing a neurotransmitter, which then diffused across the synaptic cleft and, 
through activation of a (hypothetical) receptor, produced a physiological re- 
sponse. The chemical school won this debate: over 99% of all synapses in the 
brain use chemical transmission. Based on those earlier studies, I became in- 
terested in the biochemical mechanisms by which neurotransmitters, through 
activation of their receptors, produce their physiological effects within their 
postsynaptic target nerve cells.
 We know today that there are two categories of chemical transmission be- 
tween nerve cells, which are referred to as fast and slow synaptic transmission. 
About half of the fast synapses in the brain are excitatory, and most of these 
fast excitatory synapses utilize glutamate as their neurotransmitter. The other 
half of the fast synapses are inhibitory and most of these fast inhibitory 
synapses use GABA as their neurotransmitter. Synaptic transmission at fast 
synapses occurs in less than one-thousandth of a second, and is attributable to 
the ability of the fast-acting neurotransmitters to open what are called ligand- 
operated ion channels present in the plasma membrane of the post-synaptic 
cells. In fast excitatory transmission, glutamate binds to its receptor, causing a 
change in the conformation of the receptor, allowing positively charged so- 
dium ions to rush into the cell, causing a depolarizing, i.e. excitatory, signal to 
be generated in the target cell. In fast inhibitory transmission, GABA binds to 
its receptor, causing a change in the conformation of the receptor, allowing 
negatively-charged chloride ions to permeate the cell, causing a hyperpolariz- 
ing, i.e. inhibitory, signal to be generated in the target cell.

                             Paul Greengard                       329

  Slow synaptic transmission, which occurs over periods of tens of milli- 
seconds to seconds, is enormously more complex than fast synaptic transmis- 
sion. There are about 150 compounds which are now believed to serve as 
neurotransmitters in the brain. The vast majority of these putative neuro- 
transmitters appear to work through slow synaptic transmission. Thus, it now 
seems very likely that all of the biogenic amines, and all of the peptide neuro- 
transmitters, produce their effects on their target cells through slow synaptic 
transmission. And even the fast acting neurotransmitters, including gluta- 
mate and GABA, produce many of their effects through slow synaptic trans- 
mission pathways.
  Our work in trying to elucidate the molecular basis of slow synaptic trans- 
mission was inspired by studies carried out by Earl W. Sutherland' and Edwin 
G. Krebs2. Sutherland and Krebs were interested in understanding how the 
hormones glucagon and adrenaline break down glycogen to glucose in liver 
and muscle cells. Earl Sutherland and his colleagues found that these hor- 
mones stimulated the formation of cyclic AMP from ATP by virtue of activat- 
ing a class of enzymes that they called hormone-sensitive adenylyl cyclases. 
They then showed that cyclic AMP could mimic the hormones in causing the 
breakdown of glycogen to glucose. Edwin Krebs and his colleagues subse- 
quently showed that cyclic AMP caused the breakdown of glycogen to glucose 
by activating an enzyme which they called cyclic AMP-dependent protein 
kinase. Protein kinases catalyze the reaction:
   Adenosine Triphosphate (ATP)       Adenosine Diphosphate (ADP)
            + Substrate           —>       + Phosphosubstrate
They further showed that this substrate, when phosphorylated, was an en- 
zyme which caused the breakdown of glycogen to glucose. The action of pro- 
tein kinases is reversible, an enzyme called a protein phosphatase catalyzing 
the reaction:
         Phosphosubstrate         —> Substrate + Inorganic Phosphate
When my colleagues and I started our work on the molecular basis of synap- 
tic transmission, my hypothesis was that the same signaling machinery used by 
the endocrine system, e.g. to break down glycogen to glucose, might be used 
for communication between nerve cells. One major cause for concern with 
this concept was that in the case of hormones the distance of communication 
between the sending cell and the receiving cell can be more than two meters, 
whereas the distance across a synapse is roughly one millionth of a centime- 
ter. Nevertheless, we decided to test this hypothesis. We searched in the brain 
for signaling enzymes analogous to those which had been found in liver and 
muscle. We found a family of neurotransmitter-sensitive adenylyl cyclases, 
analogous to the hormone-sensitive adenylyl cyclases of Earl Sutherland. 
These adenylyl cyclases converted ATP to cyclic AMP in the presence of neu- 
rotransmitters. The first such neurotransmitter-sensitive adenylyl cyclase, 
found by John W. Kebabian (photo 1), was a dopamine-sensitive adenylyl cy- 
clase: in the presence of dopamine, this membrane-bound enzyme stimulated

330                Physiology or Medicine 2000

















Photo 1. John W. Kehahian, 1977.Photo 2, Eishichi Miyamoto, 2001.

formation of cyclic AMP. Moreover, the data indicated that this enzyme might 
play a role in synaptic transmission.
  At about the same time, Eishichi Miyamoto (photo 2) and J. F. Kuo (photo 
3) were able to demonstrate cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase activity in 
the brain'. In addition, the concentration of this enzyme was enormously 
higher in brain than in liver. Even more intriguing was the fact that the en- 
zyme was concentrated in the synaptic region of nerve cells. These data were 
consistent with a possible role for cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase in 
synaptic transmission.



















Photo 34 I. Kuo, (undated).     Photo 4. Howard Schulman, 1968.

                         Paul Greengard                 331

















Photo 5. S. Ttiur WalailS, 1990.Photo Angus C. Nairn, 1987.

  Soon thereafter, we found a second, distinct class of regulated protein ki- 
nases, activated selectively by cyclic GMP, rather than cyclic AMP'. This cyclic 
GMP-dependent protein kinase was present both in brain and in non-neural 
tissues. Subsequently, Howard Schulman (photo 4) discovered a third group 
of regulated protein kinases, which were stimulated by calcium, in the pre- 
sence of an unidentified endogenous heat stable protein that was later shown 
to be the calcium effector protein calmodulin6. The discovery of several neu- 
rotransmitter-sensitive enzymes that made cyclic AMP and of several second 
messenger-dependent protein kinases strengthened our belief that second 
messengers and protein kinases might be involved in signaling in the brain. 
This idea was supported by the discovery of a large number of brain-specific 
substrate proteins for these protein kinases. Thus, S. Ivar Walaas (photo 5) 
and Angus C. Nairn (photo 6) found more than one hundred substrate pro- 
teins for protein kinases which were highly enriched in, or exclusively local- 
ized to, the brain, some of which were present in very high concentrations7. 
In the ensuing years, we were able to show that injections of various second 
messengers, protein kinases, protein phosphatases, and activators and in- 
hibitors of these enzymes, were able either to mimic or to antagonize the abil- 
ity of neurotransmitters to produce physiological responses in nerve cells. 
Combined, these data have provided overwhelming evidence of a role for 
those signaling molecules in synaptic transmission9.
  Some of the principal signaling pathways involved in slow synaptic trans- 
mission are shown in figure 1. The presynaptic terminal contains synaptic 
vesicles, which sequester neurotransmitter within them. In response to an ac- 
tion potential, these vesicles fuse with the plasma membrane, releasing the 
neurotransmitter. In an extensive series of studies, in which Pietro De Camilli 
(photo 7), Fabio Benfenati (photo 8), Flavia Valtorta (photo 9), and Andrew 
J. Czernik (photo 10) played leading roles, and which involved a series of col-

332                 Physiology or Medicine 2000
















Photo 7. Pietro de CanalIli, 1981.Photo S. Fabio Benienati, 1999.

laborative studies with Rodolio R, Ilinas and his colleagues, it was found that. 
the efficacy of release of neurotransmitter from the presynaptic terminal was 
controlled by regulation of the state of phosphorylation of a family of pro- 
teins in the presynaptic nerve terminal11"1. We named these proteins synap- 
sins because they are localized to synaptic vesicles in the presynaptic termi- 
nals. The synapsins are the most abundant phosphoproteins found in the 
brain and, possibly for this reason, were the first. to he discovered. Another 
seminal series of studies on the regulation of neurotransmitter release by 
cyclic AMP-dependent phosphorylation of nerve terminal proteins was car-


















Photo 9. Fia.via Valtorta, 2000.  Photo 10. Andrew J. Czernik, 1992.

                Paul Greengard      333

ried out in a collaboration between Eric R. Kandel's laboratory and my own12' 
13. The various studies of the physiology of the presynaptic terminal demon- 
strated conclusively that the efficacy of neurotransmitter release in response 
to the nerve impulse is regulated by protein phosphorylation/dephosphory- 
lation. Those studies lie outside the scope of this presentation and I shall not 
discuss them further here. Rather, I am going to concentrate on how slow-act- 
ing neurotransmitters, through activation of their receptors, produce appro- 
priate physiological responses in their postsynaptic target cells.
 Slow-acting neurotransmitters, upon binding to their receptors, change the 
level of one or another second messenger, e.g. cyclic AMP, cyclic GMP, cal- 
cium, or diacyl glycerol. These second messenger molecules in turn activate 
distinct classes of protein kinases. The activated protein kinases phosphory- 
late and thereby change the properties of substrate proteins, which serve as 
downstream physiological effectors. The substrate proteins of the nervous sys- 
tem can be divided into various classes, four of which are diagrammed in 
figure 1. One major class of substrates are the receptors for neurotransmit- 
ters, both fast- and slow-acting neurotransmitters. These protein kinases also 
phosphorylate various voltage-gated sodium, potassium, and calcium ion 
channels. Another class of substrate proteins are ion pumps, which restore 
ionic equilibrium after a burst of neuronal activity. Still another class are tran- 
scription factors present in the cell nucleus, which control new protein syn- 
thesis. Protein synthesis is involved in long-term changes in the nerve cell in 
response to activity, and may form an important component of the molecular 
basis of learning and memory, a field which was pioneered by Eric Kandel, 
and is described by him in this volume".
 Figure 1, in highly simplified form, schematizes the basic principles of slow 
synaptic transmission. Although this scheme is now a component of the 
scientific dogma, it was greeted initially with enormous skepticism, and at 
times down-right hostility, by the scientific community. In retrospect, there 
were at least two major reasons for this. At the time that we started this work, 
neuroscience was not a clearly defined field. There were two types of people 
studying the brain. There were biophysicists, working in physiology depart- 
ments, who believed that everything significant about the brain could be ex- 
plained in terms of electrical signaling. And there were biochemists working 
in biochemistry departments who would happily throw a brain into a homo- 
genizer, with as much abandon as they would a liver, and look for enzymes or 
lipids. But these biochemists were rarely interested in brain function. And so 
these two groups rarely spoke to each other, which is just as well because 
when they did they didn't have nice things to say. So, there was almost no one 
working on the biochemical basis of how nerve cells function. A second rea- 
son for the skepticism that biochemical pathways might be involved in synap- 
tic transmission was more substantive: it was not immediately obvious as to 
how the relatively slow enzymatic reactions that we were studying, involving 
protein phosphorylation and dephosphorylation, could be involved in fast 
synaptic transmission, which occurs in less than one-thousandth of a second. 
The answer to this apparent paradox was that these slow signaling pathways

334                      Physiology or Medicine 2000




                                                Neurotransmillercontaining 
                                                vesicles








                      Neurotransmitter • • 4         Synapse
                         Receptor •       hieuratransmtlier




















                                                            Neurotransmitter 
                                                            Receptors
























Figure I. Some of the signaling pathways involved in slow synaptic transmission.







don't mediate fast synaptic transmission. Rather they modulate fast synaptic 

transmission, and they do so in two major ways: a) by regulating the state of 

phosphorylation of synapsins and other key proteins present in the pre- 

synaptic terminal, thus modulating the efficacy of neurotransmitter release 

(the amount of neurotransmitter released from the nerve terminal in re- 

sponse to an action potential), and b) by regulating the state of phosphoryla- 

tion of neurotransmitter receptors present in the post-synaptic cell, thus mo- 

dulating the responsivity of these receptors to the released neurotransmitter 

(responsivity referring to the magnitude of the electrophysiological response 

to a molecule of neurotransmitter).

  The various slow signaling pathways which have been studied to date obey 

similar principles. The slow-acting neurotransmitter which we have studied 

most intensively is dopamine. There were several reasons for focusing on this 

system. First there was the pioneering work of Arvid Carlsson15, his col- 

leagues, and those who followed in his footsteps, showing that four major and 

several minor neurological and psychiatric diseases are associated with ab- 

normalities in the dopamine signaling pathway. The four major diseases are 

Parkinsonism, schizophrenia, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder 

(ADHD), and drug abuse. Parkinsonism is associated with the death of dop- 

amine-producing nerve cells, and is treated by giving Levodopa, a precursor 

of dopamine. Most currently used antipsychotic drugs block a subclass of

                         Paul Greengard                 335

















Photo 1.1. Dana W. Aswad, 1979. Photo 12. Patrick B. Allen, 2001.

dopamine receptors. ADI-ID is treated by Rimini, which works in large part by 
stimulating dopamine release. Virtually all drugs of abuse cause perturbations 
of dopamine signaling. There were two other reasons for concentrating on 
dopamine signaling. One was that the neurostriatum, a major target for 
dopa.minergic innervation, is relatively large and homogenous and thus fair- 
ly readily permits both electrophysiological and biochemical studies. The 
other reason is that the simple circuitry of the basal ganglia, compared to the 
circuitry of the cortex, makes the analysis of signaling systems much more 
manageable. However, it is worth emphasizing that although much of our re- 
search in recent years has concentrated cm the dopamine pathways, the basic


















Photo 13, James A. Bibb, 2000.  Photo 14. Allen A. Fienberg, 1996.

336                      Physiology or Medicine 2000




















Photo 15. Gilberto Fisone, 1995.        Photo 16. Jean-Antoine Girault, 1986.


principles elucidated in those pathways appear to be applicable to all slow 
synaptic pathways in the brain.
   In our studies of dopamine signaling, we were very fortunate to discover a 
molecule that we named DARPP-32, an acronym for dopamine and cyclic 
AMP regulated phosphoprotein MW = 32 kDa. Dopamine, by activation of a 
subclass of dopamine receptors, causes an increase in the level of CAMP, the 
activity of PKA and the phosphorylation of threonine 34 of DARPP-32. 
DARPP-32 plays an obligatory role in mediating the actions of dopamine and 
has served as a rosetta stone for understanding the interactions of dopamine 
with other neurotransmitters, therapeutic drugs, and drugs of abuse. DARPP-




















Photo 17. Hugh C. Hemmings, Jr. (right) Photo 18. Charles C. Quimet, 1985.
and Angus C. Nairn, 1986.

                          Paul Greengard                  337

















Photo 19. Akinori Nishi, 2000.   Photo 20. Gretchen L. Snyder, 2000.

32 was discovered by S. Ivar Walaas and Dana W. Aswad (photo 11) while 
searching for region-specific protein kinase substrates in the brain 16. DARPP- 
32 has been characterized by Patrick B. Allen (photo 12), James A. Bibb 
(photo 13), Allen A. Fienberg (photo 14), Gilberto Fisone (photo 15), jean- 
Antoine Girault (photo 16), Hugh C. Hemmings, Jr. (photo 17, together with 
Angus C. Nairn), Angus C. Nairn, Charles C. Ouimet (photo 18), Akinori 
Nishi (photo 19), Gretchen L. Snyder (photo 20), Per Svenningsson (photo 
21), S. Ivar Walaas, and Zhen Yan (photo 22).
  DARPP-32 is highly concentrated in the neostriatum (the caudate and the 
putamen), and the nucleus accumbens. An enormously simplified version of 
the neostriatal circuitry in which these DARPP-32-containing nerve cells are 
located is shown in figure 2. This circuitry has provided a useful model for
















Photo 21. Per Svenningsson, 2000.Photo 22. Zhen Yan, 2000.

338           Physiology or Medicine 2000










  Neostriatum


                           Substantia Nigra












Figure 2. Simplified diagram of some connections between cortex, neostriatum, and substantia 
nigra.
 The upper portion shows the neuroanatomy and the lower portion the corresponding nt,mro- 
chemistry. The cells shown in yellow project from the cortex to the striatum and use glutamate, 
a fast-acting. excitatory neurotransmitter, to stimulate second-order neurons, shown in blue, 
which project from the neostriatum to the substantia nigra. These latter neurons contain 
DARPP-32 and use GABA as their neurotransmitter. In addition to innervating third-order 
neurons, their axons have branches that innervate dopaminergic neurons, which in turn provide 
feedback on the DARIT-32-containing
studying the mechanisms by which slow synaptic transmission, as exemplified 
by dopamine, modulates fast synaptic transmission, as exemplified by gluta- 
mate.
  There are three major classes of glutamate receptors, designated NMDA, 
AMPA and Metabotropic, and two major classes of dopamine receptors, de- 
signated D1 and D2. The interactions between the dopamine and glutamate 
signaling pathways are highly complex and in addition are modulated by 
many other neurotransmitters and their signaling pathways. DARPP-32 plays 
a central role in the interactions amongst those various complex signaling 
pathways (figure 3). All four possible classes of mechanisms for regulating the 
state of phosphorylation of DARPP-32 on threonine 34 have been shown to 
exist, i.e., increases and decreases in phosphorylation and increases and de- 
creases in dephosphorylation. Why has so much evolutionary machinery 
gone into regulating the state of phosphorylation of DARPP-32?
 The DARPP-32 sequence has been highly conserved within mammals. Rat 
DARPP-32 is a protein consisting of 205 amino acids. Threonine 34 of 
DARPP-32 is phosphorylated by PKA or PKG and dephosphorylated by PP2B. 
Phosphorylation of DARPP-32 on threonine 34 profoundly changes its bio- 
logical properties, converting it from an inactive molecule into a very potent 
inhibitor of protein phosphatase 1, with an 1050 (figure 4) and KI of about 
104 M17. Since the concentration of DARPP-32 in medium spiny neurons is

                                                                   Paul Greengard                                                                         339




                                          Cocaine.
                                      Amphetamine                                                                           CCK

                                                                Dopamine
                                    Neurotensin                                            Haldol               Glutamate


                                       Opiate                            \Z

                         Adenosine                              -0 DI \                               AMPA                         GABA
                                                       5                                                        GABA,
                    Serotontn
                                                    21?           /
                                            511T4                                                       -4
                         VIP                 I                  • env
                                          VIP -
                               NO-          I                     i.x.     ,f- -DARPP-32                IC
                                                          4,-10----c. j                           "I. 1PP-213
                                                      cLWP        PKG           piSAIIPP-32

                                                          giCREE1,                Jr Jr                       ---i" i P--NMDA

                                                            FRAs                                        --    . ,
                                                               P                                                —AMPA
                                                      WA'                                                e /
                                                                       P                                   GABA
                                                                  Na+             r           P




Figure 3. Interactions of signaling pathways in the neosiriatum.
    Activation by dopamine of the D1 subclass of dopamine receptors stimulates the phospluiryla- 
tion of DARPP-32 at Thu-34. This is achieved through a pathway involving the activation of adeny- 
ly1 cyclase, the fbrmation of cyclic AMP, and the activation of cyclic AMP-dependent protein ki- 
nase (MA). Activation by dopamine of the D2 subclass of dopamine receptors causes the 
dephosphorylation of DARPP-32 through two synergistic mechanisms: D2 receptor activation (a) 
prevents the DI receptor-induced increase in cyclic AMP formation, and (b) raises intracellular 
calcium, which activates a calcium-dependent protein phosphatase, referred to as protein phos- 
phatase 2B (PP2kcalcium/calmodulin-dependent protein phosphatase; calcineurin). Activated 
PP-2B dephosphorylates DARPP-32 at Thr-34. Glutamate acts as both a fast-acting and slow-acting 
neurotransmitter. Activation by glutamate of AMPA receptors causes a rapid response through                                                                  in- 
flux of sodium ions, depolarization of the membrane, and tiring of an action potential. Slow 
synaptic transmission, in response to glutamate, results in part from activation of the AMPA and 
NMI)A subclasses of glutamate receptor, which increases intracellular calcium and the activity of 
PP2B, and causes the dephosphorylation of DARPP-32 on Th•-34, All other neurotransmitters 
that have been shown to alter the physiology of dopaminoceplive neurons also alter the phos- 
phorylation state of DARPP-32 on Thr-34 in these cells. For example, adenosine acting on the 
A2A. subclass of dopamine receptor, serotonin acting on the 51-IT4 subclass of serotonin receptor, 
and VIP, acting on its receptor, all increase cyclic AMP-dependent phosphorylation of DARPP-32 
at Thr-34. Nitric oxide, released from other types of nerve cells, causes an increase in cyclic GMP 
formation, resulting in activation of cyclic GMP protein kinase (PKG), which like PICA increases 
DARPP-32 phosphorylation on Thr-34, GABA, acting on the GABA A subclass of GABA receptor, 
hyperpola•izcs the cell membrane, leading to a decrease in intraceIlular calcium, an inactivation 
of PP2B, and an increase in the state of phosphorylation of DARPP-32 at Thr-34, Interestingly, 
dopamine and GABA, both of which are capable of inhibiting activity of these nerve cells, both 
increase DARPP-32 Thr-341 phosphorylation state, one by increasing phosphorylation, the other 
by decreasing dephosphorylation. As one would predict, the effects of dopamine and GABA on 
DARPP-32 phosphorylation are synergistic. Neurotransmitters which act indirectly, to affect the 
physiology of these medium spiny neurons also regulate DARPP-32 phosphorylation: neuro- 
tensin, through stimulating the release of dopamine, increases DARPP-32 phosphorylation; con- 
versely cholecystokinin, through stimulating the release of glutamate, decreases DARPP-32 phos- 
pflorylation.
    Therapeutic drugs anti drugs of abuse, all of which affect the physiology of these neurons. al- 
so regulate the state of phosphorylation of DARPP-32 on Thr-34. For example antipsychotic 
drugs, such as Haldol, which block the activation by dopamine of the D2 subclass of dopamine 
receptor, increase phosphorylation. Agonists for the mu and delta subclasses of opiate receptors 
block Dl and A2A receptor-mediated increases in cyclic AMP respectively, and the resultant in- 
creases in phosphorylation. Cocaine and amphetamine, through increasing extracellnlar 
dopamine levels, increase phosphorylation. Marijuana, nicotine, alcohol, and LSD, all of which 
affect the physiology of the medium spiny neurons, also regulate phosphorylation (unpublished 
data). Finally, all drugs of abuse have greatly reduced biological effects in animals with targeted 
deletion of the DARPP-32 gene.

340	
Physiology or Medicine 2000
Figure 4. Phospho-DARPP--52, but not dephospho-DARPP-32, inhibits protein phosphatase-1.  
(Modified from Hemmings, et al., reference 17.)
greater than 10-5 M, this means that a small burst of activity in dopaminergic  
neurons would be expected to result in significant phosphorylation of  
DARPP-32 and inhibition of protein phosphatase 1. Protein phosphatase 1  
has a very broad substrate specificity and controls the state of phosphoryla- 
tion and activity of a number of physiologically important substrates, includ- 
ing neurotransmitter receptors, voltage-gated ion channels, ion pumps, and  
transcripton factors. As a result, neurotransmitters which increase or decrease  
phospho-threonine 34 of DARPP-32, inhibit or activate, respectively, protein  
phosphatase 1, and thereby increase or decrease the state of phosphorylation  
and activity of a large array of downstream physiological effectors.
The physiological significance of the DARPP-32/PPI cascade has been  
demonstrated in two distinct types of experiments. In one type we injected  
protein kinases, protein phosphatases, or inhibitors or activators thereof,  
into medium spiny neurons and obtained physiological responses consistent  
with the scheme shown in figure 3. The other type of study involved analysis  
of mice with targeted deletion of the DARPP-32 gene. Allen Fienberg engi- 
neered this knockout mouse and, in a multi-institutional collaboration, found  
that all physiological, biochemical, and pharmacological responses to dopa- 
mine, the psychostimulant drugs of abuse, and antischizophrenic drugs, seen  
in normal mice, were either greatly diminished or abolished in DARPP-32  
knockout mice (figure 5)18.
The scheme shown in figure 3 indicates that the fast excitatory glutamate  
receptors, AMPA and NMDA, regulate, and are regulated by, the DARPP- 
32/PP1 cascade. From this scheme one would predict that PP1 would be lo-
O
10-8	
10-7
10-10	
10-"
DARPP-32 (M)
•
•	
• • •
A
dephospho-
•
phosph
•
•
•
•
A •
4611. -11e1110441114 A A
•
•
I rotein P os atase-1 Activit
100  
81)  
60  
40  
20

                                    Paul Greengard                               34 1


      Stimulus                      Parameter                   Examples:

   • Dopamine                      Ion Pumps                        10-ATPase

   • Dopamine                      Ion Channels                Ca2+ Channels 
   • Dopamine                      Neurotransmitter Release    GABA Release 
   • Dopamine                      Neurotransmitter Receptors  G1uR1 Receptor 
   • Dopamine; Psychostimulants    Immediate Early Genes       Fos Induction 
   • Psychostimutants              Brain Damage                Reactive Gnosis 
   • Antischizophrenics            Locomotor Activity          Catalepsy
   • Dopamine; Progesterone        Sexual Receptivity          Female Responsiveness

Figure 5. Responses to dopamine, psychostimaIants nod au tisaiictpfirenic drugs arc abolished 
in DARYP-k knockout mice.


calized in the vicinity of these glutamate receptors. Immtmocytochemical ex- 
periments, using antibodies prepared against recombinant PP-1, enabled us 
to localize this phosphatase in neostriatal cells. PP I was enriched in the spines 
of the dendrites of medium spiny neurons't . To answer the question as to the 
basis for the high degree of enrichment of PP I in spines, Patrick Allen used 
yeast-two hybrid technology to search for a PP1 targeting protein. He found a 
molecule, called spinophilin, which has the properties of such a targeting 
protein. Spinophilin is localized almost exclusively in dendritic spine heads at 
excitatory synapses (figure 6)21). This is precisely where the AMPA and NMDA 
receptors are concentrated.





















Figure 6. Electron micrograph showing immunoreactivity in a dc-nciritic spine neck and espe- 
cially in a spine head. Immunmeactivity (black flocculent material) lines the cytoplasmic surface 
of the spine plasmalemma and coats the postsynaptic density. Immunoreactivity is not present in 
axon terminals or in the dendritic shaft. (Bar = 100 rim) (Modified from Allen et at, reference 
20).

342                                                               Physiology or Medicine 2000


     It has recently been demonstrated that spinophilin, through control of 
PP-1, regulates the conductance properties of AMPA and NMDA receptors21. 
A model to account for the ability of spinophilin and PP1 to regulate the 
AMPA receptor is shown in figure 7. In its dephosphorylated form, the AMPA 
receptor is relatively insensitive to activation by glutamate. Its sensitivity to 
glutamate is greatly enhanced upon phosphorylation by cAMP-dependent 
protein kinase23' 24. In the absence of dopamine, the AMPA receptor is kept 
in a low conductance state by PP1. Dopamine, through activation of cAMP- 
dependent protein kinase, causes an increase in the state of phosphorylation 
of the G1uR1 subunit of the AMPA receptor, and this effect is greatly atte- 
nuated in the neostriatum of mice lacking the DARPP-32 gene. The activa- 
tion of PKA in response to dopamine increases the state of phosphorylation 
of the AMPA receptor by a synergistic mechanism involving direct phospho- 
rylation of the receptor as well as phosphorylation of threonine 34 on 
DARPP-32, resulting in inhibition of PP-J catalyzed dephosphorylation of the 
receptor.
     Physiological support for the scheme shown in figure 7 includes evidence 
that the dephosphorylation, and associated loss of responsivity of AMPA re- 
ceptors to activation by glutamate, can be prevented by incubation of cells 
either with a DI. receptor agonist, or with the PP-1 inhibitor okadaic acid, but 
not with an inactive analog of okadaic acid (figure 7). This scheme is also sup- 
ported by data demonstrating that injection of a peptide corresponding to 
residues 6-38 of phospho-DARPP-32, which retains the ability to inhibit 
PP-1, hilt not dephospho-DARPP-32 (6-38), prevents loss of AMPA receptor 
responsitivity. Injection of a spinophilin-based peptide, which prevents




                                              Na''       )ephosphorylated                                                      Chi         Na'I         Phosphorylated 
                                                         Inactivated Slate                                           DA                                 Activated. Stale

                        AMPA                                  Spinophilin                    —910`                                                           Spinophilin 
                      Channel                                   P111                                                                                                 PPL
                                                                                                                                            *      f
                                                                                                                                           •
                                                                                                                                           Pl A e,           DARPP-32



Figure 7. Regulation of AMPA-type glutamate receptors by DARPP-32 and spinophilin.
     Model illustrates how regulation of PP-1 could account for the ability of DARPP-32 and 
spinophilin to control AMPA channels. (Left) Spinophilin, by binding to an unidentified inter- 
mediate protein (not shown), localizes PP-I in the vicinity of the AMPA channel. Under basal 
conditions, the PP-I /spinophilin complex maintains the AMPA channel in a dephosphorylated, 
low-activity state. (Right) Following DI receptor stimulation, AMPA channel phosphorylation is 
increased due both to direct PKA phosphorylation and to PKA/phospho-DARPP-32-mediated in- 
hibition of PP-I. This synergistic increase in pbosphorylation stimulates AMPA channel activity. 
The kinase anchoring protein (AKAP) believed to localize PEA in the vicinity of the AMPA re- 
ceptor (reference 22) is not shown. (Modified from Greengard el at, reference 9).

