152

ENDOTHELIUM-DERIVED RELAXING FACTOR: 
DISCOVERY, EARLY STUDIES, AND 
IDENTIFICATION AS NITRIC OXIDE

Nobel Lecture, December 8, 1998 
by
ROBERT F. FURCHGOTT
Department of Pharmacology, State University of New York, Health Science 
Center at Brooklyn, Brooklyn, NY 11203, USA


AN ACCIDENTAL FINDING
In a paper published forty-five years ago, in which I introduced the helical 
strip of the rabbit aorta as a useful preparation for quantitative pharmacologi- 
cal studies on vasoactive drugs and drug-receptor interactions, I reported on 
the responses of this preparation to a number of catecholamines, sodium 
nitrite, histamine and acetylcholine (ACh). One somewhat surprising finding 
(Furchgott and Bhadrakom, 1953) was that ACh, well recognized as a very 
potent vasodilator in whole animal and perfused organ studies, elicited no 
relaxation but only contraction of the aortic strip, whether or not the strip 
was tested at rest or precontracted with a vasocontrictor like norepinephrine. 
Somewhat later, we used ACh as the contracting agent when determining the 
relative potencies of norepinephrine, epinephrine and isoproterenol as 
relaxing agents acting via /3-adrenoceptors on helical strips in which a-adre- 
noceptors had been irreversibly blocked by pretreatment with dibenamine 
(Furchgott, 1954). The relative potencies of these catecholamines as relax- 
ants (approximately 1:50:200) indicated a 02-type adrenoceptor.
 In the mid-1970s, in pharmacological studies on isolated strips of guinea- 
pig tracheal smooth muscle, we obtained evidence that the /3-adrenoceptors 
of that muscle, which according to dogma were pure 02 -type, frequently had 
a fairly high admixture of the 131 type with the /32-type. In view of this unex- 
pected finding, I decided that it would be well to reexamine the type of 13-re-  
ceptor in the smooth muscle of rabbit thoracic aorta. The plan was first to 
determine anew in a series of experiments the relative potencies of norepi- 
nephrine, epinephrine and isoproterenol in producing relaxation of prepa- 
rations of rabbit aorta after dibenamine pretreatment. To produce contrac- 
tion after the pretreatment, we planned to use a muscarinic agonist like 
carbachol or ACh, as in our earlier studies. However, in the very first experi-  
ment of this planned series in May 1978, my technician did not follow my di- 
rections correctly: early in the experiment before blocking the a-adrenergic 
receptors with dibenamine, he tested carbachol for its contracting activity be-  
fore rather than after (as prescribed in the directions) washout of a previous 
test dose of norepinephrine. The response to carbachol was not a contrac-

                      Robert F Furchgott              153


tion, but was a partial relaxation of the norepinephrine-induced contraction. 
ACh was then tested. It too produced relaxation of the aortic preparation pre- 
contracted with norepinephrine (Fig. 1). This was the first time that I had 
ever observed relaxation of rabbit aorta in response to muscarinic agonists 
over the many years that I had been using this blood vessel for in vitro 
studies.The unexpected relaxation of rabbit aorta in vitro by muscarinic 
agonists was very exciting, for it was an effect that was in accord with the 
potent vasodilating action of these agonists in vivo.





                 CCh -7 1

                      -6 5 I  I
                          -6  j -5
        1                   55
    N E -7 3








                                                -4
          'L 
 NE -7 3      5 MIN                       -6 5
Figure 1. Polygraph tracings from the first experiment in the author's laboratory in which the 
muscarinic agonists, carbachol (CCh) and acetylcholine (ACh), unexpectedly produced relaxa- 
tion of transverse rings of rabbit thoracic aorta. In this and all other experiments, unless other- 
wise noted, aortic preparations (rings or strips) were mounted in 20-m1 all-glass organ chambers 
containing Krebs-bicarbonate solutions aerated with 95%02-5%CO2, and kept at 37°. Tracings 
show changes in tension under isometric conditions. (For details of experimental procedures, 
see Furchgott and Zawadzki, 1980.) NE is norepinephrine. In this and all other figures unless 
otherwise noted, cumulative concentrations of drugs in organ chambers are expressed as log 
molar concentrations.


DISCOVERYAND EARLY STUDIES ON EDRF

Why had we failed to observe ACh-induced relaxation or aortic preparations 
in the past, and why did it now become manifest? A detailed account of our 
investigation of this matter has been published (Furchgott, 1993; 1996), so it 
will suffice here to outline briefly the sequence of findings. First, we were 
aware that the kind of preparation of rabbit thoracic aorta that we were now 
using was the transverse ring, rather than the helical strip which we had used 
in all of the earlier experiments with muscarinic agonists.
  Several experiments were therefore carried out in which we compared the 
responses to cumulative concentrations of carbachol or ACh on helical strips

154                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    Physiology or Medicine 1998



and transverse rings prepared from the same aorta. Only the rings responded 

with relaxation to these muscarinic agonists, while the strips responded with 

contraction (Fig. 2). After several weeks of work, we recognized that in any



     RING 
                                                               f --                                                                            1
                                                                                            CCh -81                                                                                                                                                                                  1.-----i \
                       NE -83                                                                                                                  -           73                                                    83 5                                      I           --43          1                                         W                                          '''--,---`------______ W                                                                                                             CCh -8.3 I -63 ,                               1 i                                                                              ..------/                  _43         1
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              -72                                                      '5.3




HELICAL                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               2G
STRIP
                                                                                                            CCh -8131                                      -73                                                        -453                        -53                           -412                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               5 MIN
                                   NE -8,13                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    CCh                                                      -73                           -83 I                          -5.3                                             -43

Figure 2. Comparison of responses to carbachol (CCh) of a transverse ring and a helical strip 
prepared from the same rabbit thoracic aorta. The ring (2.5-mm wide) was mounted on a pair of 
L-shaped hooks for attachment to the base of the organ chamber and to the force transducer. 
The strip, prepared by our standard method, had thread ties at each end for attachment. Only 
the ring, when precontracted with norepinephrine (NE), relaxed in response to low con- 
centrations of CCh. It was subsequently recognized that in our standard method of preparing 
strips,the endothelial cells were unintentionally rubbed off the intimal surface. (There is no re- 
laxation of the ring in response to CCh added after washout (W) of NE because such prepara- 
tions exhibit practically no active contractile tension in the absence of vasoconstrictor agents.) In 
this figure, concentrations of drugs are expressed as log of concentrations in g per ml. Re- 
produced with permission from Furchgott (1993).



kind of preparation (ring or strip), gentle rubbing of the intimal surface, 

whether intentionally or unintentionally (as had occurred, unbeknown to us, 

in our standard method of preparing helical strips), eliminated the relaxing 

response to Ach and other muscarinic agonists. Strips as well as rings gave ex- 

cellent relaxation when care was taken not to rub the intimal surface. That 

the loss of the relaxation response to ACh after intimal rubbing was the result 

of mechanical removal of the endothelial cells was clearly demonstrated with 

the use of a silver staining procedure to allow en face microscopy of the intimal 

surfaces. It was also demonstrated that complete removal of endothelial cells 

of the aorta by pre-incubation of the intimal surface with collagenase also 

resulted in a complete loss of the relaxation response to ACh.

                       Figure 3 is a slightly modified figure from the first full paper on the obliga- 

tory role of endothelial cells in the relaxation of arterial smooth muscle by 

ACh (Furchgott and Zawadzki, 1980). In that paper, we also reported that in 

addition to the thoracic aorta, a number of other arteries from the rabbit and 

various arteries from other species of laboratory animals also exhibited 

relaxation in response to ACh only if endothelial cells were present. 

Cyclooxygenase inhibitors did not interfere with the endothelium-dependent 

relaxation. One hypothesis to explain the obligatory role of endothelial cells 

was that ACh acting on a muscarinic receptor of these cells stimulates them to 

release a non-prostanoid substance that diffuses to and activates relaxation of

                 Robert F Furchgott       155


A   Unrubbed      RING        Rubbed
















C     Untreated     RING   Collagenase Treated

                            ACh 1-15-7 -6-5'5
                                 -6 5
NE -8          -6 -5 5 WNE -8
Figure 3. Recordings showing loss of relaxing response of rabbit aorta to ACh after complete 
removal of endothelial cells. In each panel, the recording on the left was made before removal 
and that on the right after removal of endothelial cells. The cells were removed from the ring in  
panel A by rubbing its intimal surface with a small wooden stick, from the transverse strip in 
panel B by rubbing its intimal surface on moistened filter paper, and from the ring in panel C by  
exposing its intimal surface to collagenase. After the procedure to remove endothelial cells, each 
preparation was allowed to re-equilibrate in its organ chamber for about one hour before being 
retested. Reproduced with permission from Furchgott et aL (1981).


the subjacent smooth muscle cells. Direct evidence for this hypothesis was ob- 
tained with the so-called "sandwich" procedure in which it was shown that a 
transverse strip of aorta freed of endothelial cells and therefore unable to 
relax on exposure to ACh, could be made to relax in response to ACh if it 
were remounted for recording with its endothelium-free intimal surface pla- 
ced against the endothelium-containing intimal surface of a longitudinal 
strip of aorta (Fig. 4). The ACh-induced relaxation of the transverse strip in 
the "sandwich" demonstrated that ACh stimulated the release of a diffusible 
relaxing substance (or substances) from the endothelial cells of the longi- 
tudinal strip (Furchgott and Zawadzki, 1980). The relaxing substance was 
later referred to as EDRF (for endothelium-derived relaxing factor) (Cherry 
et al., 1982).
 It should be noted here that although we had never observed relaxation of 
rabbit aortic preparations by ACh in my laboratory prior to our accidental 
finding in 1978, there had been occasional reports from other investigators of 
relaxation of isolated preparations of arteries in response to that agent. For 
example, Jellife (1962) had reported that a chain of thread-tied rings of rab- 
bit aorta precontracted with serotonin, relaxed in response to low concentra-

156                        Physiology' or Medicine 1998



     A. TRANSVERSE STRIP WITHOUT ENDOTHELIUM   B. LONGITUDINAL STRIP WITH ENDOTHELIUM

                 Om TEST)                                 (1st TEST)





                                        2G
                                            SHIN 


N E -a                                   NE-18    7.7 6.7         ACh  -7-6 -5 W




    C. "SANDWICH" OF TRANSVERSE STRIP WITHOUT D. TRANSVERSE STRIP REMOVED FROM STANDWICH
ENDOTHELIUM AND LONGITUDINAL STRIP WITH ENDOTHELIUM        {3rd TEST)


                                     2 
                                     ---Ad








  NE -7

Figure 4. 'Sandwich" experiment demonstrating release of a relaxing substance from endotheli- 
al cells in response to A(:11. A: On a transverse strip of rabbit aorta with endothelial cells removed 
by rubbing, ACh tailed to relax the NE-induced tone. B: On a longitudinal strip from the same 

aorta with endothelium present. NE and ACh produced only trivial changes in tension because 
of the orientation of the smooth muscle cells. C: On a "sandwich" made from the transverse strip 
without endothelium and the longitudinal strip with endothelium mounted together in clips 

with their entire intimal surfaces apposed. and allowed to re-equilibrate. ACh now produced re- 
laxation of the NE-induced tone. D: After removing the longitudinal strip with endothelium 

horn the endothelium-denuded transverse strip. the latter after re-equilibration, again gave no 
relaxation in response to ACh. In the diagrams of the vertical cross-sections of the preparations. 

Ad is adventitia; E is endothelial cell layer; M, and M,,, respectively, are medial layers of smooth 
muscle cells oriented vertically and horizontally. Reproduced with permission from Furchgott el

   (198l).







tions of ACh; and Vanhoutte (1974) and Todd (1974) had found that on a 

number of canine arteries prepared as strips, ACh elicited significant relaxa- 

tion of spontaneous or drug-induced contractions. After our findings on the 

obligatory role of endothelial cells in ACh-induced relaxation of arteries, it 

became apparent that these earlier examples of ACh-induced relaxation were 

dependent on the presence of endothelial cells in the preparations of the ar- 

teries being studied.

   It is of sonic interest that an unintentional removal of endothelial cells in 

another vascular preparation used in my laboratory may have prevented the 

discovery of endothelium-dependent vasodilation at an earlier date. That pre- 

paration was the perfused rabbit central ear artery which Odd Steinsland, 

while a graduate student in my laboratory in the early 1970s, used for investi- 

gating the inhibition by AGh and other muscarinic agonists of acirenergic 

neurotransmission by their action on prejunctional muscarinic inhibitory re- 

ceptors. He readily demonstrated that ACh was a potent inhibitor of neuro- 

transmission, as evidenced by its inhibition of both the release of norepine- 

phrine and the vasoconstriction in response to nerve stimulation (Steinsland 

ci al., 1973). To make sure that the inhibition of the vasoconstriction was on- 

ly due to inhibition of transmitter release, he tested whether infused ACh 

could inhibit vasoconstriction produced by infused norepinephrine, and

               Robert F Furchgott   157

found that it did not (Steinsland et al., 1973). About ten years later, after en- 
dothelium-dependent relaxation by ACh had been found in a large variety of 
arterial preparations, we were puzzled by the earlier finding that the perfused 
ear artery constricted with infused norepinephrine, had failed to show any 
vasodilation in response to ACh. Dr. Steinsland provided us with the answer. 
In his earlier work, he had not taken precautions to prevent air bubbles from 
entering the perfusion line and passing through the ear artery. When care 
was now taken to avoid the occurrence of bubbles in the perfusion stream 
through the artery, ACh elicited good vasodilation (relaxation) of norepi- 
nephrine-induced vasoconstriction (Furchgott et al., 1990b). Apparently, in 
the earlier work, the bubbles had mechanically removed the endothelial cells 
and we had been unaware of this action.

EARLY STUDIES ON AGENTS INDUCING AND INHIBITING 
ENDOTHELIUM-DEPENDENT RELAXATION
Within a few years after the discovery that ACh-induced relaxation of isolated 
arteries was endothelium-dependent, a number of other endothelium- 
dependent relaxing agents were identified in organ chamber experiments 
using rings or strips of blood vessels from a variety of species, including man. 
Among these were the calcium ionophore A23187, ATP and ADP, substance 
P, bradykinin, histamine, thrombin, serotonin and vasopressin. [For referen- 
ces to first reports on endothelium-dependent relaxation by these and other 
agents, see Furchgott and Vanhoutte (1989) and Furchgott (1990)]. The 
early finding that the calcium ionophore A23187 was a very potent endothe- 
lium-dependent relaxing agent on all vessels tested suggested a central role 
for calcium in the release, or synthesis and release, of EDRF by endothelium- 
dependent relaxing agents (Furchgott 1981).
  It was soon recognized in this early work that, depending on the agent, en- 
dothelium-dependent relaxation might be limited to certain species, or even 
to specific arteries from a given species. For example, whereas ACh relaxed by 
this mechanism practically all systemic arteries from all mammalian species 
tested, histamine, another potent vasodilator, produced endothelium-depen- 
dent relaxation of rat (van de Voorde and Leusen, 1983) but not of rabbit 
arteries (Furchgott, 1983). Another example was bradykinin, which gave en- 
dothelium-dependent relaxation of isolated canine and human arteries but 
not of rabbit or cat arteries (Cherry et al., 1982). As examples of vessel speci- 
ficity, it was found that noradrenaline activated endothelium-dependent re- 
laxation in isolated canine coronary arteries by acting on cc2-adrenoceptors of 
the endothelial cells, but failed to activate this kind of relaxation in canine 
systemic arteries (Cocks and Angus, 1983), and that serotonin activated en- 
dothelium-dependent relaxation in canine coronary arteries but not in 
canine systemic arteries (Cocks and Angus, 1983; Cohen et al., 1983).
  Among the conditions and agents which were found to inhibit endothe- 
lium-dependent relaxation of arteries in the early organ chamber experi- 
ments were anoxia and some agents that were recognized as inhibitors in the

158	
Physiology or Medicine 1998
metabolic pathway of arachidonic acid (AA) from phospholipids through li- 
poxygenase (Furchgott and Zawadzki, 1980; Furchgott et aL, 1981). Because it  
had already been reported that in certain smooth muscles there was a positive  
relationship between an increase in cyclic guanosine monophosphate  
(cGMP) and relaxation (Katsuki and Murad, 1977; Bohme et al., 1978; Murad  
et al., 1978, 1979) and that guanylate cyclase (G-cyclase) was markedly stimu- 
lated by hydroperoxides of AA (Hidaka and Asano, 1977; Goldberg et al.,  
1978), I speculated that (1) EDRF is either a short-lived hydroperoxide or  
free radical arising as an intermediate product in the oxidation of liberated  
AA by the lipoxygenase pathway, and (2) that EDRF stimulates the G-cyclase  
of the vascular smooth muscle, causing an increase in cGMP which then  
somehow activates relaxation (Furchgott et al., 1981). As it turned out, this  
early speculation about the nature of EDRF was wrong, but that about the  
role of cGMP proved to be right.
CYCLIC GMP AS A MEDIATOR FOR EDRF AND NITROVASODILATORS
The speculation that EDRF released by ACh would stimulate an increase in  
cGMP was soon proven correct in a number of independent studies — e.g.,  
Rapoport and Murad (1983) using rat aorta, Diamond and Chu (1983) and  
Furchgott et al. (1984) using rabbit aorta, Holzmann (1982) using bovine  
coronary artery, and Ignarro et al. (1984) using bovine pulmonary artery. All  
of these investigators showed that a rise in cGMP accompanied the ACh-in- 
duced relaxation of the blood vessel, consistent with the proposal that the in- 
crease in cGMP in the muscle has a causal role in the relaxation (Fig. 5).
1.0
0_8
100
a)
O
`6.	
0.6
E
6
E 0.4
a.
0.2
50
% RELAXATION (•)
10 20 30	
60	
90	
120	
180
TIME IN SECONDS
Figure 5. Time course of changes of cyclic GMP (cGMP) and of relaxation of endothelium-con- 
taining rings of rabbit thoracic aorta after addition of ACh. Norepinephrine (0.1 ,uM) was first  
added to produce a steady contraction. ACh (1 AM) was then added, and the tissue was instant- 
ly frozen in liquid nitrogen after the desired period of exposure to ACh. The level of cyclic AMP  
(not shown) did not change significantly during the endothelium-dependent relaxation.  
Reproduced with permission from Furchgott et al. (1984).

              Robert F Furchgott  159

Endothelium-dependent relaxation of rat aorta by A23187 and by histamine 
(Rapoport and Murad, 1983) and of rabbit aorta by A23187 (Furchgott et al., 
1984) was also accompanied by a rise in cGMP.
 It is well to stress at this point that Murad and coworkers (see Murad et al.,  
1978 and 1979 for reviews) had previously found that nitric oxide (NO) is a 
very potent stimulus of G-cyclase, and had proposed that a number of agents 
(e.g. glyceryl trinitrate, nitroprusside, azide) which they and others had 
found to increase cGMP and produce relaxation of certain non-vascular 
smooth muscle preparations, do so by generating NO as the proximal acti- 
vator of G-cyclase. Also, Ignarro and his coworkers (Gruetter et al., 1979) had  
found that the relaxation of a vascular preparation (bovine coronary artery) 
by NO as well as by nitroprusside was associated with an increase in cGMP. 
However, despite these early findings with NO, none of the investigators who 
several years later showed that endothelium-dependent relaxation of arteries 
in organ chamber experiments was also correlated with an increase in cGMP 
(see above) hypothesized that EDRF might be the free radical NO. Certain 
key findings had yet to be made to foster this novel proposal.

FURTHER STUDIES ON EDRF, INCLUDING THOSE WITH PERFUSION- 
BIOASSAY PROCEDURES
Hemoglobin and Methylene Blue as Inhibitors
Two agents that became widely used as inhibitors of endothelium-dependent 
relaxation were hemoglobin (Hb) and methylene blue (MB). Hb had been 
found by Murad et al. (1978) to inhibit guanylate cyclase in cellular extracts,  
and by workers at Glasgow University (Bowman et al., 1982) to inhibit the re- 
laxation of strips of bovine retractor penis (BRP) muscle in response either to  
nonadrenergic, noncholinergic (NANC) nerve stimulation or to an acid-ac- 
tivated extract of that tissue. Gruetter et al. (1981) had reported that methe-  
moglobin (metHb) interfered with NO-induced increases in vascular cGMP. 
In our laboratory, work with Hb began in 1983 when William Martin, who 
had studied the properties of extracts of the BRP muscle while a graduate 
student at Glasgow University (Gillespie et al., 1981; Bowman et al., 1981), 
came to my laboratory as a postdoctoral fellow (see below). It was soon found 
that Hb was an extremely potent and fast acting inhibitor of endothelium- 
dependent relaxation and of the associated rise in cGMP induced by ACh, 
A23187 and other agents on rabbit and rat aorta (Furchgott et al., 1984; 
Martin et al., 1985a,1986a). Myoglobin was as effective as Hb, but metHb 
only inhibited very weakly (Martin et al., 1985b) (Fig. 6).
 The degree of potentiation by Hb of contractions of arterial rings by vaso- 
constrictors such as phenylephrine also provided a measure of the relaxing 
activity of basally released EDRF (Martin et al., 1986a). Using this measure, 
the relaxing activity of basally released EDRF in the case of rings of rat aorta 
appeared to be considerably greater than in the case of rings of rabbit aorta. 
With rings from both species, addition of phosphodiesterase inhibitors (such 
as zaprinast and IBMX) produced relaxation associated with increases in

160                                               Physiology or Medicine 1998


   A                                                                                B




                           A23I87 -8s         -8.22
                                                           MB -5

 NE -7

                2G      5 MIN                   ACh      MB -5                      NE -7.5I           ACh -6    MetH8 -7  /    -61         yy

 NE -7
Figure 6. Examples of inhibition by methylene blue (MB) and by hemoglobin (Hb) of endothe- 
lium-dependent relaxation in rings of rabbit aorta. A. Addition of MB (10 bd1/1) rapidly and com- 
pletely inhibited the ongoing relaxation produced by the addition of ACh and that produced by 
addition of the calcium ionophore A23187. B. Addition of Hb at 1 /./M rapidly and almost com- 
pletely inhibited the relaxation produced by addition of ACh; however, methemoglobin 
(MetHb) at the same concentration inhibited ACh-induced relaxation only to a very small 
extent.


cGMP (Martin et al., 1986b). The responses to these inhibitors of the enzymes 
which hydrolyze cGMP to GMP were more pronounced in the case of rat 
aorta than in rabbit aorta, consistent with a higher basal release of EDRF and 
higher basal stimulation of G-cyclase in the former. The relaxation of endo- 
thelium-containing rings of both species produced by phosphodiesterase in- 
hibitors could be completely blocked by Hb.
     It was originally proposed that Hb inhibits relaxation and the rise in cGMP 
by binding EDRF as it diffuses from the endothelial cells, thus preventing it 
from reaching and activating the G-cyclase in the muscle cells (Martin et al., 
1985a). However, after the identification of EDRF as NO, it became apparent 
that the scavenging of EDRF by Hb under the usual aerobic conditions was 
the result of the very rapid reaction of Hb02 with NO to form NO3- and 
metHb, as first reported by Doyle and Hoekstra (1981).
     MB had first been shown by Gruetter et al. (1981) to inhibit stimulation of 
G-cyclase by nitrovasodilators in cell-free systems and to inhibit both the 
relaxation and increase in cGMP elicited by these agents in vascular smooth 
muscle. Subsequently, MB was found to inhibit both the endothelium-depen- 
dent relaxation and accompanying increase in cGMP produced by ACh in 
bovine arteries (Holzman, 1982; Ignarro et al., 1984) and by ACh and A23187 
in rabbit aorta (Furchgott et al., 1984; Martin et al., 1985a). Holzman (1982) 
and Ignarro et al. (1984) concluded that the inhibition of relaxation was the 
result of the inhibition of G-cyclase by the MB. On the other hand, the pres- 
ent author and his coworkers, although agreeing that such enzyme inhi- 
bition accounted for the sustained inhibition by MB developed during pro- 
longed exposure of the rabbit aorta, proposed that the extremely fast 
inhibition of endothelium-dependent relaxation immediately after addition

               Robert F. Furchgott  161

of MB to an organ chamber (as in Fig. 6) resulted from some more direct in- 
activation of EDRF by the MB (Furchgott et al., 1984; Martin et al., 1985a). It 
now appears that this more direct inactivation is due to superoxide anions, 
generated by reactions of the MB in the tissue (also see Wolin et al., 1990).

Results with Perfusion-Bioassay Procedures
For more direct studies on the properties of EDRF than were possible in 
organ chamber experiments, perfusion-bioassay procedures were developed. 
These procedures, although first developed in laboratories other than my 
own, should be considered here, because they produced results which con- 
tributed much to the identification of EDRF. In such procedures, endothelial 
cells are upstream in the perfusion (or superfusion) cascade and an endo- 
thelium-denuded arterial preparation (usually a ring or one or more strips) 
whose contractile state is monitored, is downstream to bioassay EDRF in the 
perfusion fluid. In some procedures, the endothelial cells upstream were 
native cells on the luminal surface of a perfused artery (e.g. Forstermann et 
al., 1984, Griffith et al., 1984, Rubanyi et al., 1985, Khan and Furchgott, 1987); 
in other procedures, they were cultured cells (usually from bovine or porcine 
aortas) on the surface of microcarrier beads contained in a perfused column 
(e.g. Cocks et al., 1985, Gryglewski et al., 1986).
  Perfusion-bioassay procedures allowed one to determine clearly whether 
an inhibitor of endothelium-dependent relaxation interfered with the syn- 
thesis/release of EDRF or inactivated the EDRF after its release. In addition, 
by altering the transit time of the perfusate between the endothelial cells and 
the bioassay preparation, it was possible to study the rate of decay of EDRF. 
Surprisingly, estimated half-life values for EDRF ranged from as low as 4-6 s to 
as high as 50 s depending on the biological preparations and the experimen- 
tal conditions. The likely explanation of these discrepant values came with 
the important finding that superoxide dismutase (SOD) markedly stabilizes 
EDRF released from either endothelial cells on arteries (Rubanyi and Van- 
houtte 1986) or cultured endothelial cells on microcarrier beads (Gryglewski 
et al., 1986), clearly showing that the superoxide anion (02) very rapidly in- 
activates EDRF. Thus, the marked differences in half-life of EDRF reported 
from different laboratories could largely be attributed to differences in con- 
centrations of 02 in the perfusion fluid leaving the endothelial cells under 
the different experimental conditions used. Subsequently, Moncada et al. 
(1986) were able to show with their perfusion-bioassay procedure that inhibi- 
tion of endothelium-dependent relaxation by certain reducing agents (e.g. 
hydroquinone, phenidone and pyrogallol) originally demonstrated in organ 
chamber experiments, was principally the result of inactivation of EDRF by 
02 formed in a single-electron oxidation of the reducing agent by 02.
  Development of perfusion-bioassay procedures also led to the important 
finding that increases in shear stress on endothelial cells of the perfused 
artery with increases in rate of flow of the perfusion fluid resulted in in- 
creases in the rate of release of EDRF (e.g. Holtz et al., 1984; Rubanyi et al., 
1986). Increase in flow through arteries both in situ (Holtz et al. 1984; Kaiser

162         Physiology or Medicine 1998

and Sparks 1986; Pohl et al., 1986) and in vitro produced vasodilation that 
could not be blocked by inhibitors of cyclooxygenase but was abolished by 
removal of the endothelium. These findings concerning increased EDRF 
release with increased shear stress were important for they provided evidence 
that EDRF has a continuous physiological role in the control of regional 
blood flow and regulation of blood pressure.

FINDINGS THAT LED TO THE IDENTIFICATION OF EDRF AS NO
While Billy Martin was working in my laboratory (1983-1985), I became in- 
terested in the work that he and others had done in John Gillespie's labora- 
tory in Glasgow in trying to identify the neurotransmitter released from 
NANC (non-adrenergic, non-cholinergic) nerves that elicit relaxation of 
bovine retractor penis (BRP) muscle and certain other smooth muscle prep- 
arations. I learned that both relaxation produced by NANC nerve stimulation 
and relaxation produced by a partly purified extract made by Martin from the 
BRP muscle (referred to as BRP inhibitory factor or BRPIF) were both in- 
hibited by Hb (Bowman et al., 1982) and were both associated with increases 
in cGMP in the muscle (Bowman and Drummond, 1984). One important as- 
pect of Martin's work with BRPIF extract was that it had to be acidified for a 
short period prior to testing in order for it to have a relaxing effect on 
smooth muscle preparations of retractor penis and arteries in organ baths 
(Gillespie et al., 1981). Once activated by acidification, the BRPIF extract 
gave good relaxations of the smooth muscle preparations, but the relaxations 
were transient, lasting no more than a few minutes.
 As discussed in the paper that I presented at a symposium in Rochester, 
MN, in July, 1986 (Furchgott, 1988), I was struck by the similarities of the 
transient relaxations produced by the acid-activated BRPIF extract of Martin 
and the transient relaxations of rabbit aorta produced by acidified solutions 
of sodium nitrite (NaNO2). That acidified, but not neutral solutions of 
NaNO2, produce strong transient relaxations of rabbit aorta had been found 
about fifteen years earlier in my laboratory when a new postdoctoral fellow, 
assigned to obtain cumulative dose-response curves for NaNO2, accidentally 
made his standard solutions of that salt with acidified diluting fluid (used in 
my laboratory for making stabile standard solutions of catecholamines) 
rather than with neutral diluting fluid (Fig. 7). At that time, I became aware 
that the HNO2 (pKa of 3.2) produced by acidification of NaNO2 solutions im- 
mediately generates low concentrations of NO and NO2 as a result of a rever- 
sible dismutation.
          NO2 + H+     HNO2
        2HNO2 4.1 ■ NO + NO2 + H2O
However, when a solution of acidified nitrite is added to the oxygenated, well- 
buffered physiological salt solution used in our organ chambers, any NO 
present will be removed very rapidly — thus accounting for the transiency of 
the relaxation of the aortic rings receiving acidified nitrite.

                                          Robert F Furchgott                                         163












                                                                                     2g

ACIDIFIED                                                                                      5min




 PEw -7 22
Figure 7. Comparison of the relaxing effects of cumulative additions of neutral and acidified 
solutions of sodium nitrite on rings of rabbit aorta. In this typical experiment, two rings from the 
same aorta after contraction with phenylephrine (PE), were exposed, respectively, to additions of 
NaNO2 diluted with neutral physiological saline and to additions of NaNO2 diluted with the 
saline acidified with 11 mM HO. The concentrations shown are the final nitrite concentrations 
(log molar) in the organ chambers. Note the striking transient relaxations in the case of the 
acidified nitrite solutions. The rings in this experiment were denuded of endothelial cells, but re- 
sults were essentially the same when endothelial cells were present. Reproduced with permission 
from Furchgott (1988).



In the spring of 1986, recalling the much earlier accidental finding in my 
laboratory with acidified sodium nitrite solutions, I began to consider the pos- 
sibility that Martin's acid-activatable BRPIF was inorganic nitrite. An en- 
couraging early finding was that the degree of transient relaxation as a func- 
tion of pH of the added NaNO2 solution in the case of rabbit aorta was similar 
to that found by Martin for his added extract in the case of the BRP — maxi- 
mal transient relaxation at a pH of 2 or lower, and approximately half-maxi- 
mal at a pH of 3.
   By the time I had begun to use acidified nitrite solutions as a source of NO 
in experiments with rabbit aorta in 1986, I had also become aware of the re- 
cent findings by Gryglewski, Palmer and Moncada (1986) and by Rubanyi 
and Vanhoutte (1986) demonstrating that the superoxide anion (02) rapidly 
inactivates EDRF and that superoxide dismutase (SOD) protects against this 
inactivation. Assuming that the free radical NO might rapidly react with the 
free radical 02, to form inactive NO3, I began to speculate on the possibility 
that EDRF is NO. [Later, it was pointed out by Beckman et al. (1990) that the 
immediate product of the reaction between NO and Oi is peroxynitrite 
(oNocr), which is protonated to HONOO (pKa = 6.8), which decays within 
seconds at physiological pH.]
   My speculation in the spring of 1986 that EDRF might be NO led to a large 
number of experiments on rabbit aorta, carried out with the assistance of D. 
Jothianandan and M.T. Khan, comparing the characteristics of relaxation by

164                                                                                                     Physiology or Medicine 1998



NO (present in acidified solutions of NaNO2) with the characteristics of 

relaxation by EDRF (released by ACh). It was found that relaxation by NO 

like that produced by EDRF was strongly inhibited by Hb, strongly inhibited 

by MB, strongly inhibited by superoxide generators (e.g., hydroquinone, phe- 

nidone, ferrous sulfate), and potentiated by SOD when superoxide was limit- 

ing the degree of relaxation (Fig. 8). It was already known that relaxation of



SOD 25 U/ml present
                                          NO2- -7                                   -6.5                               -I                              -5.5                                                     -5                                               -4.5         /

                   Control 
                                                                I                               I
                                          NO2-7                                     -6.5                               -6                              -5.5                                                     -5                                               -4.5         I
               FeSO4
            3X 104re.                 ..
               present                                          I                                                                                                     l                                                r---                                                     IV----
                                          NO2 -7                                    -6.5                               -     16                        -5.5                                                     -5                                                 -4.5
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      -                    -     -     -      -     -     -     -

Figure 8. Transient relaxations of endothelium-free rings of rabbit aorta by nitric oxide present 
in acidified solutions (pH 2) of NaNO2, potentiation of the relaxation by superoxide dismutase 
(SOD), and inhibition by FeSO4 (a superoxide generator). Three matched rings from one aorta 
were contracted above basal tone (dashed line) with phenylephrine. SOD and FeSO4 were added 
about five min before first additions of the acidified nitrite. Reproduced with permission from 
Furchgott (1988).





vascular smooth muscle by NO, like that by EDRF, is accompanied by an in- 

crease in cGMP. On finding the characteristics of NO and EDRF so similar, I 

had no hesitancy in proposing in the paper which I delivered at the July, 

1986, symposium that EDRF is NO (Furchgott, 1988). [Shortly after the sym- 

posium, we began using solutions of NO gas rather than acidified nitrite as a 

source of NO in our experiments and obtained identical results (Fig. 9).]

         In my symposium presentation, I also proposed that the acid-activatable in- 

hibitory factor in the BRP extract of Martin and Gillespie is inorganic nitrite, 

and that the possibility had to be considered that the neurotransmitter of 

NANC nerves might also be NO (Furchgott, 1988).

         At the same symposium at which I proposed that EDRF is NO, Ignarro, on 

the basis of studies in his laboratory on isolated bovine pulmonary arteries, 

independently made the same proposal (Ignarro et al., 1988). (Unfortunately, 

the papers presented at that symposium were delayed in publication until 

1988.) Soon after the 1986 symposium, three laboratories utilized perfusion- 

bioassay procedures to compare more accurately the biological and chemical 

characteristics of EDRF and NO. Ignarro and coworkers using bovine pulmo- 

nary vessels (Ignarro et al. 1987), Moncada and coworkers using cultured por- 

cine aortic endothelial cells (Palmer et al., 1987), and Khan and myself using 

rabbit aorta (Khan and Furchgott, 1987) as a source of EDRF, all found 

EDRF released upstream and NO infused upstream to have similar rates of 

decay, similar susceptibility to inhibitors like Hb and superoxide generators, 

similar stabilization by SOD, etc. In addition, Ignarro's laboratory presented

                   Robert F Furchgott        165










CONTROL 2p1 5p1 10p1     2p1 5p1
       NO5               NO       10p1





                                           5mln






  SOD 
30 U//ML









Figure 9. Similarity of the relaxing effects of a solution of acidified sodium nitrite and a solution 

of nitric oxide gas on rings of rabbit aorta in the absence and presence of superoxide dismutase 

(SOD). The acidified nitrite was 2.5 mM at pH 2.0. The NO solution was 15 t.t.M. (See Furchgott 

et al. (1990a) for method for making solutions of NO.) Additions were to 20 ml of Krebs solution 

in each organ chamber, so that 2 i.t1 of the NO solution gave an initial concentration of 1.5 nM. 

Both rings were precontracted with phenylephrine. The potentiation by SOD of the transient 

relaxations produced by the NO in the acidified nitrite and in the NO solution indicates that 

there was a considerable endogenous production of the superoxide anion 02 in the organ 

chambers.











spectroscopic evidence that the product of the reaction of released EDRF and 


Hb was the same as that of NO and Hb, and Moncada's laboratory showed 


that the amount of NO released by bradykinin (as determined by a chemilu- 


minescence assay) could fully account for the relaxation of the bioassay strip 


by the EDRF released by the peptide. A year late, Moncada and coworkers 


made the major finding that the source of endothelial NO was a guanidinium 


nitrogen of L-arginine and that the enzyme responsible for its formation was 


an oxygenase (now called endothelial nitric oxide synthase or eNOS) 


(Palmer et al., 1988). These findings marked the beginning of a major world- 


wide expansion of research on the role of NO in vascular physiology and 


pathophysiology.


  Despite the evidence for the identity of EDRF and NO, some results obtain- 


ed in various laboratories in the late 1980s did not appear to be completely 


consistent with that conclusion. [For a review of these apparent or real in- 


consistencies, see Furchgott et al., 1990a.] Nevertheless, as of now, it has be- 


come generally accepted that EDRF is either NO, or some adduct that readi- 


ly releases NO, or perhaps a mixture of NO and some adduct of NO. This 


does not preclude a contribution to endothelium-dependent relaxation in 


some blood vessels from the release of a non-nitric oxide endothelium- 


derived hyperpolarizing factor (EDHF) along with EDRF (for review see 


Garland et al., 1995).







ACKNOWLEDGEMENT




The research in the author's laboratory referred to in this article was sup- 


ported by grants from the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute Of the 


National Institutes of Health.

166           Physiology or Medicine 1998

REFERENCES
Beckman, J.S., Beckman, T.W., Chen, J., Marshall, P.A. and Freeman, B.A. (1990) Apparent 
 hydroxyl radical production by peroxynitrite: implications for endothelial injury from 
 nitric oxide and superoxide. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 87, 1620-1624.
BOhme, E, Graf, H. and Schultz, G. (1978) Effects of sodium nitroprusside and other 
 smooth muscle relaxants on cyclic GMP formation in smooth muscle and platelets. Adv. 
 Cyclic Nucleotide Res. 9, 131-143.
Bowman, A., and Drummond, A.H. (1984) Cyclic GMP mediates neurogenic relaxation in 
 the bovine retractor penis muscle. Br. J. Pharmacol., 81, 665-674.
Bowman, A., Gillespie, J.S., and Martin, W. (1981) Actions on the cardiovascular system of 
 an inhibitory material extracted from the bovine retractor penis. Br. J Pharmacol. 72, 
 365-372.
Bowman, A., Gillespie, J.S., and Pollock, D. (1982) Oxyhaemoglobin blocks nonadrenergic 
 inhibition in the bovine retractor penis muscle. Eur. J. Pharmacol. 85, 221-224.
Cherry, P.D., Furchgott, R.F., Zawadzki, IV., and Jothianandan, D. (1982) The role of 
 endothelial cells in the relaxation of isolated arteries by bradykinin. Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. 
 79, 2106-2110.
Cocks, T.M. and Angus, J.A. (1983) Endothelium-dependent relaxation of coronary arte- 
 ries by noradrenaline and serotonin. Nature 305, 627-630.
Cocks, T.M., Angus, J.A., Campbell, J.H. and Campbell, G.R. (1985) Release and properties 
 of endothelium-derived relaxing factor (EDRF) from endothelial cells in culture. J. Cell 
 Physiol. 123, 310-320.
Cohen, R.A., Shepherd, J.T. and Vanhoutte, P.M. (1983) 5-Hydroxytryptamine can me- 
 diate endothelium-dependent relaxation of coronary arteries. Am. J. Physiol. 245, 
 H1077-1080.
Diamond, J. and Chu, E.B. (1983) Possible role for cyclic GMP in endothelium-dependent 
 relaxation of rabbit aorta by ACh. Comparison with nitroglycerin. Res. Comm. Chem. 
 Pathol. Pharmacol. 41, 369-381.
Doyle, M.P., and Hoekstra, J.W. (1981) Oxidation of nitrogen oxides by bound dioxygen in 
 hemoproteins. J. Inorg. Biochem. 14, 351-358.
Forstermann, U., Trogisch, G. and Busse, R. (1984) Species-dependent differences in the 
 value of endothelium-derived vascular relaxing factor. Eur. J. Pharmacol. 106, 639-643.
Furchgott, R.F. (1954) Dibenamine blockade in strips of rabbit aorta and its use in 
 differentiating receptors. j Pharmacol. Exp. Then 111, 265-284.
Furchgott, R.F. (1981) The requirement for endothelial cells in the relaxation of arteries by 
 ACh and some other vasodilators. Trends Pharmacol. Sci. 2, 173-176.
Furchgott, R.F. (1983) Role of endothelium in the responses of vascular smooth muscle. 
 Circ. Res. 53, 557-573.
Furchgott, R.F. (1988) Studies on relaxation of rabbit aorta by sodium nitrite: the basis for 
 the proposal that the acid-activatable inhibitory factor from retractor penis is inorganic 
 nitrite and the endothelium-derived relaxing factor is nitric oxide. In: Vasodilatation: Vas- 
 cular Smooth Muscle, Peptides, and Endothelium, edited by P.M. Vanhoutte, pp. 401-414, 
 Raven Press, New York.
Furchgott, R.F. (1990) The 1989 Ulf von Euler Lecture: Studies on endothelium-depen- 
 dent vasodilation and the endothelium-derived relaxing factor. Acta Physiol. Scand. 139, 
 257-270.
Furchgott, R.F. (1993) The discovery of endothelium-dependent relaxation. Circulation 
 87 (Suppl V) V3—V8.
Furchgott, R.F. (1996) The discovery of endothelium-derived relaxing factor and its impor- 
 tance in the identification of nitric oxide. J.A.M.A. 276, 1186-1188.
Furchgott, R.F. and Bhadrakom, S. (1953) Reactions of strips of rabbit aorta to epine- 
 phrine, isopropylarterenol, sodium nitrite and other drugs. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Therap., 
 108, 129-143.

